<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<preface id="tsvn-preface">
	<title>Preface</title>
	<simplesect>
		<graphic srccredit="TortoiseSVN Logo" fileref="images/tortoisesvn_logo_hor468x64.png"/>
	</simplesect>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_ABOUT"?>
	<simplesect>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>version control</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Version control is the art of managing changes to
			information. It has long been a critical tool for programmers,
			who typically spend their time making small changes to software
			and then undoing or checking some of those changes the next day.  
			Imagine a team of such developers working concurrently - and perhaps even
			simultaneously on the very same files! - and you can see why
			a good system is needed to <emphasis>manage the potential chaos</emphasis>.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-preface-about">
		<title>What is TortoiseSVN?</title>
		<para>
			TortoiseSVN is a free open-source Windows client for the
			<firstterm>Subversion</firstterm> version control system.
			That is, TortoiseSVN manages files and directories over time.
			Files are stored in a central <firstterm>repository</firstterm>.
			The repository is much like an ordinary file server, except that it
			remembers every change ever made to your files and directories.
			This allows you to recover older versions of your files and examine
			the history of how and when your data changed, and who changed it.
			This is why many people think of Subversion and version control
			systems in general as a sort of <quote>time machine</quote>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Some version control systems are also software configuration
			management (SCM) systems.  These systems are specifically
			tailored to manage trees of source code, and have many features
			that are specific to software development - such as natively
			understanding programming languages, or supplying tools for
			building software.  Subversion, however, is not one of these
			systems; it is a general system that can be used to manage
			<emphasis>any</emphasis> collection of files, including
			source code.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-preface-features">
		<title>TortoiseSVN's Features</title>
		<para>
			What makes TortoiseSVN such a good Subversion client?
			Here's a short list of features.
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Shell integration</term>
				<listitem>
					<indexterm>
						<primary>Windows shell</primary>
					</indexterm>
					<indexterm>
						<primary>explorer</primary>
					</indexterm>
					<para>
						TortoiseSVN integrates seamlessly into the Windows shell
						(i.e. the explorer). This means you can keep working
						with the tools you're already familiar with. And you
						do not have to change into a different application
						each time you need the functions of version control.
					</para>
					<para>
						And you are not limited to using the Windows Explorer;
						TortoiseSVN's context menus work in many other file managers,
						and also in the File/Open dialog which is common to most
						standard Windows applications.
						You should, however, bear in mind that TortoiseSVN
						is intentionally developed as an extension for the Windows
						Explorer. Thus it is possible that in other applications
						the integration is not as complete and e.g. the icon
						overlays may not be shown.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Icon overlays</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The status of every versioned file and folder is
						indicated by small overlay icons. That way you can see
						right away what the status of your working copy is.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Graphical User Interface</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When you list the changes to a file or folder, you can click
						on a revision to see the comments for that commit. You can also
						see a list of changed files - just double click on a file to
						see exactly what changed.
					</para>
					<para>
						The commit dialog lists all the items that will be included
						in a commit, and each item has a checkbox so you can choose
						which items you want to include. Unversioned files can also be
						listed, in case you forgot to add that new file.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Easy access to Subversion commands</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						All Subversion commands are available from the explorer
						context menu. TortoiseSVN adds its own submenu there.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
			Since TortoiseSVN is a Subversion client, we would also like to show you
			some of the features of Subversion itself:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Directory versioning</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						CVS only tracks the history of individual files, but
						Subversion implements a <quote>virtual</quote>
						versioned filesystem that tracks changes to whole
						directory trees over time.
						Files <emphasis>and</emphasis> directories are
						versioned. As a result, there are real client-side
						<command>move</command> and <command>copy</command>
						commands that operate on files and directories.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Atomic commits</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						A commit either goes into the repository completely,
						or not at all.  This allows developers to construct and
						commit changes as logical chunks.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Versioned metadata</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Each file and directory has an invisible set of
						<quote>properties</quote> attached. You can invent and
						store any arbitrary key/value pairs you wish.
						Properties are versioned over time, just like file
						contents.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Choice of network layers</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Subversion has an abstracted notion of repository
						access, making it easy for people to implement new
						network mechanisms. Subversion's <quote>advanced</quote>
						network server is a module for the Apache web server,
						which speaks a variant of HTTP called WebDAV/DeltaV.
						This gives Subversion a big advantage in stability and
						interoperability, and provides various key features for
						free: authentication, authorization, wire compression,
						and repository browsing, for example. A smaller,
						standalone Subversion server process is also available.
						This server speaks a custom protocol which can be
						easily tunneled over ssh.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Consistent data handling</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Subversion expresses file differences using a binary
						differencing algorithm, which works identically on both
						text (human-readable) and binary (human-unreadable) files.
						Both types of files are stored equally compressed in the
						repository, and differences are transmitted in both
						directions across the network.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Efficient branching and tagging</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The cost of branching and tagging need not be
						proportional to the project size. Subversion creates
						branches and tags by simply copying the project, using
						a mechanism similar to a hard-link.
						Thus these operations take only a very small,
						constant amount of time, and very little space in the repository.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect1>
	<!-- =================================================================== -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-preface-source">
		<title>License</title>
		<para>
			TortoiseSVN is an Open Source project developed under the GNU
			General Public License (GPL). It is free to download and free to use,
			either personally or commercially, on any number of PCs.
		</para>
		<para>
			Although most people just download the installer, you also have full
			read access to the source code of this program.
			You can browse it on this link
			<ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/tortoisesvn/source/browse/">
				<citetitle>http://code.google.com/p/tortoisesvn/source/browse/</citetitle>
			</ulink>.
			The current development line is located under
			<filename>/trunk/</filename>,
			and the released versions are located under
			<filename>/tags/</filename>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- =================================================================== -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-preface-development">
		<title>Development</title>
		<para>
			Both TortoiseSVN and Subversion are developed by a community of
			people who are working on those projects. They come from different
			countries all over the world, working together to create great
			software.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-preface-history">
			<title>TortoiseSVN's History</title>
			<para>
				In 2002, Tim Kemp found that Subversion was a very good version
				control system, but it lacked a good GUI client. The idea for a
				Subversion client as a Windows shell integration was inspired by
				the similar client for CVS named TortoiseCVS.
				Tim studied the source code of TortoiseCVS and used it as a base for
				TortoiseSVN. He then started the project, registered the domain
				<literal>tortoisesvn.org</literal> and put the source code online.
			</para>
			<para>
				Around that time, Stefan K端ng was looking for a good and free version
				control system and found Subversion and the source for TortoiseSVN.
				Since TortoiseSVN was still not ready for use, he joined the project
				and started programming. He soon rewrote most of the existing code and
				started adding commands and features, up to a point where nothing of
				the original code remained.
			</para>
			<para>
				As Subversion became more stable it attracted more and more users
				who also started using TortoiseSVN as their Subversion client.
				The user base grew quickly (and is still growing every day).
				That's when L端bbe Onken offered to help out with some nice icons
				and a logo for TortoiseSVN. He now takes care of the website
				and manages the many translations.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-preface-acknowledgements">
			<title>Acknowledgments</title>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Tim Kemp</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for founding the TortoiseSVN project
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Stefan K端ng</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for the hard work to get TortoiseSVN to what it is now,
							and his leadership of the project
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>L端bbe Onken</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for the beautiful icons, logo, bug hunting, translating and
							managing the translations
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Simon Large</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for maintaining the documentation
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Stefan Fuhrmann</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for the log cache and revision graph
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>The Subversion Book</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for the great introduction to Subversion and its
							chapter 2 which we copied here
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>The Tigris Style project</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for some of the styles which are reused in this documentation
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Our Contributors</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for the patches, bug reports and new ideas, and for
							helping others by answering questions on our mailing list
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Our Donators</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							for many hours of joy with the music they sent us
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<!-- =================================================================== -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-preface-readingguide">
		<title>Reading Guide</title>
		<para>
			This book is written for computer-literate folk who want to use
			Subversion to manage their data, but prefer to use a GUI client rather
			than a command line client. TortoiseSVN is a windows shell extension
			and it is assumed that the user is familiar with the windows
			explorer and how to use it.
		</para>
		<para>
			This <xref linkend="tsvn-preface"/> explains what TortoiseSVN is,
			a little about the TortoiseSVN project and the community of people who
			work on it, and the licensing conditions for using it and distributing it.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <xref linkend="tsvn-introduction"/> explains how to install TortoiseSVN
			on your PC, and how to start using it straight away.
		</para>
		<para>
			In <xref linkend="tsvn-basics"/> we give a short introduction
			to the <emphasis>Subversion</emphasis> revision control system which
			underlies TortoiseSVN. This is borrowed from the documentation for the
			Subversion project and explains the different approaches to version
			control, and how Subversion works.
		</para>
		<para>
			The chapter on <xref linkend="tsvn-repository"/> explains how to set up
			a local repository, which is useful for testing Subversion and TortoiseSVN
			using a single PC. It also explains a bit about repository administration
			which is also relevant to repositories located on a server.
			There is also a section here on how to setup a server if you need one.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <xref linkend="tsvn-dug"/> is the most important section as
			it explains all the main features of TortoiseSVN and how to use them.
			It takes the form of a tutorial, starting with checking out a working copy,
			modifying it, committing your changes, etc. It then progresses to more
			advanced topics.
		</para>
		<para>
			<xref linkend="tsvn-subwcrev"/> is a separate program included with TortoiseSVN
			which can extract the information from your working copy and write it into a
			file. This is useful for including build information in your projects.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <xref linkend="tsvn-howto"/> section answers some common questions
			about performing tasks which are not explicitly covered elsewhere.
		</para>
		<para>
			The section on <xref linkend="tsvn-automation"/> shows how the
			TortoiseSVN GUI dialogs can be called from the command line. This is useful
			for scripting where you still need user interaction.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <xref linkend="tsvn-cli"/> give a correlation
			between TortoiseSVN commands and their equivalents in the Subversion
			command line client <literal>svn.exe</literal>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-preface-terminology">
		<title>Terminology used in this document</title>
		<para>
			To make reading the docs easier, the names of all the screens and Menus 
			from TortoiseSVN are marked up in a different font.
			The <guilabel>Log Dialog</guilabel> for instance.
		</para>
		<para>
			A menu choice is indicated with an arrow.
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Show Log</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			means: select <emphasis>Show Log</emphasis> from the
			<emphasis>TortoiseSVN</emphasis> context menu.
		</para>
		<para>
			Where a local context menu appears within one of the TortoiseSVN
			dialogs, it is shown like this:
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Save As ...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
		</para>
		<para>
			User Interface Buttons are indicated like this:
			Press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to continue.
		</para>
		<para>
			User Actions are indicated using a bold font.
			<keycap>Alt+A</keycap>: press the
			<keycap>Alt</keycap>-Key on your keyboard and while holding it down
			press the <keycap>A</keycap>-Key as well.
			<action>Right-drag</action>: press the right mouse button and while
			holding it down <emphasis>drag</emphasis> the items to the new location.
		</para>
		<para>
			System output and keyboard input is indicated with a
			<literal>different</literal> font as well.
		</para>
		<important>
			<para>
				Important notes are marked with an icon.
			</para>
		</important>
		<tip>
			<para>
				Tips that make your life easier.
			</para>
		</tip>
		<caution>
			<para>
				Places where you have to be careful what you are doing.
			</para>
		</caution>
		<warning>
			<para>
				Where extreme care has to be taken. Data corruption or other
				nasty things may occur if these warnings are ignored.
			</para>
		</warning>
		<graphic srccredit="hide" fileref="images/background.png" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
	</sect1>
</preface>
