<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<appendix id="tsvn-lang" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Language Packs and Spell Checkers</title>
    <simplesect>
        <para>
            The standard installer has support only for English, but you
            can download separate language packs and spell check dictionaries
            separately after installation.
        </para>
    </simplesect>
    <sect1 id="tsvn-intro-install-lang">
        <title>Language Packs</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>language packs</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>translations</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
            The TortoiseSVN user interface has been translated into many
            different languages, so you may be able to download a language
            pack to suit your needs.
            You can find the language packs on our
            <ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.net/translation_status">
                <citetitle>translation status page</citetitle>
            </ulink>.
            And if there is no language pack available, why not join
            the team and submit your own translation ;-)
        </para>
        <para>
            Each language pack is packaged as a <literal>.msi</literal> installer.
            Just run the install program and follow the instructions.
            After the installation finishes, the translation will be available.
        </para>
        <para>
            The documentation has also been translated into several different
            languages. You can download translated manuals from the
            <ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.net/support">
                <citetitle>support page</citetitle>
            </ulink>
            on our website.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="tsvn-intro-install-spell">
        <title>Spellchecker</title>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>spellchecker</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
            <primary>dictionary</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
            TortoiseSVN includes a spell checker which allows you to check your
            commit log messages. This is especially useful if the project language
            is not your native language.
            The spell checker uses the same dictionary files as
            <ulink url="http://openoffice.org">
                <citetitle>OpenOffice</citetitle>
            </ulink>
            and
            <ulink url="http://mozilla.org">
                <citetitle>Mozilla</citetitle>
            </ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
            The installer automatically adds the US and UK English dictionaries.
            If you want other languages, the easiest option is simply to
            install one of TortoiseSVN's language packs. This will install
            the appropriate dictionary files as well as the TortoiseSVN local
            user interface.
            After the installation finishes, the dictionary will be available too.
        </para>
        <para>
            Or you can install the dictionaries yourself. If you have OpenOffice or
            Mozilla installed, you can copy those dictionaries, which are located
            in the installation folders for those applications.
            Otherwise, you need to download the required dictionary files from
            <ulink url="http://wiki.services.openoffice.org/wiki/Dictionaries">
                <citetitle>http://wiki.services.openoffice.org/wiki/Dictionaries</citetitle>
            </ulink>
        </para>
        <para>
            Once you have got the dictionary files, you
            probably need to rename them so that the filenames only have
            the locale chars in it.
            Example:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <filename>en_US.aff</filename>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <filename>en_US.dic</filename>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            Then just copy them to the <filename>bin</filename> sub-folder of
            the TortoiseSVN installation folder. Normally this will be
            <filename>C:\Program Files\TortoiseSVN\bin</filename>.
            If you don't want to litter the <filename>bin</filename> sub-folder,
            you can instead place your spell checker files in
            <filename>C:\Program Files\TortoiseSVN\Languages</filename>. If that folder isn't
            there, you have to create it first.
            The next time you start TortoiseSVN, the spell checker will be available.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you install multiple dictionaries, TortoiseSVN uses these rules
            to select which one to use.
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                    Check the <literal>tsvn:projectlanguage</literal> setting.
                    Refer to <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-propertypage"/> for information
                    about setting project properties.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                    If no project language is set, or that language is not
                    installed, try the language corresponding to the Windows locale.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                    If the exact Windows locale doesn't work, try the
                    <quote>Base</quote> language, e.g.
                    <literal>de_CH</literal> (Swiss-German) falls back to
                    <literal>de_DE</literal> (German).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                    If none of the above works, then the default language
                    is English, which is included with the standard installation.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
</appendix>
<!--
local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
