<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<chapter id="tsvn-monitor">
  <title>Commit Monitor</title>
  <simplesect>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>commit monitor</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>remote commits</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>monitoring projects</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The commit monitor is a helpful tool that monitors repositories and
      notifies you in case there are new commits.
    </para>
  </simplesect>
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="tsvn-commitmonitor-addprojects">
    <title>Adding projects to monitor</title>
    <para>
      If you first start the commit monitor, the tree view on the left side
      is empty. To add projects, click on the button at the top of the dialog
      named <guibutton>Add Project</guibutton>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <figure id="tsvn-commitmonitor-addprojects-dia-1">
        <title>The edit project dialog of the commit monitor</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/monitor-editproject.png"/>
      </figure>
      To add a project for monitoring, fill in the required information.
      The name of the project is not optional and must be filled in, all
      other information is optional.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the box for <literal>Path or Url</literal> is left empty, then
      a folder is added. This is useful to group monitored projects.
    </para>
    <para>
      The fields <literal>Username</literal> and <literal>Password</literal>
      should only be filled in if the repository does not provide anonymous
      read access, and only if the authentication is not stored by Subversion
      itself.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <literal>Monitor interval in minutes</literal> specifies the minutes
      to wait in between checks.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="tsvn-commitmonitor-maindialog">
    <title>Monitor dialog</title>
    <para>
      <figure id="tsvn-commitmonitor-maindialog-dia-1">
        <title>The main dialog of the commit monitor</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/monitor.png"/>
      </figure>
      The commit monitor shows all monitored projects on the left in a tree
      view. The projects can be moved around, for example one project can be moved
      below another project, making it a child/subproject.
    </para>
    <para>
      A click on a project shows all the log messages of that project on
      the right.
    </para>
    <para>
      Projects that have updates are shown in bold, with the number of
      new commits in brackets at the right. A click on a project marks
      it automatically as read.
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
