<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<chapter id="tsvn-quick-start">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    <simplesect>
        <para>
            This section is aimed at people who would like to find out what
            TortoiseSVN is all about and give it a test drive. It explains
            how to install TortoiseSVN and set up a local repository, and
            it walks you through the most commonly used operations.
        </para>
    </simplesect>
    <!-- ================================================================= -->
    <sect1 id="tsvn-qs-install">
        <title>Installing TortoiseSVN</title>
        <sect2>
            <title>System requirements</title>
            <para>
                TortoiseSVN runs on Windows XP or higher and is available in both
                32-bit and 64-bit flavours. If you are running 64-bit Windows you
                may want to install both versions.
            </para>
            <para>
                Support for Windows 98, Windows ME and Windows NT4 was dropped in
                version 1.2.0 and Windows 2000 support was dropped in 1.7.0.
                You can still download and install older versions if you need them.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Installation</title>
            <indexterm>
                <primary>install</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>
                TortoiseSVN comes with an easy to use installer. Double click on
                the installer file and follow the instructions. The installer
                will take care of the rest. Don't forget to reboot after installation.
            </para>
            <important>
                <para>
                    You need Administrator privileges to install TortoiseSVN.
                </para>
            </important>
            <para>
                Language packs are available which translate the TortoiseSVN
                user interface into many different languages. Please check
                <xref linkend="tsvn-lang"/> for more information on how to
                install these.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you encounter any problems during or after installing
                TortoiseSVN please refer to our online FAQ at
                <ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/faq.html">
                    <citetitle>http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/faq.html</citetitle>
                </ulink>
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <!-- ================================================================= -->
    <sect1 id="tsvn-qs-basics">
        <title>Basic Concepts</title>
        <para>
            Before we get stuck into working with some real files, it is important
            to get an overview of how subversion works and the terms that are used.
        </para>
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>The Repository</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Subversion uses a central database which contains all your
                        version-controlled files with their complete history. This
                        database is referred to as the <emphasis>repository</emphasis>.
                        The repository normally lives on a file server running the
                        Subversion server program, which supplies content to Subversion
                        clients (like TortoiseSVN) on request.
                        If you only back up one thing, back up your repository as it is
                        the definitive master copy of all your data.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Working Copy</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This is where you do the real work. Every developer has his
                        own working copy, sometimes known as a sandbox, on his local
                        PC. You can pull down the latest version from the repository,
                        work on it locally without affecting anyone else, then when
                        you are happy with the changes you made commit them back to
                        the repository.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        A Subversion working copy does not contain the history of
                        the project, but it does keep a copy of the files as they
                        exist in the repository before you started making changes.
                        This means that it is easy to check exactly what changes
                        you have made.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para>
            You also need to know where to find TortoiseSVN because there is not
            much to see from the Start Menu. This is because TortoiseSVN is a
            Shell extension, so first of all, start Windows Explorer. Right click
            on a folder in Explorer and you should see some new entries in the
            context menu like this:
            <figure id="tsvn-qs-basics-context">
                <title>The TortoiseSVN menu for unversioned folders</title>
                <graphic fileref="images/ContextMenuDirNoControl.png"/>
            </figure>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <!-- ================================================================= -->
    <sect1 id="tsvn-qs-guide">
        <title>Go for a Test Drive</title>
        <para>
            This section shows you how to try out some of the most commonly
            used features on a small test repository.
            Naturally it doesn't explain everything - this is just the Quick
            Start Guide after all. Once you are up and running you should take
            the time to read the rest of this user guide, which takes you
            through things in much more detail. It also explains more about
            setting up a proper Subversion server.
        </para>
        <sect2 id="tsvn-qs-repo">
            <title>Creating a Repository</title>
            <para>
                For a real project you will have a repository set up somewhere safe
                and a Subversion server to control it. For the purposes of this tutorial
                we are going to use Subversion's local repository feature which allows
                direct access to a repository created on your hard drive without needing
                a server at all.
            </para>
            <para>
                First create a new empty directory on your PC. It can go anywhere, but
                in this tutorial we are going to call it <filename>C:\svn_repos</filename>.
                Now right click on the new folder and from the context menu choose
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Create Repository here...</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
                The repository is then created inside the folder, ready for you to use.
            </para>
            <important>
                <para>
                    The local repository feature is very useful for test and evaluation
                    but unless you are working as a sole developer on one PC you should
                    always use a proper Subversion server. It is tempting in a small company
                    to avoid the work of setting up a server and just access your repository
                    on a network share. Don't ever do that. You will lose data. Read
                    <xref linkend="tsvn-repository-local-share"/> to find out why this is
                    a bad idea, and how to set up a server.
                </para>
            </important>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="tsvn-qs-import">
            <title>Importing a Project</title>
            <para>
                Now we have a repository, but it is completely empty at the moment.
                Let's assume I have a set of files in <filename>C:\Projects\Widget1</filename>
                that I would like to add. Navigate to the <filename>Widget1</filename> folder
                in Explorer and right click on it. Now select
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice> which brings up a dialog
                <figure id="tsvn-qs-import-dia">
                    <title>The Import dialog</title>
                    <graphic fileref="images/QS_import.png"/>
                </figure>
                A Subversion repository is referred to by URL, which allows us to specify
                a repository anywhere on the Internet. In this case we need to point to our
                own local repository which has a URL of <filename>file:///c:/svn_repos/Widget1</filename>
                Note that there are 3 slashes after <filename>file:</filename> and that
                the forward slashes are used throughout.
            </para>
            <para>
                The other important feature of this dialog is the <guilabel>Import Message</guilabel>
                box which allows you to enter a message describing what you are doing.
                When you come to look through your project history, these commit messages
                are a valuable guide to what changes have been made and why. In this case
                we can say something simple like <quote>Import the Widget1 project</quote>.
                Click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and the folder is added to your repository.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="tsvn-qs-wc">
            <title>Checking out a Working Copy</title>
            <para>
                Now that we have a project in our repository, we need to create a working
                copy to use for day-to-day work. Note that the act of importing a folder
                does not automatically turn that folder into a working copy. The Subversion
                term for creating a fresh working copy is <literal>Checkout</literal>.
                We are going to checkout the Widget1 folder of our repository into a
                development folder on the PC called <filename>C:\Projects\Widget1-Dev</filename>.
                Create that folder, then right click on it and select
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Checkout...</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
                Enter the URL to checkout, in this case <filename>file:///c:/svn_repos/Widget1</filename>
                and click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. Our development folder is then populated
                with files from the repository.
            </para>
            <para>
                You will notice that the appearance of this folder is different from our
                original folder. Every file has a green check mark in the bottom left corner.
                These are TortoiseSVN's status icons which are only present in a working copy.
                The green state indicates that the file is unchanged from the version in the
                repository.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="tsvn-qs-changes">
            <title>Making Changes</title>
            <para>
                Time to get to work. In the <filename>Widget1-Dev</filename> we start editing
                files - let's say we make changes to <filename>Widget1.c</filename> and
                <filename>ReadMe.txt</filename>. Notice that the icon overlays on these files
                have now changed to red, indicating that changes have been made locally.
            </para>
            <para>
                But what are the changes? Right click on one of the changed files and select
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Diff</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
                TortoiseSVN's file compare tool starts, showing you exactly which lines have
                changed.
                <figure id="tsvn-qs-diff-2pane">
                    <title>File Difference Viewer</title>
                    <graphic fileref="images/TMerge_TwoPane.png"/>
                </figure>
            </para>
            <para>
                OK, so we are happy with the changes, let's update the repository. This
                action is referred to as a <literal>Commit</literal> of the changes.
                Right click on the <filename>Widget1-Dev</filename> folder and select
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Commit</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
                The commit dialog lists the changed files, each with a checkbox.
                You might want to choose only a subset of those files, but in this
                case we are going to commit the changes to both files.
                Enter up a message to describe what the change is all about and
                click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The progress dialog shows the
                files being uploaded to the repository and you're done.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="tsvn-qs-add">
            <title>Adding More Files</title>
            <para>
                As the project develops you will need to add new files - let's say you add
                some new features in <filename>Extras.c</filename> and add a reference in
                the existing <filename>Makefile</filename>. Right click on the folder and
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Add</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
                The Add dialog now shows you all unversioned files and you can select
                which ones you want to add. Another way of adding files would be to
                right click on the file itself and select
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Add</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>.
            </para>
            <para>
                Now when you go to commit the folder, the new file shows up as
                <emphasis>Added</emphasis> and the existing file as
                <emphasis>Modified</emphasis>. Note that you can double click on
                the modified file to check exactly what changes were made.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="tsvn-qs-log">
            <title>Viewing the Project History</title>
            <para>
                One of the most useful features of TortoiseSVN is the Log dialog.
                This shows you a list of all the commits you made to a file or
                folder, and shows those detailed commit messages that you entered ;-)
                <figure id="tsvn-qs-log-image">
                    <title>The Log Dialog</title>
                    <graphic fileref="images/LogMessages.png"/>
                </figure>
                OK, so I cheated a little here and used a screenshot from the
                TortoiseSVN repository.
            </para>
            <para>
                The top pane shows a list of revisions committed along with the start
                of the commit message. If you select one of these revisions, the
                middle pane will show the full log message for that revision and the
                bottom pane will show a list of changed files and folders.
            </para>
            <para>
                Each of these panes has a context menu which provides you with lots
                more ways of using the information. In the bottom pane you can
                <action>double click</action> on a file to see exactly what changes
                were made in that revision. Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-showlog"/>
                to get the full story.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="tsvn-qs-revert">
            <title>Undoing Changes</title>
            <para>
                One feature of all revision control systems is that they let you undo
                changes that you made previously. As you would expect, TortoiseSVN
                makes this easy to access.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you want to get rid of changes that you have not yet committed
                and reset your file to the way it was before you started editing,
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Revert</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                is your friend. This discards your changes (to the Recycle bin, just
                in case) and reverts to the committed version you started with. If
                you want to get rid of just some of the changes, you can use
                TortoiseMerge to view the differences and selectively revert changed
                lines.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you want to undo the effects of a particular revision, start
                with the Log dialog and find the offending revision. Select
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
                    <guimenuitem>Revert changes from this revision</guimenuitem>
                </menuchoice>
                and those changes will be undone.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="tsvn-qs-end">
        <title>Moving On ...</title>
        <para>
            This guide has given you a very quick tour of some of TortoiseSVN's
            most important and useful features, but of course there is far
            more that we haven't covered. We strongly recommend that you
            take the time to read the rest of this manual, especially
            <xref linkend="tsvn-dug"/> which gives you a lot more detail
            on day-to-day operations.
        </para>
        <para>
            We have taken a lot of trouble to make sure that it is both informative
            and easy to read, but we recognise that there is a lot of it! Take your
            time and don't be afraid to try things out on a test repository as you
            go along. The best way to learn is by using it.
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
<!--
local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
