<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<chapter id="tsvn-projectmonitor">
  <title>Project Monitor</title>
  <simplesect>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>commit monitor</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>project monitor</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>remote commits</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>monitoring projects</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      The project monitor is a helpful tool that monitors repositories and
      notifies you in case there are new commits.
    </para>
  </simplesect>
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="tsvn-projectmonitor-addprojects">
    <title>Adding projects to monitor</title>
    <para>
      If you first start the project monitor, the tree view on the left side
      is empty. To add projects, click on the button at the top of the dialog
      named <guibutton>Add Project</guibutton>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <figure id="tsvn-projectmonitor-addprojects-dia-1">
        <title>The edit project dialog of the project monitor</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/monitor-editproject.png"/>
      </figure>
      To add a project for monitoring, fill in the required information.
      The name of the project is not optional and must be filled in, all
      other information is optional.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the box for <literal>Path or Url</literal> is left empty, then
      a folder is added. This is useful to group monitored projects.
    </para>
    <para>
      The fields <literal>Username</literal> and <literal>Password</literal>
      should only be filled in if the repository does not provide anonymous
      read access, and only if the authentication is not stored by Subversion
      itself. If you're accessing the monitored repository with TortoiseSVN
      or other svn clients and you've stored the authentication already,
      you should leave this empty: you won't have to edit those projects
      manually if the password changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      The <literal>Monitor interval in minutes</literal> specifies the minutes
      to wait in between checks.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="tsvn-projectmonitor-maindialog">
    <title>Monitor dialog</title>
    <para>
      <figure id="tsvn-projectmonitor-maindialog-dia-1">
        <title>The main dialog of the project monitor</title>
        <graphic fileref="images/monitor.png"/>
      </figure>
      The project monitor shows all monitored projects on the left in a tree
      view. The projects can be moved around, for example one project can be moved
      below another project, making it a child/subproject.
    </para>
    <para>
      A click on a project shows all the log messages of that project on
      the right.
    </para>
    <para>
      Projects that have updates are shown in bold, with the number of
      new commits in brackets at the right. A click on a project marks
      it automatically as read.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="tsvn-projectmonitor-maindialog-buttons">
      <title>Main operations</title>
      <para>
        The toolbar at the top of the dialog allows to configure
        and operate the project monitor.
      </para>
      <para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Check Now</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                While each monitored project is checked according to the
                interval that's set up, clicking this button will force
                a check of all projects immediately. Note that if there
                are updates, the notification won't show up until all
                projects have been checked.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Add Project</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Opens a new dialog to set up a new project for monitoring.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Edit</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Opens the configuration dialog for the selected project.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Remove</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Removes the selected project after a confirmation dialog
                is shown.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Mark all as read</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Marks all revisions in all projects as read. Note that if
                you select a project with unread revisions, those revisions
                are automatically marked as read when you select another
                project.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Update all</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Runs an <command>Update</command> on all monitored working
                copies. Projects that are monitored via an url are not
                updated, only those that are set up with a working copy
                path.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>Options</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Shows a dialog to configure the behavior of the project
                monitor.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
