<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix id="tsvn-faq" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude">
	<title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)</title>
	<simplesect>
		<para>
			This appendix contains an extract of the questions we are asked the most on
			the TortoiseSVN mailing list
			<email>dev@tortoisesvn.tigris.org</email>.
			We maintain an interactive online FAQ at 
			<ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.berlios.de/faq/">
				<citetitle>Berlios.de</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			which contains a lot more information.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-faq-installation">
		<title>Installation issues</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>install</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Many of these answers came from the
			<ulink url="http://www.tortoisecvs.org/faq.html">
				<citetitle>TortoiseCVS FAQ</citetitle>
			</ulink>
		</para>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-0">
			<title>The installer aborts with an error message</title>
			<para>
				If the msi installer shows you the error message <literal>The 
				installer was interrupted before TortoiseSVN could be installed. 
				You need to restart the installer to try again. Click Close 
				to exit</literal> then the user SYSTEM doesn't
				have read access to the folder where the msi file is located.
			</para>
			<para>
				Just move the msi file to another location, e.g.
				<filename>c:\</filename> and try again.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-0A">
			<title>
				I installed TortoiseSVN as Administrator.
				Now when I log in as me, it's not there
			</title>
			<para>
				When you started the installation you forgot to select the option
				to <literal>install for all users</literal> instead of 
				<literal>just for me</literal>. The easiest way to correct that
				is to uninstall, reboot, then reinstall.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-00">
			<title>
				When upgrading TortoiseSVN, do I have to uninstall the
				existing version first?
			</title>
			<para>
				No. You can just install the new version over the old one. The 
				installer will take care of uninstalling the old version first
				automatically.
			</para>
			<para>
				But you <emphasis>must</emphasis> reboot your computer after
				the installer finishes! Or at least you have to log off and log on
				again. If you don't, TortoiseSVN will crash!
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-1">
			<title>Why don't the icon overlays appear?</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>overlays</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							If you are using Windows 95 the icon overlays won't
							appear. You can try the instructions for Windows NT4
							below if you like, but it may still not work.
							Please note: We don't support Windows 95 at all -
							so there may be other issues if you're using that OS
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							If you are using Windows NT4, you need to install
							the IE4 shell or desktop extensions to get a more
							recent version of Explorer. 
							To do this install IE4, and choose Yes to 
							install the active desktop. Don't worry, you can 
							turn off the actual active desktop later by right 
							clicking on it. It's the new version of Explorer 
							that we are after.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							If you've already installed IE5, you must either: 
							<orderedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Uninstall IE5 and then install IE4 
										with desktop extensions, and then
										install IE5 again. What a palaver.
									</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Run IE5 setup with command line 
										switches to install the IE4 desktop
										(shell) extensions
									</para>
									<para>
										The command must be run from the folder
										that contains the
										<filename>ie5setup.exe</filename> file.
										If the browser appears unstable afterwards
										just run the IE5 repair function.
									</para>
									<para>
										For Win95:
<screen>
ie5setup.exe /c:"ie5wzd /e:IE4Shell WIN /I:Y"
</screen>
									</para>
									<para>
										For WinNT:
<screen>
ie5setup.exe /c:"ie5wzd /e:IE4Shell NTx86 /I:Y"
</screen>
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</orderedlist>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							For IE6:
						</para>
						<para>
							Run IE6 setup with command line switches to install 
							the IE4 desktop (shell) extensions. The same 
							caveats apply as for IE5. The command must be run from
							the folder that contains the
							<filename>ie6setup.exe</filename> file.
						</para>
						<para>
							For WinNT:
<screen>
ie6setup.exe /c:"ie6wzd /e:IE4Shell NTx86 /I:Y"
</screen>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The shortcut labelled
							<literal>Win NT Explorer</literal>
							on your start menu probably points to 
							<filename>C:\WINNT\explorer.scf</filename> and
							doesn't get the overlays. Create a new shortcut to
<screen>
%windir%\Explorer.exe /n, /e
</screen>
							and it may get the overlays.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							If you're using an IntelliPoint mouse 
							driver, and launching Explorer via a mouse click, 
							you need to upgrade from version 3 to version 3.2 or higher 
							of IntelliPoint. Strangely, launching Explorer from the 
							Start menu gives icons in this case, 
							but not when launched from the mouse.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-2">
			<title>I followed the instructions, but there are still no icons?!?</title>
			<para>
				You rebooted your PC off course?
				So after installing the shell extensions you now 
				have WinNT / Win95 and IE >= 5.5 installed?
			</para>
			<para>
				If you installed TortoiseSVN as a different user 
				under WinNT/Win2K/WinXP than you are using now, 
				do the following thing: Go to the settings of TSVN and 
				activate the icon overlays for at least the fixed 
				drives. The installer does this automatically for the 
				<emphasis>current</emphasis> user (can't do it for 
				other users...) but since you are using TSVN as a 
				different user than you installed it you need to 
				set this manually.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-2-1">
			<title>The overlay icons appear, but not all of them!</title>
			<para>
				This usually happens if you have other programs installed which
				use icon overlays like e.g. TortoiseCVS. The reason for this is
				that Windows only has 15 slots for icon overlays, and about three
				or four are used by Windows itself (e.g. for links, shared folders, ...).
				If all those slots are full then TortoiseSVN can't register another
				one and won't show all overlays.
			</para>
			<para>
				TortoiseSVN uses five overlay slots for the status:
				<graphic fileref="images/InSubVersionIcon.png"/>
				normal
				<graphic fileref="images/ModifiedIcon.png"/>
				modified
				<graphic fileref="images/ConflictIcon.png"/>
				conflicted
				<graphic fileref="images/DeletedIcon.png"/> 
				deleted
				<graphic fileref="images/AddedIcon.png"/> 
				added
			</para>
			<para>
				So most likely the <literal>added</literal> overlay will be
				missing, then the <literal>deleted</literal> and so on.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-2-2">
			<title>Why is there no overlay icon for unversioned files?</title>
			<para>
				For the same reason. There are only 15 slots for icon overlays available.
				We don't want to waste a slot for the least important information. That's why.
				If you want to distinguish <literal>unversioned</literal> and
				<literal>ignored</literal> files in the explorer, switch to the
				explorers detailed view and activate the column
				<guilabel>SVN Status</guilabel>.
				Then you will see the difference.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-3">
			<title>Why do the overlay icons sometimes change to random graphics?</title>
			<para>
				The Windows icon cache is a fairly buggy creature. 
				You can solve this in one of the following ways: 
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Install Microsoft's
							<application>
								<ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/ntworkstation/downloads/powertoys/networking/nttweakui.asp">
									<citetitle>TweakUI</citetitle>
								</ulink>
							</application>
							and run the option to rebuild icons.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Or increase the icon cache size. Go to 
<screen>
HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\Software\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Explorer
</screen>
							and add a new String Value called
							<literal>Max Cached Icons</literal>.
							The default value is 500 - try increasing it to 2048 (see 
							<ulink url="http://support.microsoft.com/support/kb/articles/Q132/6/68.asp">
								<citetitle>Q132668</citetitle>
							</ulink>
							in the Microsoft knowledge base for more details).
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Or delete the file called ShellIconCache 
							in your Windows directory. And reboot.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-4">
			<title>Those icons are grotesque, I want better ones!</title>
			<para>
				You can create your own icon set if you want. And if you do 
				please contribute them to the rest of the world! Just send them
				to the mailing list <email>dev@tortoisesvn.tigris.org</email>.
			</para>
			<para>
				The icons should have at least two sizes (16x16 and 32x32 
				with 16 colors), for Windows XP there should also be a 
				set with 48x48 pixels.
			</para>
			<para>
				To install the icons you should copy them to the 
				directory where TortoiseSVN was installed. There you will
				find a directory called <filename>Icons</filename> which contains
				a separate subfolder for each available icon set. Copy your own
				icon set in there. Then start the settings dialog, and set the
				active icon set to the one you created.
			</para>
			<para>
				After that you need to restart (or logoff) your computer 
				so that explorer reads in the icons again. 
				Alternatively you can flush the icon cache with the 
				<ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/ntworkstation/downloads/powertoys/networking/nttweakui.asp">
					<citetitle>TweakUI</citetitle>
				</ulink>
				tool from Microsoft. For WinXP you can get
				<ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/windowsxp/pro/downloads/powertoys.asp">
					<citetitle>TweakUI</citetitle>
				</ulink>
				here.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-5">
			<title>The TortoiseSVN menu is invisible!</title>
			<para>
				There are a number of known problems with disappearing menus,
				which are due to the Windows Explorer, not TSVN. Usually
				it shows up as a blank space in the menu where the text and
				icon should be.
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							If you select a folder in the left pane of explorer,
							then use the File menu to access TSVN, the menu text
							and icons are invisible the second time you use the
							File menu. If you select another folder, the menu
							is restored. This happens under Windows 98, ME, 
							NT and 2000. Everything works fine under XP.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Under Windows NT 4, the context menu text and icons
							for TSVN sometimes disappear. This can happen
							anywhere in explorer.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-5a">
			<title>
				The TortoiseSVN menus are shown as ownerdrawn 
				(no icons, no text) in some software
			</title>
			<para>
				This is because the icons are completely ownerdrawn. 
			</para>
			<para>
				I you don't like the way TSVN handles it's menu entries, 
				you can do the following: Just create a (DWORD) 
				registry entry under: 
<screen>
HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\OwnerdrawnMenus
</screen>
				and set it to <literal>0</literal>. This will force TortoiseSVN
				to use the windows standard routine to draw menu entries. 
				You'll have all the menu entries any time, but you will 
				have ugly icons, since window's default only allows 
				10x10 icons. If you delete this registry key (the default) 
				or set it to something other than <literal>0</literal>
				you have the nice icons back. 
			</para>
			<para>
				In case you want no icons at all you can set this value to
				<literal>2</literal>. Then the context menu entries show up as text only.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-6">
			<title>How do I uninstall TortoiseSVN?</title>
			<para>
				Simply uninstall from Add/Remove Programs in the Windows 
				control panel. This does not effect your repositories or 
				working copies at all. Be aware however, that the 
				subversion database schema might change before 
				subversion 1.0 is released. When you are working with 
				local repositories (<filename>file:///</filename> URLs), a 
				newer version of TortoiseSVN might be incompatible to 
				an old repository. Please check the subversion release notes. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-7">
			<title>
				I installed a new version of TortoiseSVN, but
				the new functions aren't visible?!?
			</title>
			<para>
				TortoiseSVN is a Windows explorer shell extension. 
				So after updating you <emphasis>must</emphasis> restart 
				windows or at least the explorer process. 
				If you don't then the the explorer process still has the old 
				version of the dll loaded in RAM and uses that old version... 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-8">
			<title>Can I use TortoiseCVS and TortoiseSVN on the same computer?</title>
			<para>
				Yes they can live happily together on the same PC. 
				You can even use them on the same folder if that 
				makes any sense to you.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-9">
			<title>I've got PowerDesk 5 installed and TSVN doesn't work on my PC</title>
			<para>
				Well, in this case Powerdesk is the bad guy. However, they have
				now provided a fix, as reported by Paul Gifford.
			</para>
			<blockquote>
				<para>
					There is a fix for Powerdesk 5, but it's not available on
					their website; you have to contact support to get it.
					They'll give you an update to a later version (5.0.1.7 -
					which is strangely not on the update portion of the site)
					then send you a patch to bring you to 5.0.1.8. which
					fixes the problem.
				</para>
				<para>
					Version 6 does not have the menu problem.
				</para>
			</blockquote>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-10">
			<title>Where is the spellchecker?</title>
			<para>
				If you want to use a spellchecker when entering your log messages
				please follow the installation instructions here: 
				<xref linkend="tsvn-ch-1-sect-4"/>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-faq-dug">
		<title>Daily use questions</title>
		<para>
			This section answers questions about problems you may encounter
			while using TortoiseSVN on a daily basis.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-1">
			<title>I accidentally removed a file, and now it's gone!</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>remove</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>delete</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>revert</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				You can do a
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenuitem>revert</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>
				on the parent folder where you deleted the file or 
				directory.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you have already committed the deleted file, then you can
				use the repository browser, change to the revision where the file
				still existed and then use the command 
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenuitem>Copy to...</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>
				from the context menu. Enter the path to your working copy
				as the target.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-2">
			<title>When I remove a file it vanishes, how do I commit it?</title>
			<para>
				Easy, you commit the whole directory! 
				<action>Right-click</action> in the Explorer window 
				next to the file, and choose
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenuitem>commit</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>.
				I nearly always commit things from the top level 
				directory - it is recursive through the whole project. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-3">
			<title>I always get an error when I check out a single file</title>
			<para>
				There's nothing wrong with it. Subversion only allows you to 
				check out directories - not files. A warning is not 
				possible because TortoiseSVN has no possibility to check 
				if a URL (e.g.
				<systemitem class="url">
				http://svn.collab.net/svn/repos/trunk/README</systemitem>) 
				is a file or a folder (ok, it could - but that would
				take a few seconds to check...). But subversion itself 
				complains if it's a file... 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-4">
			<title>I'm in trouble renaming a file from UPPERcase to upperCASE</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>case sensitive</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				There are (at least) two possible solutions to rename a file
				without losing its log history. It is important to rename it
				<emphasis>within</emphasis> subversion. Just renaming in the
				explorer will corrupt your working copy!!!
			</para>
			<para>
				Solution A) (recommended)
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Commit the changes in your working copy.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Rename the file from
							<filename>UPPERcase</filename> to
							<filename>upperCASE</filename> inside the repository 
							using the
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenuitem>repository browser</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Select the <emphasis>file</emphasis> you renamed,
							<emphasis>not</emphasis> any of its parent folders,
							right-click and do an update. After that, update the
							parent folder.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Or: delete your working copy and do a fresh 
							checkout. Just updating won't work, because it will 
							result in an obstructed update.
						</para>
						<para>
							If you don't want to checkout the whole working
							copy again, delete the parent folder of the file
							you've just renamed and do an update.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				Solution B)
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Rename from
							<filename>UPPERcase</filename> to
							<filename>UPPERcase_</filename> with the
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenuitem>rename</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>
							command in the TortoiseSVN submenu.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Commit the changes
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Rename from
							<filename>UPPERcase_</filename> to
							<filename>upperCASE</filename>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Commit the changes
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-6">
			<title>
				Can I mix and match with the Subversion command line
				client or another Subversion client?
			</title>
			<para>
				Yes, you can change from one client to another 
				whenever you want.
			</para>
			<para>
				There's only one exception: if you use the special build to work
				around the VS.NET bug with web projects then you can't use any
				other subversion clients anymore. You're stuck with that special
				build. Other Subversion clients won't recognize your working copies.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-7">
			<title>
				Can I work on lots of working copies 
				from different repositories at once?
			</title>
			<para>
				Yes, you can. This is a standard feature of Subversion. 
				Each directory which was checked out of Subversion remembers 
				where it came from. You can even multiply select 
				working copies which came from different places, and 
				update or commit them all at once. 
			</para>
			<para>
				If you want to have different subdirectories to come 
				from different repositories you can set a 
				special Subversion property called
				<literal>svn:externals</literal>.
				Please look at the chapter
				<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.1/ch07s02.html#svn-ch-7-sect-2.3.6">
					<citetitle>External Definitions</citetitle>
				</ulink>
				in the
				<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">
					<citetitle>Subversion Book</citetitle>
				</ulink>. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-8">
			<title>How does TortoiseSVN handle conflicts?</title>
			<para>
				Imagine you check out revision 24 of a file and started 
				editing it. In the meantime, someone else committed 
				revision 25, and shortly after that revision 26. You 
				tell TortoiseSVN to update your file now, and Subversion will 
				try to incorporate all the changes between revision 24 
				and 26 into your local file. 
			</para>
			<para>
				But if the changes made between 24 and 26 were too 
				close to or even overlap with the changes you have 
				made, Subversion detects a conflict and creates conflict 
				markers in the file. You then have to resolve these conflicts
				yourself. Read
				<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-conflicts"/> to find out more.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-9">
			<title>
				I tried to commit my changes and got a message telling me
				my working copy is out-of-date
			</title>
			<para>
				That means you need to use the
				<menuchoice>
					<guimenuitem>Update</guimenuitem>
				</menuchoice>
				command to update your working copy to the same level as the repository.
			</para>
			<para>
				It may not be obvious why you need to do this, especially if you
				<emphasis>know</emphasis> the repository has not changed. The answer
				is simply that your working copy is not completely updated by a
				commit.Only changed files and folders get updated automatically.
				Consider this example on a newly created repository:
<screen>
Add Folder in revision 1
Add File1 and File2 in revision 2
Modify File1 and commit in revision 3
</screen>
				Now the repository is at revision 3, but in your working copy
				the revisions look like this:
<screen>
Folder       : revision 1
Folder/File1 : revision 3
Folder/File2 : revision 2
</screen>
				Now if you modify File2 and try to commit, it fails. The client
				tells the repository that File2 is at revision 2 with local
				modifications, but the repository is already at revision 3.
				If you then do an update, File2 will be at revision 3 as well
				(and of course your local changes will still be there).
			</para>
			<para>
				The same thing may happen if you try to create a branch or tag.
				The answer is always the same:
				If your working copy is out-of-date, update it!
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-faq-misc">
		<title>Misc Questions</title>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-1">
			<title>TortoiseSVN seems very slow on big directories</title>
			<para>
				To show you the file and folder icon overlays TortoiseSVN must 
				fetch the status each time you open such a folder in the explorer.
				This takes usually only a few seconds, but can take much longer
				if you have either a slow harddisk or a very big directory.
			</para>
			<para>
				Note: usually it's only very slow the first time you open a 
				versioned folder. If you browse the same directory later again it's
				much faster due to internal caching.
			</para>
			<para>
				You can try to speed things up by:
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						To speed up browsing in the explorer you should 
						first turn off the recursive overlays. Go to 
						the settings dialog and uncheck
						<guilabel>Recurse into folders to fetch the status</guilabel>.
						This will tell TortoiseSVN not to scan subfolders.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Whenever the <emphasis>last modified time</emphasis>
						of a file changed, TortoiseSVN needs to do a complete
						diff (!) of that file to find out if it has changed.
						If you often change a file, undo the changes and save
						the file again you'll encounter a slowdown in browsing.
						A fresh checkout of your working copy would solve
						that problem.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						There are several Virus scanners around that interfere
						with TortoiseSVN. Most of the time they lock files
						inside the <filename>.svn</filename>
						Status directory, which can cause TortoiseSVN to hang
						or to become very slow. Sometimes you might even get
						an <emphasis>Access Denied</emphasis> error.
					</para>
					<para>
						Try to configure your virus scanner so that it
						ignores <filename>.svn</filename> directories.
					</para>
					<para>
						Virus scanners that are known to behave badly are:
						McAfee, Norton Antivirus, ...
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If you're working on Windows XP then you can also
						disable the <emphasis>zipfolders</emphasis>. This will
						also increase the browsing speed.
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Select <command>Run</command> from the
									start menu
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Type
									<command>regsvr32 /u %windir%\system32\zipfldr.dll</command>
									at the prompt and click ok
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									The change will take effect immediately,
									but you may have to restart Windows 
									for all traces of the built-in ZIP support
									to disappear.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
						If, at any time, you wish to re-enable Windows XP's 
						built-in ZIP support, just follow these steps:
						<orderedlist>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Select <command>Run</command> from the
									start menu
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									Type
									<command>regsvr32 %windir%\system32\zipfldr.dll </command>
									at the prompt and click ok
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									The change will take effect immediately,
									but you may have to restart Windows 
									for all features of the built-in ZIP
									support to be available.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-2">
			<title>TortoiseSVN doesn't work with VS.NET web projects?</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>VS.NET</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				VS.NET when used with web projects can't handle the
				<filename>.svn</filename> folders Subversion uses to store its
				internal information. This is <emphasis>not</emphasis> a bug in
				Subversion. The bug is in VS.NET and the frontpage extensions
				it uses. Even though you might argue that Windows can't handle
				such foldernames, it's not correct.
				Windows can handle such folders very well, you just can't
				create them with the explorer.
			</para>
			<para>
				However, this bug applies only when you use web projects, 
				which is not the same as ASP.NET projects. Usually, when you
				want to create an ASP.NET project, you choose to create a web
				project. But you can create or convert an ASP.NET project as a
				class project. 
				With some minor tweaking, you won't notice the difference,
				and you then can use TortoiseSVN and SVN with
				<filename>.svn</filename> folders without problems.
			</para>
			<para>
				There is a really good blog post that helps you to convert 
				your ASP.NET web projects to ASP.NET class project. You can
				find it
				<ulink url="http://www.pluralsight.com/fritz/Samples/aspdotnet_without_web_projects.htm">
					<citetitle>here</citetitle>
				</ulink>.
				If you follow those instructions, you'll have a VS.NET working
				with ASP.NET projects and Subversion without troubles.
			</para>
			<para>
				Alternatively, upgrade your copy of VS.NET. The bug has been
				fixed in VS.NET2005, so it no longer has this problem.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you still want to use TortoiseSVN with web projects, these
				are the questions we face every few weeks and here are the
				answers once and for all:
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>You need to fix this in Subversion!</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								No, we don't. It's a bug in VS.NET and not in
								Subversion. So the bug has to be fixed there.
								In fact in VS.NET2005 it has been fixed, so if
								you can upgrade VS.NET, the problem goes away.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>Why not make the foldername configurable?</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								There are many reasons <emphasis>not</emphasis>
								to do that. It would require major changes to
								the existing sourcecode, it would make the
								interaction of different Subversion clients
								very hard if not impossible and it would lead
								to confusion among users.
							</para>
							<para>
								There are more reasons, but they are very
								technical and don't belong in this FAQ.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>
							Then just create a special version of TortoiseSVN
							which uses a different foldername, and all
							problems are gone!
						</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								No, we won't. <emphasis>Your</emphasis> problems
								might be gone, but all others who are using
								Subversion and TortoiseSVN would get into
								troubles if we did that.
							</para>
							<para>
								One of the big advantages in using this folder
								name is that it is universal. i.e. you can use
								the same working copy from your Linux box and
								from your Windows box. Very useful if you have
								a dual boot computer and don't want to have
								two working copies for each OS you boot.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>But I can't use TortoiseSVN if that's not fixed!</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Then don't use it! Nobody forces you to use our
								product. If you really want to use it, then you
								could compile yourself a special version using
								a different foldername. After all, both
								Subversion and TortoiseSVN are open source.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</para>
			<para>
				But you're not completely lost in this case. Usually a few days
				after each official release of TortoiseSVN some people upload
				an installer for TortoiseSVN which is specially compiled to use
				<filename>_svn</filename> instead of the default
				<filename>.svn</filename> foldername. You can use that version
				then. Just be aware that we don't support that version at all!
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-3">
			<title>Does TortoiseSVN support SSH?</title>
			<para>
				TortoiseSVN uses Subversion. And Subversion supports SSH 
				<systemitem class="url">svn+ssh://</systemitem> (repository 
				reachable via svnserve). If you don't want to use the svnserve
				server but Apache instead (which I would recommend!) then
				Subversion supports secure connections via SSL.
			</para>
			<para>
				A guide on how to secure your Apache server with SSL can be
				found in <xref linkend="tsvn-serversetup-apache-6"/>
			</para>
			<para>
				Please have a look at the subversion book and the 
				INSTALL file of subversion on how to use
				<systemitem class="url">svn+ssh://</systemitem>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-4">
			<title>Can I get the project revision number into my project?</title>
			<para>
				If you want the revision number in your program version number
				you need an additional tool to do that. You can find the tool 
				<literal>SubWCRev.exe</literal> on the download page on our
				website or in your TortoiseSVN Folder under 
				<filename>bin</filename>.
			</para>
			<para>
				This tool traverses your whole working copy for the most recent
				revision. Once that revision is found, it replaces all
				occurrences of the following strings:
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>$WCREV$</term>
						<listitem>
							This string will be replaced by the revision 
							number of your working copy. 
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>$WCMODS?Modified:Not modified$</term>
						<listitem>
							If you have local modifications, the string between 
							Question mark and colon will be inserted. If you 
							have no local modifications, the string between colon 
							and dollar sign will be inserted. In our example above 
							<literal>Modified</literal> or
							<literal>Not modified</literal>.
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>$WCDATE$</term>
						<listitem>
							Will be replaced by the date of the highest revision
							in your working copy. 
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</para>
			<para>
				As an example, have a look at the file
				<filename>version.in</filename> in the
				<ulink url="http://svn.collab.net/repos/tortoisesvn/trunk/src/version.in">
					<citetitle>TortoiseSVN source tree</citetitle>
				</ulink>.
				This file is used in TortoiseSVN and its resource files. The
				SubWCRev.exe tool is called from the build script like this:
<screen>
SubWCRev.exe path\to\working\copy version.in version.h
</screen>
				This creates a new file <filename>version.h</filename> with all
				the strings above replaced with the values of the working copy. 
				The <filename>version.h</filename>
				file is then used in the project itself and included in the 
				resource files for the version information.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-5">
			<title>Can I lose data, when I use TortoiseSVN?</title>
			<para>
				TortoiseSVN uses Subversion. Nuff said :-)
			</para>
			<para>
				Seriously - No! Read the Subversion pages. You can 
				screw up your working copy any way you like, but if you 
				commit your data regularly, you can always revert to a 
				functional state. Just remember that TortoiseSVN was not made
				to protect you against stupidity (e.g. Format C:). 
			</para>
			<para>
				You can only lose your data if you throw your computer out
				of the window, format your harddrive, nail your 
				harddrive to a wall...
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-6">
			<title>I'm looking for an external diff tool</title>
			<para>
				This list is by no means complete, but might help 
				you to find something: 
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://winmerge.sourceforge.net/">
								<citetitle>WinMerge</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
							a great open-source viewer
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="ftp://ftp.perforce.com/pub/perforce/r03.1/bin.ntx86/p4diff.zip">
								<citetitle>Perforce Win Diff</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
							a free tool from Perforce. You can download the full
							<ulink url="http://www.perforce.com/perforce/loadprog.html">
								<citetitle>installer</citetitle>
							</ulink>
							here.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://www.prestosoft.com/">
								<citetitle>Examdiff or Examdiff Pro</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
							an excellent Free or Shareware tool,
							The 3.2 version can handle unicode.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://www.scootersoftware.com/">
								<citetitle>Beyond Compare</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
							an excellent Shareware tool, can handle Unicode
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://www.scintilla.org/SciTEDownload.html">
								<citetitle>SciTE</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
							for showing unified diffs, it has built-in support
							for syntax-coloring, since it's not only a viewer
							but a Text Editor as well.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-7">
			<title>I'm looking for an external merge tool</title>
			<para>
				This list is by no means complete, but might help 
				you to find something: 
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://winmerge.sourceforge.net/">
								<citetitle>WinMerge</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
							a great open-source viewer.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="ftp://ftp.perforce.com/pub/perforce/r03.1/bin.ntx86/p4winmrg.zip">
								<citetitle>Perforce Win Diff</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
 							a free tool from Perforce. You can find the full
							<ulink url="http://www.perforce.com/perforce/loadprog.html">
								<citetitle>installer</citetitle>
							</ulink>
							here.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://www.accurev.com/free/tkdiff/">
								<citetitle>TkDiff</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
 							uses TCL/TK
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/conflicteditor/">
								<citetitle>CvsConflictEditor</citetitle>
							</ulink>,
							buggy but has potential.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-20">
			<title>What are the hidden registry settings?</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>Registry</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				There are some registry settings for TortoiseSVN which aren't
				available through the settings dialog. These registry settings
				usually are for debugging purposes or very special occasions.
				You can set those with the registry editor 
				<command>regedt32</command>.
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\Debug</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Set this value to 1 for TortoiseSVN to show you the
								parameters it gets from the shell extension part.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\OwnerdrawnMenus</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								Set this value to 0 if you don't want TortoiseSVN to
								use ownerdraw menu items in the shell context menu.
								This helps if you use something else than the windows
								explorer or if you get problems with the context menu
								showing up.
							</para>
							<para>
								Set this value to 2 if you don't want TortoiseSVN
								to use icons in the context menu at all. With this
								value set to 2 the context menu is text only.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\BlockStatus</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
								If you don't want the explorer to update the status
								overlays while another TortoiseSVN command is running
								(e.g. an update, commit, ...) then set this value to 1.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</para>
			<para>
				Please don't mess with those and any other registry setting if
				you don't know <emphasis>exactly</emphasis> what you're doing!
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-100">
			<title>I love TortoiseSVN, how can I do something for the developers?</title>
			<para>
				Thanks for asking!
			</para>
			<xi:include href="./wishlist.xml"/>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</appendix>
<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "appendix")
end:
-->
