<appendix id="tsvn-faq">
	<title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ)</title>
	<simplesect>
		<para>
	This appendix answers the questions we are asked the most on
	the TortoiseSVN mailing list <email>dev@tortoisesvn.tigris.org</email>
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-faq-installation">
		<title>Installation issues</title>
		<indexterm><primary>install</primary></indexterm>
		<para>
		Most of these answers came from the <application>TortoiseCVS
		</application>
			<ulink url="http://www.tortoisecvs.org/faq.html">FAQ
		</ulink>
		</para>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-0">
			<title>The installer aborts with an error message</title>
			<para>
			If the msi installer shows you the error message <literal>The 
			installer was interrupted before TortoiseSVN could be installed. 
			You need to restart the installer to try again. Click "Close" 
			to exit</literal> then the user SYSTEM doesn't
			have read access to the folder where the msi file is located.
			</para>
			<para>
			Just move the msi file to another location, e.g. <filename>c:\</filename>
			and try again.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-1">
			<title>Why don't the icon overlays appear?</title>
			<indexterm><primary>overlays</primary></indexterm>
			<para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>If you are using Windows 95 the icon 
				overlays won't appear. You can try the instructions 
				for Windows NT4 below if you like, but it may 
				still not work. Please note: We don't support Windows 95 at
				all - so there may be other issues if you're using that OS
				</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>If you are using Windows NT4, you 
				need to install the IE4 shell or desktop extensions 
				to get a more recent version of Explorer. 
				To do this install IE4, and choose Yes to 
				install the active desktop. Don't worry, you can 
				turn off the actual active desktop later by right 
				clicking on it. It's the new version of Explorer 
				that we are after.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>If you've already installed IE5, 
				you must either: 
					<orderedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>Uninstall IE5 and then install IE4 
						with desktop extensions, and then install 
						IE5 again. What a palaver.</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
									<para>Run IE5 setup with command line 
						switches to install the IE4 desktop (shell) 
						extensions.</para>
									<para>The command must be run from the folder that 
						contains the ie5setup.exe file. If the browser 
						appears unstable afterwards just run the 
						IE5 repair function.</para>
									<para>For Win95: ie5setup.exe /c:"ie5wzd /e:IE4Shell WIN /I:Y"</para>
									<para>For WinNT: ie5setup.exe /c:"ie5wzd /e:IE4Shell NTx86 /I:Y"</para>
								</listitem>
							</orderedlist>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>For IE6:</para>
						<para>Run IE6 setup with command line switches to install 
				the IE4 desktop (shell) extensions. The same 
				caveats apply as for IE5. The command must be run from the 
				folder that contains the ie6setup.exe file. 
				For WinNT: ie6setup.exe /c:"ie6wzd /e:IE4Shell NTx86 /I:Y" 
				</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The shortcut labelled Win NT Explorer 
				on your start menu probably points to 
				<filename>C:\WINNT\explorer.scf</filename> and doesn't 
				get the overlays. Create a new shortcut to
<screen>
%windir%\Explorer.exe /n, /e
</screen>
				and it may get the overlays.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>If you're using an IntelliPoint mouse 
				driver, and launching Explorer via a mouse click, 
				you need to upgrade from version 3 to version 3.2 or higher 
				of IntelliPoint. Strangely, launching Explorer from the 
				Start menu gives icons in this case, 
				but not when launched from the mouse.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-2">
			<title>I followed the instructions, but there are 
			still no icons?!?</title>
			<para>
			You rebooted your PC off course?
			So after installing the shell extensions you now 
			have WinNT / Win95 and IE >= 5.5 installed?
			</para>
			<para>
			If you installed TortoiseSVN as a different user 
			under WinNT/Win2K/WinXP than you are using now, 
			do the following thing: Go to the settings of TSVN and 
			activate the icon overlays for at least the fixed 
			drives. The installer does this automatically for the 
			<emphasis>current</emphasis> user (can't do it for 
			other users...) but since you are using TSVN as a 
			different user than you installed it you need to 
			set this manually.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-2-1">
			<title>The overlay icons appear, but not all of them!</title>
			<para>
			This usually happens if you have other programs installed which
			use icon overlays like e.g. TortoiseCVS. The reason for this is
			that Windows only has 15 slots for icon overlays, and about three
			or four are used by Windows itself (e.g. for links, shared folders, ...).
			If all those slots are full then TortoiseSVN can't register another
			one and won't show all overlays.
			</para>
			<para>
			TortoiseSVN uses five overlay slots for the status:
			<graphic fileref="images/InSubVersionIcon.png"/>
			normal
			<graphic fileref="images/ModifiedIcon.png"/>
			modified
			<graphic fileref="images/ConflictIcon.png"/>
			conflicted
			<graphic fileref="images/DeletedIcon.png"/> 
			deleted
			<graphic fileref="images/AddedIcon.png"/> 
			added
			</para>
			<para>
			So most likely the "added" overlay will be missing, then the "deleted"
			and so on.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-2-2">
			<title>Why is there no overlay icons for unversioned files?</title>
			<para>
			  For the same reason. There are only 15 slots for icon overlays available.
			  We don't want to waste a slot for the least important information. That's why.
			  If you want to distinguish "unversioned" and "ignored" files in the explorer,
			  switch to the explorers detailed view and activate the column "SVN Status". 
				Then you will see the difference.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-3">
			<title>Why do the overlay icons sometimes 
			change to random graphics?</title>
			<para>
			The Windows icon cache is a fairly buggy creature. 
			You can solve this in one of the following ways: 
			<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Install Microsoft's <application>
								<ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/ntworkstation/downloads/powertoys/networking/nttweakui.asp">	TweakUI</ulink>
							</application> and run the option 	to rebuild icons.</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Or increase the icon cache size. 
				Go to 
<screen>
HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\Software\Microsoft\Windows\CurrentVersion\Explorer
</screen>
				 and add 
				a new String Value called <literal>Max Cached Icons</literal>. 
				The default value is 500 - try increasing it to 2048 
				(see <ulink url="http://support.microsoft.com/support/kb/articles/Q132/6/68.asp">this</ulink>
				 knowledge base article for more details).
				</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Or delete the file called ShellIconCache 
				in your Windows directory. And reboot.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-4">
			<title>Those icons are grotesque, I want better ones!</title>
			<para>
			You can create your own icon set if you want. And if you do 
			please contribute them to the rest of the world! Just send them
			to the mailing list <email>dev@tortoisesvn.tigris.org</email>.
			</para>
			<para>
			The icons should have at least two sizes (16x16 and 32x32 
			with 16 colors), for Windows XP there should also be a 
			set with 48x48 pixels.
			</para>
			<para>
			To install the icons you should copy them to the 
			directory where TortoiseSVN was installed. There you 
			can either replace the existing icons or give them 
			new names. If you choose not to overwrite the original 
			ones then you also need to tweak some registry settings. 
			Under <filename>HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\</filename> change 
			the keys <literal>ConflictIcon</literal>, <literal>InSubversionIcon</literal>, 
			<literal>AddedIcon</literal>, <literal>DeletedIcon</literal> and <literal>ModifiedIcon</literal> 
			to the path and names of your own icon set.
			</para>
			<para>
			After that you need to restart (or logoff) your computer 
			so that explorer reads in the icons again. 
			Alternatively you can flush the icon cache with the 
			<ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/ntworkstation/downloads/powertoys/networking/nttweakui.asp">
					<application>TweakUI</application>
				</ulink>
			tool from Microsoft. For
			WinXP you can get it <ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/windowsxp/pro/downloads/powertoys.asp">here</ulink>.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-5">
			<title>
The TortoiseSVN menu is missing when nothing is selected!
			</title>
			<para>
			The main menu is known to disappear under Windows 98, ME, 
			NT and 2000. Everything works fine under XP.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-5a">
			<title>
				The TortoiseSVN menus are shown as ownerdrawn 
				(no icons, no text) in some software
			</title>
			<para>
			This is because the icons are completely ownerdrawn. 
			</para>
			<para>
			I you don't like the way TSVN handles it's menu entries, 
			you can do the following: Just create a (DWORD) 
			registry entry under: 
<screen>
HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\OwnerdrawnMenus
</screen>
			and set it to 0. This will force TortoiseSVN to use the 
			windows standard routine to draw menu entries. 
			You'll have all the menu entries any time, but you will 
			have ugly icons, since window's default only allows 
			10x10 icons. If you delete this registry key (the default) 
			or set it to something else than 0 you have the nice 
			icons back. 
			</para>
			<para>
			In case you want no icons at all you can set this value to 2. Then
			the context menu entries show up as text only.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-6">
			<title>How do I uninstall TortoiseSVN?</title>
			<para>
			Simply uninstall from Add/Remove Programs in the Windows 
			control panel. This does not effect your repositories or 
			working copies at all. Be aware however, that the 
			subversion database schema might change before 
			subversion 1.0 is released. When you are working with 
			local repositories (<filename>file:///</filename> URLs), a 
			newer version of TortoiseSVN might be incompatible to 
			an old repository. Please check the subversion release notes. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-7">
			<title>I installed a new version of TortoiseSVN, but 
			the new functions aren't visible?!?</title>
			<para>
			TortoiseSVN is a Windows explorer shell extension. 
			So after updating you <emphasis>must</emphasis> restart 
			windows or at least the explorer process. 
			If you don't then the the explorer process still has the old 
			version of the dll loaded in RAM and uses that old version... 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-8">
			<title>Can I use TortoiseCVS and TortoiseSVN 
			on the same computer?</title>
			<para>
			Yes they can live happily together on the same PC. 
			You can even use them on the same folder if that 
			makes any sense to you.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-9">
			<title>I've got PowerDesk 5 installed 
			and TSVN doesn't work on my PC</title>
			<para>
			Well, in this case Powerdesk is the bad guy.
			</para>
			<para>
			We sent an assistance request to the people from 
			PD and this is their response (Thanks guys):
			<blockquote>
					<para>
				For now, we suggest the users of the Tortoise shell 
				extension may wish to save off the PD context menu key, 
				and temporarily delete it from the registry while 
				we work on a fix to the PD code. The PD context menu 
				key is here:
<screen>
[HKEY_CLASSES_ROOT\*\shellex\ContextMenuHandlers\PowerDeskMenu]
</screen>
				Hopefully, removing that key will prevent a shell crash 
				when both apps are on the system. Unfortunately, this 
				will disable the PowerDesk features of the user's 
				shell context menu. We believe the problem to be inside 
				the PD code as we have seen other shell extensions run 
				into similar problems when PD5 is installed. We are 
				working on a fix and we will provide a patch ASAP.
				</para>
				</blockquote>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-installation-10">
		<title>Where is the spellchecker?</title>
		<para>
		If you want to use a spellchecker when entering your log messages
		please follow the installation instructions here: 
		<xref linkend="tsvn-ch-1-sect-4" />
		</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-faq-dug">
		<title>Daily use questions</title>
		<para>
		This section answers questions about problems you may encounter
		while using TortoiseSVN on a daily basis.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-1">
			<title>I accidentally removed a file, and now it's gone!</title>
			<indexterm><primary>remove</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>delete</primary></indexterm>
			<indexterm><primary>revert</primary></indexterm>
			<para>
			You can do a <guimenuitem>revert</guimenuitem> on the 
			parent folder where you deleted the file or 
			directory. But use that carefully: you will lose all 
			changes you made in that folder since you last committed! 
			That means not only the file you deleted but changes to other
			files as well!
			</para>
			<para>
			Alternatively you can use Subversion's <command>revert</command> command
			to revert only the removed file.
			Please look at the chapter <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/html-chunk/ch03s05.html#svn-ch-3-sect-4.3.3">
					<citetitle>svn revert</citetitle>
				</ulink>
			in the <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">
					<citetitle>Subversion Book</citetitle>
				</ulink>. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-2">
			<title>When I remove a file it vanishes, how 
			do I commit it?</title>
			<para>
			Easy, you commit the whole directory! 
			<action>Right&ndash;click</action> in the Explorer window 
			next to the file, and choose <guimenuitem>commit</guimenuitem>. 
			I nearly always commit things from the top level 
			directory &mdash; it is recursive through the whole project. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-3">
			<title>I always get an error when I check out a single file</title>
			<para>
			There's nothing wrong with it. Subversion only allows you to 
			check out directories &mdash; not files. A warning is not 
			possible because TortoiseSVN has no possibility to check 
			if a URL (e.g. <systemitem class="url">
			http://svn.collab.net/svn/repos/trunk/README</systemitem>) 
			is a file or a folder (ok, it could &mdash; but that would
			take a few seconds to check...). But subversion itself 
			complains if it's a file.... 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-4">
			<title>I'm in trouble renaming a file from UPPERcase to upperCASE</title>
			<indexterm><primary>case sensitive</primary></indexterm>
			<para>There are (at least) two possible solutions to rename a file without losing it's log history.
			It is important to rename it <emphasis>within</emphasis> subversion. 
			Just renaming in the explorer will corrupt your working copy!!!
			</para>
			<para>
			Solution A) (recommended)
			<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Commit the changes in your working copy</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Rename the file from <filename>UPPERcase</filename> 
						to <filename>upperCASE</filename> inside the repository 
						using the <guimenuitem>repository browser</guimenuitem>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Delete your working copy and do a fresh 
						checkout. Just updating won't work, because it will 
						result in an obstructed update.</para>
						<para>If you don't want to checkout the whole working
						copy again, delete the parent folder of the file you've
						just renamed and do an update. </para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
			Solution B)
			<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Rename from <filename>UPPERcase</filename>to <filename>UPPERcase_</filename>
						with the <guimenuitem>rename</guimenuitem> command in the TortoiseSVN submenu.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Commit the changes</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Rename from <filename>UPPERcase_</filename>to <filename>upperCASE</filename>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Commit the changes</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-5">
			<title>I deleted a file and created a file with 
			the same name. Now I can't commit?!?</title>
			<para>
			Your're trying to fool subversion aren't you? No &mdash; seriously 
			&mdash; what did you expect to happen?
			</para>
			<para>
			Assume you're in revision #55.
			</para>
			<para>You removed a file using TortoiseSVN, which told it 
			to mark the file for deletion with the next commit 
			and to remove it from the explorer. It's not really 
			gone from the revision yet. Then you created a file with the 
			same name and added it to TortoiseSVN, which marks the file 
			for adding with the next commit. It's not yet added to the 
			repository. Now you commit. Poor subversion tries to decide 
			whether to add or remove your file at the same time 
			in revision #56. The commit fails.
			</para>
			<para>
			You should have committed immediately after you 
			deleted the file using TortoiseSVN's <guimenuitem>remove
			</guimenuitem> command. You still have no clue what 
			to do? Well, in that case:
			
			<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>Move that file to a safe place</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Commit your changes. That tells the 
				repository, that the file is gone in the 
				first place</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Copy the file back</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>Commit again</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-6">
			<title>Can I mix and match with the Subversion 
			command line client or another Subversion client?</title>
			<para>
			Yes, you can change from one client to another 
			whenever you want.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-7">
			<title>Can I work on lots of working copies 
			from different repositories at once?</title>
			<para>
			Yes, you can. This is a standard feature of Subversion. 
			Each directory which was checked out of Subversion remembers 
			where it came from. You can even multiply select 
			working copies which came from different places, and 
			update or commit them all at once. 
			</para>
			<para>
			If you want to have different subdirectories to come 
			from different repositories you can set a 
			special Subversion property called <literal>svn:externals</literal>.
			Please look at the chapter <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/html-chunk/ch07s03.html">
					<citetitle>External Definitions</citetitle>
				</ulink>
			in the <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">
					<citetitle>
			Subversion Book</citetitle>
				</ulink>. 
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-dug-8">
			<title>How does TortoiseSVN handle conflicts?</title>
			<para>
			Imagine you check out revision 24 of a file and started 
			editing it. In the meantime, someone else committed 
			revision 25, and shortly after that revision 26. You 
			tell TortoiseSVN to update your file now, and Subversion will 
			try to incorporate all the changes between revision 24 
			and 26 into your local file. 
			</para>
			<para>
			But if the changes made between 24 and 26 were too 
			close to or even overlap with the changes you have 
			made, Subversion detects a conflict and creates conflict 
			markers in the file. Subversion also creates three special 
			files for every conflicted file:
			
			<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>filename.*.mine</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>This is your file as it existed in your 
					working copy before you updated your working copy
					&mdash; that is, without conflict markers. This file has 
					your latest changes in it and nothing else.
					</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>filename.*.rOLDREV</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>This is the file that was the BASE 
					revision before you updated your working copy. That is,
					it the file that you checked out before you made 
					your latest edits.
					</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>filename.*.rNEWREV</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>This is the file that your Subversion 
					client just received from the server when you updated 
					your working copy. This file corresponds to the HEAD 
					revision of the repository.
					</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			At this point TortoiseSVN will not allow you to commit 
			the conflicted file until you <emphasis>resolved</emphasis> 
			the conflict. To tell TortoiseSVN that you resolved the 
			conflict simply delete the three additional files 
			or use the command <guimenuitem>resolved</guimenuitem> to 
			do that for you.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-faq-misc">
		<title>Misc Questions</title>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-1">
			<title>TortoiseSVN seems very slow on big directories</title>
			<para>
			To show you the file and folder icon overlays TortoiseSVN must 
			fetch the status each time you open such a folder in the explorer.
			This takes usually only a few seconds, but can take much longer
			if you have either a slow harddisk or a very big directory.
			</para>
			<para>
			Note: usually it's only very slow the first time you open a 
			versioned folder. If you browse the same directory later again it's
			much faster due to internal caching.
			</para>
			<para>You can try to speed things up by:</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					To speed up browsing in the explorer you should 
					first turn off the recursive overlays. Go to 
					the settings dialog and uncheck <command>Indicate 
					folders with changed contents</command>. This
					will tell TortoiseSVN not to scan subfolders.
					</para>
					<para>
					If you want to disable the recursive overlays only for some
					folders but not for all then you can do that by creating a
					file called <filename>_tsvnexcluderecursive</filename> inside
					that folder. This will disable the recursive overlays for
					that folder, but <emphasis>not</emphasis> for the files or
					folders inside it.
					</para>
					<para>
					You can also disable the overlays completely for a folder
					by creating a file called <filename>_tsvnexcludethis</filename>
					inside that folder. Again, this disables the overlays only
					for that folder, not the folders inside it.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Whenever the <emphasis>last modified time</emphasis> of
					a file changed, TortoiseSVN needs to do a complete diff (!)
					of that file to find out if it has changed. If you often
					change a file, undo the changes and save the file again
					you'll encounter a slowdown in browsing. A fresh checkout
					of your working copy would solve that problem.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					There are several Virus scanners around that interfere with TortoiseSVN.
					Most of the time they lock files inside the <filename>.svn</filename>
					Status directory, which can cause TortoiseSVN to hang or to become very slow. 
					Sometimes you might even get an <emphasis>Access Denied</emphasis> error.
					</para>
					<para>
					Try to configure your virus scanner so that it ignores <filename>.svn</filename>
					directories.
					</para>
					<para>
					Virus scanners that are known to behave badly are: McAfee, Norton Antivirus, ...
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					If you're working on Windows XP then you can also disable
					the <emphasis>zipfolders</emphasis>. This will also
					increase the browsing speed.
					<orderedlist>
						<listitem><para>Select <command>Run</command> from the
						start menu</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Type <command>regsvr32 /u %windir%\system32\zipfldr.dll</command>
						at the prompt and click ok</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>The change will take effect 
						immediately, but you may have to restart Windows 
						for all traces of the built-in ZIP support to 
						disappear.</para></listitem>
					</orderedlist>
					If, at any time, you wish to re-enable Windows XP's 
					built-in ZIP support, just follow these steps:
					<orderedlist>
						<listitem><para>Select <command>Run</command> from the
						start menu</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>Type <command>regsvr32 %windir%\system32\zipfldr.dll </command>
						at the prompt and click ok</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>The change will take effect 
						immediately, but you may have to restart Windows 
						for all features of the built-in ZIP support to 
						be available. </para></listitem>						
					</orderedlist>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-2">
			<title>TortoiseSVN doesn't work with VS.NET web projects?</title>
			<indexterm><primary>VS.NET</primary></indexterm>
			<para>
			VS.NET when used with web projects can't handle the <filename>.svn
			</filename> folders Subversion uses to store its internal information.
			This is <emphasis>not</emphasis> a bug in Subversion. The bug is in
			VS.NET and the frontpage extensions it uses. Even though you might
			argue that Windows can't handle such foldernames, it's not correct.
			Windows can handle such folders very well, you just can't create them
			with the explorer.
			</para>
			<para>
			To answer the questions we face every few weeks once and for all:
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>You need to fix this in Subversion!</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						No, we don't. It's a bug in VS.NET and not in Subversion.
						So the bug has to be fixed there.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Why not make the foldername configurable?</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						There are many reasons to <emphasis>not</emphasis> do that.
						It would require major changes to the existing sourcecode,
						it would make the interaction of different Subversion clients
						very hard if not impossible and it would lead to confusion
						among users.
						</para>
						<para>
						There are more reasons, but they are very technical and
						don't belong in this FAQ.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Then just create a special version of TortoiseSVN which
					uses a different foldername, and all problems are gone!</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						No, we won't. <emphasis>Your</emphasis> problems might be gone,
						but all others which are using Subversion and TortoiseSVN would
						get into troubles if we did that.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>But I can't use TortoiseSVN if that's not fixed!</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Then don't use it! Nobody forces you to use our product.
						If you really want to use it, then you could compile
						yourself a special version using a different foldername.
						After all, both Subversion and TortoiseSVN are open source.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			</para>
			<para>
			But you're not completely lost in this case. Usually a few days after
			each official release of TortoiseSVN some people upload an installer
			for TortoiseSVN which is specially compiled to use <filename>_svn</filename>
			instead of the default <filename>.svn</filename> foldername. You can
			use that version then. Just be aware that we don't support that
			version at all!
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-3">
			<title>Does TortoiseSVN support SSH?</title>
			<para>
			TortoiseSVN uses Subversion. And Subversion supports SSH 
			<systemitem class="url">svn+ssh://</systemitem> (repository 
			reachable via svnserve). If you don't want to use the svnserve
			server but Apache instead (which I would recommend!) then
			Subversion supports secure connections via SSL.
			</para>
			<para>
			A guide on how to secure your Apache server with SSL you can find
			in <xref linkend="tsvn-serversetup-apache-6"/>
			</para>
			<para>
			Please have a look at the subversion book and the 
			INSTALL file of subversion on how to use <systemitem class="url">
			svn+ssh://</systemitem>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-4">
			<title>Can I lose data, when I use TortoiseSVN?</title>
			<para>
			TortoiseSVN uses Subversion. Nuff said :-)
			</para>
			<para>
			Seriously &mdash; No! Read the Subversion pages. You can 
			screw up your working copy any way you like, but if you 
			commit your data regularly, you can always revert to a 
			functional state. TortoiseSVN was not made to protect 
			you against stupidity (e.g. Format C:). 
			</para>
			<para>
			You can only lose your data if you throw your computer out
			of the window, if you format your harddrive, ...
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-5">
			<title>I'm looking for an external diff tool</title>
			<para>
			This list is by no means complete, but might help 
			you to find something: 
			<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://winmerge.sourceforge.net/">
				WinMerge</ulink>, a great open-source viewer</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="ftp://ftp.perforce.com/pub/perforce/r03.1/bin.ntx86/p4diff.zip">
				Perforce Win Diff</ulink>, a free tool from Perforce. 
				You can find the full installer 
				<ulink url="http://www.perforce.com/perforce/loadprog.html">
				here</ulink>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://www.prestosoft.com/">Examdiff or Examdiff Pro</ulink>, an excellent Free or 
				Shareware tool, The 3.2 Version can handle unicode</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://www.scootersoftware.com/">
				Beyond Compare</ulink>, an excellent Shareware tool, can handle Unicode</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://www.scintilla.org/SciTEDownload.html">
				SciTE</ulink>, for showing unified diffs, it has 
				built&ndash;in support for syntax&ndash;coloring, since it's 
				not only a viewer but a Text Editor as well.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-6">
			<title>I'm looking for an external merge tool</title>
			<para>
			This list is by no means complete, but might help 
			you to find something: 
			<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://winmerge.sourceforge.net/">
				WinMerge</ulink>, a great open-source viewer</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="ftp://ftp.perforce.com/pub/perforce/r03.1/bin.ntx86/p4winmrg.zip">
				Perforce Win Diff</ulink>, a free tool from Perforce. 
				You can find the full installer 
				<ulink url="http://www.perforce.com/perforce/loadprog.html">
				here</ulink>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://www.accurev.com/free/tkdiff/">
				TkDiff</ulink>, uses TCL/TK</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/conflicteditor/">
				CvsConflictEditor</ulink>, buggy but has potential</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-7">
			<title>What are the hidden registry settings?</title>
			<para>
			There are some registry settings for TortoiseSVN which aren't
			available through the settings dialog. These registry settings
			usually are for debugging purposes or very special occasions.
			You can set those with the registry editor 
			<command>regedt32</command>.
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\Debug</term>
					<listitem>
					<para>
					Set this value to 1 for TortoiseSVN to show you the
					parameters it gets from the shell extension part.
					</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\OwnerdrawnMenus</term>
					<listitem>
					<para>
					Set this value to 0 if you don't want TortoiseSVN to
					use ownerdraw menu items in the shell context menu.
					This helps if you use something else than the windows
					explorer or if you get problems with the context menu
					showing up.
					</para>
					<para>
					Set this value to 2 if you don't want TortoiseSVN to use
					icons in the context menu at all. With this value set to 2
					the context menu is text only.
					</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>HKCU\Software\TortoiseSVN\BlockStatus</term>
					<listitem>
					<para>
					If you don't want the explorer to update the status
					overlays while another TortoiseSVN command is running
					(e.g. an update, commit, ...) then set this value to 1.
					</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			</para>
			<para>
			Please don't mess with those and any other registry setting if
			you don't know <emphasis>exactly</emphasis> what you're doing!
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="tsvn-faq-misc-8">
			<title>I love TortoiseSVN, how can I do 
			something for the developers?</title>
			<para>
			Thanks for asking!
			</para>
			<para>
			If you like TortoiseSVN and use it often, 
			please support the developers!
			</para>
			<para>
			You can help us by either sending in patches and 
			play an active role in development or you can 
			cheer up the hard working developers.
			</para>
			<para>
			While working on TortoiseSVN we love to listen to music. 
			And since we work many hours on the project we need a 
			<emphasis>lot</emphasis> of music. Therefore we have set 
			up some wish-lists with our favourite music CD's and DVD's:
	
			<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>The media wish list of 
				Stefan is <ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/o/registry/17DKTOSXX1KJK">
				here</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.thinkgeek.com/brain/gimme.cgi?wid=81d0854b9">here</ulink>
				(English) or <ulink url="http://www.amazon.de/exec/obidos/wishlist/26JA3LXZXY4TB/">here
				</ulink> (Deutsch).</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>L&uuml;bbe has got a <ulink url="http://www.amazon.de/exec/obidos/wishlist/3IKWLV2U0TVUA/">
				wishlist</ulink> too.</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			
			Please have a look at the list of contributors.
	
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</appendix>
<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "appendix")
end:
-->
