<chapter id="tsvn_introduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<simplesect>
		<para>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>version control</primary>
			</indexterm>
		Version control is the art of managing changes to
		information.  It has long been a critical tool for programmers,
		who typically spend their time making small changes to software
		and then undoing those changes the next day.  Imagine a team of
		these programmers working concurrently - and perhaps even simultaneously
		at the very same files! - and you can see why a
		good system is needed to manage the potential chaos.
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ch-1-sect-1">
		<title>What is TortoiseSVN?</title>
		<para>
		TortoiseSVN is a free/open-source client for the Subversion version
		control system.
		That is, TortoiseSVN manages files and directories over time.
		Files are stored into a central <firstterm>repository</firstterm>.
		The repository is much like an ordinary file server, except that it
		remembers every change ever made to your files and directories.
		This allows you to recover older versions of your files and examine
		the history of how and when your data changed. This is why many
		people think of Subversion and version control systems in general as
		a sort of <quote>time machine</quote>.
		</para>
		<para>
		Some version control systems are also software configuration
		management (SCM) systems.  These systems are specifically
		tailored to manage trees of source code, and have many features
		that are specific to software development - such as natively
		understanding programming languages, or supplying tools for
		building software.  Subversion, however, is not one of these
		systems; it is a general system that can be used to manage
		<emphasis>any</emphasis> collection of files, including
		source code.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ch-1-sect-2">
		<title>TortoiseSVN's History</title>
		<para>
		In 2002, Tim Kemp found that Subversion was a very good version control
		system, but it lacked a good GUI client. The idea for a subversion
		client as a Windows shell integration was inspired by the similar
		client for CVS named TortoiseCVS.
		</para>
		<para>
		Tim studied the sourcecode of TortoiseCVS and used it as a base for
		TortoiseSVN. He then started the project, registered the domain
		tortoisesvn.org and put the sourcecode online. During that time,
		Stefan Küng was looking for a good and free version control system
		and found Subversion and the source for TortoiseSVN. Since TortoiseSVN
		was still not ready for use then he joined the project and started
		programming. Soon he rewrote most of the existing code and started
		adding commands and features, up to a point where nothing of the
		original code remained.
		</para>
		<para>
		As Subversion became more stable it attracted more and more users who
		also started using TortoiseSVN as their Subversion client. The userbase
		grew quickly (and is still growing every day). That's when Lübbe
		Onken offered to help out with some nice icons and a logo for
		TortoiseSVN. And he takes care of the website.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ch-1-sect-3">
		<title>TortoiseSVN's Features</title>
		<para>
		What makes TortoiseSVN such a good Subversion client? Here's a short
		list of features.
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Shell integration</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<indexterm>
							<primary>Windows shell</primary>
						</indexterm>
						<indexterm>
							<primary>explorer</primary>
						</indexterm>
				TortoiseSVN integrates seamless into the Windows shell (i.e.
				the explorer). This means you can keep working with the tools
				you're already familiar with. And you do not have to change into
				a different application each time you need functions of the version
				control!
				</para>
					<para>
				And you are not even forced to use the Windows Explorer. Also in
				other filemanagers principally the context menu as well as the other
				functions of TortoiseSVN are readily available for you. Any time you
				want or need them. One should, however, bear in mind that TortoiseSVN
				is intentionally developed as extension for the Windows Explorer.
				Thus it is possible that in other applications the integration is
				not as complete and e. g. the icon overlays are not shown.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Icon overlays</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
				The status of every versioned file and folder is indicated
				by small overlay icons. That way you can see right away what
				the status of your working copy is.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Easy access to Subversion commands</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
				All Subversion commands are available from the explorer
				context menu. TortoiseSVN adds its own submenu there.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
		Since TortoiseSVN is a Subversion client, we also like to show you
		some of the features of Subversion itself:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Directory versioning</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>CVS only tracks the history of individual files,
				but Subversion implements a
				<quote>virtual</quote> versioned filesystem that tracks
				changes to whole directory trees over time.  Files
				<emphasis>and</emphasis> directories are versioned.  As a
				result, there are real client-side <command>move</command>
				and <command>copy</command> commands that operate on files
				and directories.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Atomic commits</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>A commit either goes into the repository completely,
				or not at all.  This allows developers to construct and
				commit changes as logical chunks.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Versioned metadata</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Each file and directory has an invisible set of
				<quote>properties</quote> attached.  You can invent and
				store any arbitrary key/value pairs you wish.  Properties
				are versioned over time, just like file contents.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Choice of network layers</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Subversion has an abstracted notion of repository
				access, making it easy for people to implement new network
				mechanisms.  Subversion's <quote>advanced</quote> network
				server is a module for the Apache web server, which speaks
				a variant of HTTP called WebDAV/DeltaV.  This gives
				Subversion a big advantage in stability and
				interoperability, and provides various key features for
				free: authentication, authorization, wire compression, and
				repository browsing, for example.  A smaller, standalone
				Subversion server process is also available.  This server speaks
				a custom protocol which can be easily tunneled over ssh.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Consistent data handling</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Subversion expresses file differences using a binary
				differencing algorithm, which works identically on both
				text (human-readable) and binary (human-unreadable) files.
				Both types of files are stored equally compressed in the
				repository, and differences are transmitted in both
				directions across the network.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Efficient branching and tagging</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
				The cost of branching and tagging need not be proportional to the
				project size.  Subversion creates branches and tags by
				simply copying the project, using a mechanism similar to a
				hard-link.  Thus these operations take only a very small,
				constant amount of time.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Hackability</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>Subversion has no historical baggage; it is
				implemented as a collection of shared C libraries with
				well-defined APIs.  This makes Subversion extremely
				maintainable and usable by other applications and
				languages.</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<!-- ======================== SECTION 4 ============================== -->
	<!-- ================================================================= -->
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ch-1-sect-4">
		<title>Installing TortoiseSVN</title>
		<sect2>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>install</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<title>System requirements</title>
			<para>
		TortoiseSVN runs on Windows 98/Me, Win2k SP2 or WinXP, IE5.5 or later.
		</para>
			<para>
		It also works on WinNT4 and Win95, but you need to have the IE4 shell extensions
		installed to get a newer shell version.
		Check the following FAQ entry <xref linkend="tsvn-faq-installation-1"/> to find out how.
		The minimum shell version is 4.72! We have reports that TortoiseSVN works on these
		old systems, but use it at your own risk.
		</para>
			<para>
		Win98/ME <emphasis>can not</emphasis> host BDB repositories, check the following Subversion FAQ entry
		<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/project_faq.html#portability">
					<citetitle>What operating systems does Subversion run on?</citetitle>
				</ulink> to find out why. However, you can use an Fsfs repository,
		introduced in Subversion 1.1.0.
		</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Installation</title>
			<para>
		TortoiseSVN comes with an easy to use installer. Doubleclick on the
		installer file and follow the instructions. The installer will take
		care of the rest. On WinNT, Win2K, WinXP and later, be sure to select
		the "Install for all users" option, unless you <emphasis>really</emphasis>
		want to restrict its use to the current user only.
		</para>
			<para>
				<indexterm>
					<primary>spellchecker</primary>
				</indexterm>
				<indexterm>
					<primary>thesaurus</primary>
				</indexterm>
		If you want to use a spell checker and/or thesaurus for your log messages
		then you have to download the required dictionaries yourself. You can use
		the same dictionary files as 
		<ulink url="http://openoffice.org">
					<citetitle>OpenOffice</citetitle>
				</ulink>
		and 
		<ulink url="http://mozilla.org">
					<citetitle>Mozilla</citetitle>
				</ulink> use.
		You can find the required dictionary files on various places:
		<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://lingucomponent.openoffice.org/spell_dic.html">
								<citetitle>http://lingucomponent.openoffice.org/spell_dic.html</citetitle>
							</ulink>
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<ulink url="http://lingucomponent.openoffice.org/thes_dic.html">
								<citetitle>http://lingucomponent.openoffice.org/thes_dic.html</citetitle>
							</ulink>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
		You can also use the dictionaries which get installed with Mozilla. They're
		located in the installation folder of Mozilla.
		</para>
			<para>
		Once you got the dictionary and thesaurus files, you probably need to
		rename them so that the filenames only have the locale chars in it.
		Example:
		<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>en_US.aff</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>en_US.dic</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>en_US.idx</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>en_US.dat</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
		Then just copy them to the installation folder of TortoiseSVN. The next
		time you start TortoiseSVN, the spell checker and thesaurus will be
		available.
		</para>
			<para>
		If you encounter any problems while or after installing TortoiseSVN
		please refer to <xref linkend="tsvn-faq"/> first.
		</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
<!--
local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
