<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-ignore">
	<title>Ignoring Files And Directories</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>ignore</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_IGNORE"?>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-ignoring-dia-1">
			<title>Explorer context menu for unversioned files</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/ContextMenuFileNoControl.png"/>
		</figure>
		In most projects you will have files and folders that should not be subject
		to version control. These might include files created by the compiler,
		<filename>*.obj, *.lst</filename>, maybe an output folder used to store
		the executable. Whenever you commit changes, TSVN shows your unversioned
		files, which fills up the file list in the commit dialog. Of course you
		can turn off this display, but then you might forget to add a new source
		file.
	</para>
	<para>
		The best way to avoid these problems is to add the derived files
		to the project's ignore list. That way they will never show up in
		the commit dialog, but genuine unversioned source files will still
		be flagged up.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you right click on a single unversioned file, and select the command
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenuitem>Ignore</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		from the context menu, a submenu appears allowing you to select just that
		file, or all files with the same extension.
		If you select multiple files, there is no submenu and you can only add
		those specific files/folders.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you want to remove a file from the ignore list, you need to edit
		the properties of the parent folder and remove the file from
		the <filename>svn:ignore</filename> property. Read
		<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-propertypage"/> for more information. 
	</para>
	<tip>
		<title>The Global Ignore List</title>
		<para>
			Another way to ignore files is to add them to the
			<firstterm>global ignore list</firstterm>. The big difference here
			is that the global ignore list is a client property.
			It applies to <emphasis>all</emphasis> Subversion projects, but on
			the client PC only. In general it is better to use the
			<filename>svn:ignore</filename> property where possible, because it
			can be applied to specific project areas, and it works for
			everyone who checks out the project. Read
			<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-settings"/> for more information. 
		</para>
	</tip>
</sect1>
