<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-ignore">
	<title>Ignoring Files And Directories</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>ignore</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_IGNORE"?>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-ignoring-dia-1">
			<title>Explorer context menu for unversioned files</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/ContextMenuFileNoControl.png"/>
		</figure>
		In most projects you will have files and folders that should not be subject
		to version control. These might include files created by the compiler,
		<filename>*.obj, *.lst</filename>, maybe an output folder used to store
		the executable. Whenever you commit changes, TSVN shows your unversioned
		files, which fills up the file list in the commit dialog. Of course you
		can turn off this display, but then you might forget to add a new source
		file.
	</para>
	<para>
		The best way to avoid these problems is to add the derived files
		to the project's ignore list. That way they will never show up in
		the commit dialog, but genuine unversioned source files will still
		be flagged up.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you <action>right click</action> on a single unversioned file,
		and select the command
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Add to Ignore List</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		from the context menu, a submenu appears allowing you to select just that
		file, or all files with the same extension.
		If you select multiple files, there is no submenu and you can only add
		those specific files/folders.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you want to remove one or more items from the ignore list,
		<action>right click</action> on those items and select
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Remove from Ignore List</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		You can also access a folder's <literal>svn:ignore</literal>
		property directly. That allows you to specify more general
		patterns using filename globbing, described in the section below.
		Read <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-propertypage"/> for more information
		on setting properties directly.
	</para>
	<tip>
		<title>The Global Ignore List</title>
		<para>
			Another way to ignore files is to add them to the
			<firstterm>global ignore list</firstterm>. The big difference here
			is that the global ignore list is a client property.
			It applies to <emphasis>all</emphasis> Subversion projects, but on
			the client PC only. In general it is better to use the
			<filename>svn:ignore</filename> property where possible, because it
			can be applied to specific project areas, and it works for
			everyone who checks out the project. Read
			<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-settings-main"/> for more information. 
		</para>
	</tip>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-ignore-glob">
		<title>Filename Globbing in Ignore Lists</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>globbing</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Subversion's ignore patterns make use of filename globbing,
			a technique originally used in Unix to specify files using
			meta-characters as wildcards. The following characters have
			special meaning:
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>*</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Matches any string of characters, including
							the empty string (no characters).
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>?</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Matches any single character.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>[...]</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Matches any one of the characters enclosed in the
							square brackets. Within the brackets, a pair of
							characters separated by <quote>-</quote>
							matches any character lexically between the two.
							For example <literal>[AGm-p]</literal> matches
							any one of <literal>A</literal>, <literal>G</literal>,
							<literal>m</literal>, <literal>n</literal>,
							<literal>o</literal> or <literal>p</literal>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
		<para>
			The globbing is done by Subversion, so the path delimiter
			is always <literal>/</literal>, not the Windows backslash.
		</para>
		<para>
			Pattern matching is case sensitive, which can cause problems
			on Windows. You can force case insensitivity the hard way
			by pairing characters, eg. to ignore <literal>*.tmp</literal>
			regardless of case, you could use a pattern like
			<literal>*.[Tt][Mm][Pp]</literal>.
		</para>
		<para>
			If directory names are present in a path, they are included
			in the matching, so pattern <literal>Fred.*</literal> will match
			<literal>Fred.c</literal> but not <literal>subdir/Fred.c</literal>.
			This is significant if you add a folder containing some files
			that you want to be ignored, because those filenames will be
			preceded with the folder name.
		</para>
		<para>
			To ignore all <literal>CVS</literal> folders you should either
			specify a pattern of <literal>*CVS</literal> or better, the pair
			<literal>CVS */CVS</literal>. The first option works, but would
			also exclude something called <literal>ThisIsNotCVS</literal>.
			Using <literal>*/CVS</literal> alone will not work on an
			immediate child <literal>CVS</literal> folder, and
			<literal>CVS</literal> alone will not work on subfolders.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want an official definition for globbing, you can find
			it in the IEEE specifications for the shell command language
			<ulink url="http://www.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/009695399/utilities/xcu_chap02.html#tag_02_13">
				<citetitle>Pattern Matching Notation</citetitle>
			</ulink>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
