<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-blame">
	<title>Who Changed Which Line?</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>blame</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>annotate</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>praise</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_BLAME"?>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-blame-dia-1">
			<title>The Annotate / Blame Dialog</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/BlameDialog.png"/>
		</figure>
		Sometimes you need to know not only what lines have changed, but also
		who exactly changed specific lines in a file. That's when the
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenuitem>Blame...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		command, sometimes also referred to as <firstterm>annotate</firstterm> command comes in handy.
	</para>
	<para>
		This command lists for every line in a file the author and the revision
		the line was changed.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you're not interested in changes from earlier revisions you can
		set the revision from which the blame should start. Set this to <literal>1</literal>,
		if you want the blame for <emphasis>every</emphasis> revision.
	</para>
	<para>
		By default the blame file is viewed using <firstterm>TortoiseBlame</firstterm>,
		which highlights the different revisions to make it easier to read. If you
		wish to print or edit the blame file, select <guilabel>Use Text viewer to view blames</guilabel>
	</para>
	<para>
		Once you press <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> TortoiseSVN starts retrieving
		the data to create the blame file. Please note: This can take several
		minutes to finish, depending on how much the file has changed and
		of course your network connection to the repository. Once the blame
		process has finished the result is written into a temporary file and
		you can view the results.
	</para>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-blame-dia-2">
			<title>TortoiseBlame</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/TortoiseBlame.png"/>
		</figure>
		TortoiseBlame, which is included with TortoiseSVN, makes the blame file
		easier to read. When you hover the mouse over a line in the blame info
		column, all lines with the same revision are shown with a darker
		background. Lines from other revisions which were changed by the same author
		are shown with a light background.
		The colouring may not work as clearly if you have your display set to
		256 colour mode.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you <action>left-click</action>
		on a line, all lines with the same revision are highlighted, and lines from
		other revisions by the same author are highlighted in a lighter colour.
		This highlighting is sticky, allowing you to move the mouse without losing
		the highlights. Click on that revision again to turn off highlighting.
	</para>
	<para>
		The revision comments are shown in a hint box whenever the mouse hovers over
		the blame info column.
	</para>
	<para>
		The example shows the first thirty lines of the file
		<filename>/Subversion/include/svn_io.h</filename> as of Revision 7566 from
		the Subversion source. For each line it shows the
		<literal>line number</literal>,
		<literal>revision</literal>,
		<literal>date of last commit</literal>, the
		<literal>author</literal> and of course the actual
		<literal>line</literal> in the file.
<screen>
line  rev    date              author     content

  0  4127 03:03:39, 15.12.2002 rooneg     /**
  1  4127 03:03:39, 15.12.2002 rooneg      * @copyright
  2  1224 21:24:10, 08.02.2002 kfogel      * ====================================================================
  3  4233 02:28:10, 03.01.2003 blair       * Copyright (c) 2000-2003 CollabNet.  All rights reserved.
  4     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         *
  5     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * This software is licensed as described in the file COPYING, which
  6     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * you should have received as part of this distribution.  The terms
  7     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * are also available at http://subversion.tigris.org/license-1.html.
  8     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * If newer versions of this license are posted there, you may use a
  9     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * newer version instead, at your option.
 10     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         *
 11     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * This software consists of voluntary contributions made by many
 12     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * individuals.  For exact contribution history, see the revision
 13     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * history and logs, available at http://subversion.tigris.org/.
 14     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         * ====================================================================
 15  4127 03:03:39, 15.12.2002 rooneg      * @endcopyright
 16  4127 03:03:39, 15.12.2002 rooneg      *
 17  4127 03:03:39, 15.12.2002 rooneg      * @file svn_io.h
 18  4127 03:03:39, 15.12.2002 rooneg      * @brief general Subversion I/O definitions

 19     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn         */
 20     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn
 21     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn        /* ==================================================================== */
 22     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn
 23     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn
 24     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn        #ifndef SVN_IO_H
 25     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn        #define SVN_IO_H

 26     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn
 27     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn        #include &lt;apr.h&gt;
 28     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn        #include &lt;apr_pools.h&gt;
 29     1 06:24:14, 31.08.2001 svn        #include &lt;apr_file_io.h&gt;
 30   303 03:26:32, 25.10.2001 cmpilato   #include &lt;apr_thread_proc.h&gt;
</screen>
	</para>
</sect1>
