<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-propertypage">
	<title>Get/Set Information About Files/Directories</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>properties</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-propertypage-dia-1">
			<title>Subversion property page</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/Properties.png"/>
		</figure>
		Sometimes you want to have a more detailed information
		about a file/directory than just the icon overlay.
		You can get all the information Subversion provides in the
		explorer properties dialog. Just select the file or
		directory and select
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		in the context menu (note: this is the normal properties menu entry
		the explorer provides, not in the TortoiseSVN submenu!).
		In the properties dialog box TortoiseSVN has added a new
		property page for files/folders under Subversion control.
	</para>
	<para>
		On the Subversion page you can see all relevant
		information about the selected file/directory. In
		addition you can read and set the subversion properties.
		You can add your own properties, or some properties with a 
		special meaning in subversion. These begin with <literal>svn:</literal>. 
		The <literal>svn:externals</literal> is such a property; see how to handle externals in 
		<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-import-4"/>.
		For more information about properties in subversion see the  
		<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/svnbook-1.1/ch07s02.html#svn-ch-7-sect-2.3">
			<citetitle>Subversion Manual</citetitle>
		</ulink>.
	</para>
	<para>
		TortoiseSVN has a few special properties of its own, and these begin
		with <literal>tsvn:</literal>.
		<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				<literal>tsvn:minlogmsgsize</literal>
				sets the minimum length of a log message for a commit.
				If you enter a shorter message than specified here, the commit is disabled.
				This feature is very useful for reminding you to supply a proper
				descriptive message for every commit. If this property is not set,
				or the value is zero, empty log messages are allowed.
			</para>
			<para>
				<literal>tsvn:logwidthmarker</literal> is used with projects which
				require log messages to be formatted with some maximum width
				(typically 80 characters) before a line break. Setting this
				property to a non-zero will do 2 things in the log message
				entry dialog: it places a marker to indicate the maximum width,
				and it disables word wrap in the display, so that you can see
				whether the text you entered is too long. Note: this feature
				will only work correctly if you have a fixed-width font
				selected for log messages.
			</para>
			<para>
				<literal>tsvn:logtemplate</literal> is used with projects which
				have rules about log message formatting. The property holds
				a multi-line text string which will be inserted in the commit
				message box when you start a commit. You can then edit it to
				include the required information. Note: if you are also using
				<literal>tsvn:minlogmsgsize</literal>, be sure to set the length
				longer than the template or you will lose the protection mechanism.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<important>
		<title>Set the properties on folders</title>
		<para>
			These <literal>tsvn:</literal> properties must be set on folders for the system to work. 
			When you commit a file or folder the properties are read from that folder.
			If the properties are not found there, TortoiseSVN will search upwards
			through the folder tree to find them until it comes to an unversioned
			folder, or the tree root (eg. <literal>C:\</literal>) is found.
			If you can be sure that each user checks out only from e.g
			<filename>trunk/</filename> and not some subfolder, then it's enough if
			you set the properties on <filename>trunk/</filename>.
			If you can't be sure, you should set the properties recursively on each subfolder.
			A property setting deeper in the project hierarchy overrides settings on
			higher levels (closer to <filename>trunk/</filename>).
		</para>
	</important>
	<note>
		<title>Commit properties</title>
		<para>
			Subversion properties are versioned. After you change or add a 
			property you have to commit your changes.
		</para>
	</note>
	<tip>
		<title>Conflicts on properties</title>
		<para>
			If there's a conflict on committing the changes, because another 
			user has changed the same property, Subversion generates a 
			<filename>.prej</filename> file. Delete this file after you 
			have resolved the conflict. 
		</para>
	</tip>
	<tip>
		<title>Automatic property setting</title>
		<para>
			You can configure subversion to set properties automatically 
			on files and folders when they are added to the repository.
			Read <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-settings"/> for further information. 
		</para>
	</tip>
	<para>
		<application>TortoiseSVN</application> can integrate with some bugtracking 
		tools. This uses properties, which start with <literal>bugtraq:</literal>.
		Read <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-bugtracker"/> for further information. 
	</para>
</sect1>
