<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-repobrowser">
	<title>The Repository Browser</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>repobrowser</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_REPOSITORY_BROWSER"?>
	<para>
		Sometimes you need to work directly on the repository, without having
		a working copy. That's what the <firstterm>Repository Browser</firstterm>
		is for. Just as the explorer and the icon overlays allow you to view your
		working copy, so the Repository Browser allows you to view the structure
		and status of the repository.
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-repobrowser-dia-1">
			<title>The Repository Browser</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/Repobrowser.png"/>
		</figure>
		With the Repository Browser you can execute commands like copy, move,
		rename, ... directly on the repository.
	</para>
	<para>
		At the top of the Repository Browser Window you can enter the URL of
		the repository and the revision you want to browse. Browsing an older
		revision is useful if you want to e.g. recover a previously deleted
		file. Use the 
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Copy To...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		command to do that and enter the full working copy path to where
		you want to recover your deleted file.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you select two items, you can view the differences either as a
		unified-diff, or as a list of files which can be visually diffed
		using the default diff tool. This can be particularly useful for
		comparing two tags to see what changed.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you select 2 tags which are copied from the same root
		(typically <literal>/trunk/</literal>), you can use
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Show Log...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		to view the list of revisions between the two tag points.
	</para>
	<para>
		You can also use the repository browser for drag-and-drop operations.
		If you drag a folder from explorer into the repo browser, it will be
		imported into the repository. Note that if you drag multiple items,
		they will be imported in separate commits.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you want to copy/move a file or folder to another location and also
		give it a new name at the same time, you can <action>right-drag</action>
		the item instead of just drag it. In that case, a rename dialog
		is shown where you can enter a new name for the file or folder.
	</para>
</sect1>
