<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-bugtracker">
	<title>Integration with Bugtracking Systems</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>bugtracking</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>bugtracker</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		You can integrate a Bugtracking Tool of your choice in
		<application>TortoiseSVN</application>. To do this, you have to define
		some properties, which start with <literal>bugtraq:</literal>.
		They must be set on Folders: (<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-propertypage"/>)
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:message</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>
							This property activates the Bugtracking System.
						</emphasis>
						If this property is set, then <application>TortoiseSVN</application>
						will prompt you to enter an issue number when you commit
						your changes. It's used to add a line at the end of the
						logmessage. It must contain
						<literal>%BUGID%</literal>, which is replaced with the
						issuenumber on commit. This ensures that your commit log
						contains a reference to the issuenumber which is always
						in a consistent format and can be parsed by your
						Bugtracking tool to associate the issuenumber with a
						particular commit. e.g the TortoiseSVN project is using
						<literal>Issue : %BUGID%</literal>, 
						but this depends on your Tool.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:append</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This property defines if the bug-ID is appended (true)
						to the end of the log message or inserted (false) at the
						start of the log message. Valid values are
						<literal>true/false</literal>.
						<emphasis>
							If not defined, <literal>true</literal> is assumed,
							so that existing projects don't break.
						</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:url</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Set this property to the url of your bugtracking tool.
						It must be properly URI encoded and it has to contain
						<literal>%BUGID%</literal>.
						<literal>%BUGID%</literal> is replaced with the Issuenumber
						you entered. This allows <application>TortoiseSVN</application>
						to display a link in the log dialog, so when you are looking
						at the revision log you can jump directly to your
						bugtracking tool.
						You do not have to provide this property, but then
						<application>TortoiseSVN</application> shows only the
						issuenumber and not the link to it.
						e.g the TortoiseSVN project is using
						<literal>http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/issues/show_bug.cgi?id=%BUGID%</literal>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:label</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This text is shown by <application>TortoiseSVN</application>
						on the commit dialog to label the edit box where you enter
						the issuenumber. If it's not set,
						<literal>Bug-ID / Issue-Nr:</literal> will be displayed.
						Keep in mind though that the window will not be resized
						to fit this label, so keep the size of the label below
						20-25 characters. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:number</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If set to <literal>true</literal> only numbers are allowed
						in the issuenumber textfield.
						An exception is the comma, so you can comma separate several
						numbers. Valid values are <literal>true/false</literal>. 
						<emphasis>
							If not defined, <literal>true</literal> is assumed.
						</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:warnifnoissue</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Set this to <literal>true</literal>, if you want
						<application>TortoiseSVN</application> to warn you
						because of an empty issuenumber textfield. Valid values 
						are <literal>true/false</literal>.
						<emphasis>
							If not defined, <literal>true</literal> is assumed.
						</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<important>
			<title>Set the Properties on Folders</title>
			<para>
				These properties must be set on folders for the system to work. 
				When you commit a file or folder the properties are read from that folder.
				If the properties are not found there, TortoiseSVN will search upwards
				through the folder tree to find them until it comes to an unversioned
				folder, or the tree root (eg. <literal>C:\</literal>) is found.
				If you can be sure that each user checks out only from e.g
				<filename>trunk/</filename> and not some subfolder, then it's enough if
				you set the properties on <filename>trunk/</filename>.
				If you can't be sure, you should set the properties recursively
				on each subfolder.
				A property setting deeper in the project hierarchy overrides settings on
				higher levels (closer to <filename>trunk/</filename>).
			</para>
		</important>
	</para>
</sect1>
