<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-wcstatus">
	<title>Getting Status Information</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>status</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		While you are working on your working copy you often need to know
		which files you have changed/added/removed or renamed, or even which
		files got changed and committed by others.
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-wcstatus-1">
		<title>Icon Overlays</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>overlays</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-wcstatus-dia-1">
				<title>Explorer showing icon overlays</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/Overlays.png"/>
			</figure>
			Now that you have checked out a working copy from a Subversion
			repository you can see your files in the windows explorer with
			changed icons. This is one of the reasons why TortoiseSVN is so
			popular. TortoiseSVN adds a so called overlay icon to each
			file icon which overlaps the original file icon. Depending on
			the Subversion status of the file the overlay icon is different.
		 	<graphic fileref="images/InSubVersionIcon.png"/>
			A fresh checked out working copy has a green checkmark as overlay.
			That means the Subversion status is <literal>normal</literal>.
			<graphic fileref="images/ModifiedIcon.png"/>
			As soon as you start editing a file,
			the status changes to <literal>modified</literal>
			and the icon overlay then changes to a red exclamation
			mark. That way you can easily see which files were changed
			since you last updated your working copy and need to be committed.
			<graphic fileref="images/ConflictIcon.png"/>
			If during an update a <literal>conflict</literal> occurs then
			the icon changes to a yellow exclamation mark.
			<graphic fileref="images/AddedIcon.png"/> 
			The plus sign tells you that a file or folder has been scheduled to be
			<literal>added</literal> to version control.
			<graphic fileref="images/DeletedIcon.png"/> 
			This Icon shows you that some files or folders inside the current folder
			have been scheduled do be <literal>deleted</literal> from version control
			or a file under version control is missing in a folder.
		</para>
		<para>
			The folder icons also have icon overlays displayed. By default,
			only the status of the folder itself is shown. But you can
			change that behaviour in the 
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			(<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-settings"/>),
			so that the status of folders is shown recursively. This will
			make the icon overlays for folders slower and is therefore
			not recommended on slower machines or large working copies.
		</para>
		<para>
			With this setting each folder shows the status of all files below it,
			where status <literal>conflict</literal> overrides
			<literal>modified</literal> and <literal>modified</literal> overrides
			<literal>normal</literal>. So you can easily see if there's a file
			with a conflict or a modified file in a folder.
			<tip>
				<title>Slow Overlays</title>
				<para>
					You may notice that if you enable the recursive overlay for folders
					that the explorer slows down remarkably when browsing working
					copies. This depends on how big your working copy is and how much
					RAM Windows can use for file index caching. Usually it's only
					very slow the first time you browse such a directory - if
					you browse the same directory later again it's much faster.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you want to disable the recursive overlays for some
					folders but not for all then you can do that by creating a
					file called <filename>_tsvnexcluderecursive</filename> inside
					that folder. This will disable the recursive overlays for
					that folder, but <emphasis>not</emphasis> for the files or
					folders inside it.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can also disable the overlays completely for a folder
					by creating a file called <filename>_tsvnexcludethis</filename>
					inside that folder. Again, this disables the overlays only
					for that folder, not the folders inside it.
					You can define specific paths to be excluded from showing overlays
					on the settings page
					(<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-settings-overlay"/>).
				</para>
			</tip>
		</para>
		<para>
			Unlike <application>TortoiseCVS</application> (the CVS shell
			integration) no overlay icon for unversioned files is shown.
			We do this because the number of icon overlays are limited system wide
			and should be used economically.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2>
		<title>TortoiseSVN Columns In Explorer</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>Explorer Columns</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			The same information which is available from the icon overlays
			(and much more) can be displayed as additional columns in
			Explorer's Detailed View.
		</para>
		<para>
			Simply right click on one of the headings of a column, choose
			<guimenuitem>More...</guimenuitem> from the context menu displayed. A
			dialog will appear where you can specify the columns and their
			order, which is displayed in the "Detailed View". Scroll down
			until the entries starting with SVN come into view. Check the
			ones you would like to have displayed and close the dialog by
			pressing <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The columns will be appended
			to the right of those currently displayed. You can reorder them by
			drag and drop, or resize them, so that they fit your needs.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				If you want the current layout to be displayed in all your
				working copies, you may want to make this the default view.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-wcstatus-2">
		<title>Status Of The Repository</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>status</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-wcstatus-dia-2">
				<title>Check for Modifications</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/RepoStatus.png"/>
			</figure>
			It's often very useful to know which files you have
			changed and also which files got changed and
			committed by others. That's where the command
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenuitem>Check For Modifications...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			comes in handy.
			This dialog will show you every file that has changed in any
			way in your working copy, as well as any unversioned files
			you may have. If you click on the
			<guibutton>Check Repository</guibutton> then you can also
			look for changes in the repository. That way
			you can check before an update if there's a possible conflict.
		</para>
		<para>
			From the context menu of the dialog you can show a diff of the
			changes or revert your local changes. TortoiseSVN automatically
			downloads the most recent version from the repository to do
			the diff.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-diffing">
		<title>Viewing Diffs</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>diffing</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Often you want to look inside your files, to have a look at what
			you've changed. You can accomplish this by selecting a file which
			has changed, and selecting <guimenuitem>Diff</guimenuitem> from
			TortoiseSVN's context menu. This starts the external
			diff-viewer, which will then compare the current file to it's
			contents, after the last checkout or update.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				Even when not inside a working copy or when you have multiple
				versions of the file lying around, you can still display diffs:
			</para>
			<para>
				Select the two files you want to compare in explorer
				(e.g. using <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and the mouse) and
				choose <guimenuitem>Diff</guimenuitem> from TortoiseSVN's
				context menu. The file clicked last (the one with the focus,
				i.e. the dotted rectangle) will be regarded as the later
				one. 
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
