<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-merge">
	<title>Merging</title>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_MERGE"?>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>merge</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		Where branches are used to maintain separate lines of development,
		at some stage you will want to merge the changes made on one branch
		back into the trunk, or vice versa.
	</para>
	<para>
		It is important to understand how branching and merging works in
		subversion before you start using it, as it can become quite complex.
		It is highly recommended that you read the chapter
		<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.1/ch04.html">
			<citetitle>Branching and Merging</citetitle>
		</ulink>
		in the
		<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">
			<citetitle>Subversion Book</citetitle>
		</ulink>
		which gives a full description, and many examples of how it is used.
	</para>
	<para>
		There are two common use cases for merging which are handled in
		slightly different ways, as described below.
	</para>
	
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-merge-2">
		<title>Merging a Range of Revisions</title>
		<para>
			This method covers the case when you have made one or more
			revisions to a branch (or to the trunk) and you want to port
			those changes across to a different branch.
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-merge-dia-1">
				<title>The Merge Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/Merge.png"/>
			</figure>
			To merge revisions you need to go to a working copy of the
			branch in which you want to receive the changes, often the trunk.
			Select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenuitem>Merge...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			from the context menu.
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>From:</guilabel> field enter the full
						folder url of the branch or tag containing the changes
						you want to port into your working copy.
						You may also click
						<guibutton>...</guibutton>
						to browse the repository and find the desired branch.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Because you are porting a range of revisions from
						the same branch into your working copy, make sure the
						<guilabel>Use "From:" URL</guilabel> checkbox is
						checked.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>From Revision</guilabel> field enter the
						initial revision number. This is the revision
						<emphasis>before</emphasis> the changes you want to merge.
						Revision numbers are auto-incremented after each commit.
						You want to start merging the changes before the revision
						number is auto-incremented. For example,
						if your log messages look something like this:
<screen>
Rev Comments
39. Working on MyBranch
38. Working on trunk
37. Working on MyBranch
36. Create branch MyBranch
35. Working on trunk
34. Working on trunk
         ...
</screen>
						If you now want to merge the changes from MyBranch into
						the trunk you have to choose 36 as the
						<guilabel>From Revision</guilabel>. Not 37 as you might think.
					</para>
					<para>
						The easiest way to find the revision you need is to
						click on <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton>, as this will
						list recent changes with their log comments. Select the
						revision you require in the Show Log dialog, then
						click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>To Revision</guilabel> field enter the
						last revision number in the range you want to merge.
						Often this will be the HEAD revision, although it doesn't
						need to be - you can just want to merge a single revision.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to complete the merge.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			The merge is now complete. It's a good idea to have a look at the
			merge and see if it's as expected. Merging is usually quite complicated.
			Conflicts often arise if the branch has drifted far from the trunk.
		</para>
		<para>
			When you have tested the changes and come to commit this revision,
			your commit log message should <emphasis>always</emphasis>
			include the revision numbers which have been ported in the merge.
			If you want to apply another merge at a later time you will need to
			know what you have already merged, as you do not want to port a
			change more than once. Unfortunately merge information is not
			stored by Subversion. For more information about this, refer to
			<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.1/ch04s03.html#svn-ch-4-sect-3.2.1">
				<citetitle>Tracking Merges Manually</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			in the
			<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">
				<citetitle>Subversion Book</citetitle>
			</ulink>
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to keep this branch up to date with the trunk, you should
			immediately merge changes from trunk back to the this branch. Use
			this method and local changes won't get in your way. Of course, you
			should still avoid repeated merging of trunk changes, as explained above.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to see what changes will be made by a merge and see where
			possible conflicts may occur you can check the option
			<guibutton>
				Dry Run
			</guibutton>.
			This will force the merge command to do a merge, but <emphasis>not</emphasis>
			modify the working copy at all.
		</para>
		<important>
			<para>
				Subversion can't merge a file with a folder and vice versa - only
				folders to folders and files to files. If you click on a file and
				open up the merge dialog, then you have to give a path to a file
				in that dialog. If you select a folder and bring up the dialog,
				then you must specify a folder url for the merge.
			</para>
		</important>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-merge-3">
		<title>Merging Two Different Trees</title>
		<para>
			This method covers the case when you have made a feature branch
			as discussed in the Subversion book. All trunk changes have been
			ported to the feature branch, week by week, and now the feature
			is complete you want to merge it back into the trunk. Because
			you have kept the feature branch synchronized with the trunk,
			the latest versions of branch and trunk will be absolutely
			identical except for your branch changes. So in this special case,
			you would merge by comparing the branch with the trunk.
		</para>
		<para>
			<!-- There may be a different version of the dialog for this case.
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-merge-dia-1">
				<title>The Merge Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/Merge.png"/>
			</figure>
			-->
			To merge the feature branch back into the trunk you need to go to
			a working copy of the trunk.
			Select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenuitem>Merge...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			from the context menu.
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>From:</guilabel> field enter the full
						folder url of the <emphasis>trunk</emphasis>. This
						may sound wrong, but remember that the trunk is the
						start point to which you want to add the branch changes.
						You may also click
						<guibutton>...</guibutton>
						to browse the repository.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Because you are comparing two different trees, make sure
						the <guilabel>Use "From:" URL</guilabel> checkbox is
						<emphasis>not</emphasis> checked.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>To:</guilabel> field enter the full
						folder url of the feature branch.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In both the <guilabel>From Revision</guilabel> field and
						the <guilabel>To Revision</guilabel> field, enter the
						last revision number at which the two trees were
						synchronized. If you are sure no-one else is making
						commits you can use the HEAD revision in both cases.
						If there is a chance that someone else may have made
						a commit since that synchronization, use the specific
						revision number to avoid losing more recent commits.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to complete the merge.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			In this case you will not need the feature branch again
			because the new feature is now integrated into the trunk.
			The feature branch is redundant and can be deleted
			from the repository if required.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
