<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-propertypage">
	<title>Get/Set Information About Files/Directories</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>properties</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-propertypage-dia-1">
			<title>Subversion property page</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/Properties.png"/>
		</figure>
		Sometimes you want to have a more detailed information
		about a file/directory than just the icon overlay.
		You can get all the information Subversion provides in the
		explorer properties dialog. Just select the file or
		directory and select
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		in the context menu (note: this is the normal properties menu entry
		the explorer provides, not in the TortoiseSVN submenu!).
		In the properties dialog box TortoiseSVN has added a new
		property page for files/folders under Subversion control.
	</para>
	<para>
		On the Subversion page you can see all relevant
		information about the selected file/directory. In
		addition you can read and set the subversion properties.
		You can add your own properties or some properties with a 
		special meaning in subversion, they begin with <literal>svn:</literal>. 
		The <literal>svn:externals</literal> is such a property see how to handle externals in 
		<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-import-4"/>.
		For more information about properties in subversion see the  
		<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/svnbook/ch07s02.html#svn-ch-7-sect-2.3">
			<citetitle>Subversion Manual</citetitle>
		</ulink>.
		</para>
	<note>
		<title>commit properties</title>
		<para>
			Subversion properties are versioned. After you changed or added a 
			property you have to commit your changes.
		</para>
	</note>
	<tip>
		<title>Conflicts on properties</title>
		<para>
			If there's a conflict on committing the changes, because another 
			user has changed the same property Subversion generates a 
			<filename>.prej</filename> file. Delete this file after you 
			resolved the conflict. 
		</para>
	</tip>
	<para>
		<application>TortoiseSVN</application> could integrate with some bugtracking 
		tools. This happens with properties, which start with <literal>bugtraq:</literal>. Please read 
		on <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-bugtracker"/> for further information. 
	</para>
</sect1>
