<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-commit">
	<title>Sending Your Changes To The Repository</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>commit</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_LOGPROMPT"?>
	<para>
		Sending the changes you made to your working copy is known as
		<firstterm>committing</firstterm> the changes. But before you
		commit you have to make sure that your working copy is up to
		date. You can either use
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Update</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		directly. Or you can use
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Check for Modifications</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		first, to see which files have changed locally or on the server.
	</para>
	<para>
		If your working copy is up to date and there are no conflicts,
		you are ready to commit your changes. Select any file
		and/or folders you want to commit, then
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Commit...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-commit-dia-1">
			<title>The Commit dialog</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/CommitContextMenu.png"/>
		</figure>
	</para>
	<para>
		The commit dialog will show you every changed file,
		including added, deleted and unversioned files. If you don't
		want a changed file to be committed, just uncheck that
		file. If you want to include an unversioned file,
		just check that file to add it to the commit.
		<tip>
			<title>Commit files or folders?</title>
			<para>
				When you commit files, the commit dialog shows only
				the files you have selected. When you commit a folder
				the commit dialog will select the changed files automatically.
				If you forget about a new file you created, committing the
				folder will find it anyway. Committing a folder does <emphasis>not</emphasis>
				mean that every file gets marked as changed; It just makes
				your life easier by doing more work for you.
			</para>
		</tip>
		<tip>
			<title>Many unversioned files in the commit dialog</title>
			<para>
				If you think that the TSVN commit dialog shows you too
				many unversioned (e.g. compiler generated or editor backup)
				files, there are several ways to handle this. You can:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							add the file (or a wildcard extension)
							to the list of files to exclude on the settings page.
							This will affect every working copy you have.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							add the file to the <literal>svn:ignore</literal> list
							using
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
								<guimenuitem>Add to ignore list</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>
							This will only affect the directory on
							which you set the <literal>svn:ignore</literal> property.
							Using the SVN Property Dialog, you can alter the
							<literal>svn:ignore</literal> property for a directory.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
				Read <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-ignore"/> for more information. 
			</para>
		</tip>
	</para>
	<para>
		<action>Doubleclicking</action> on any modified file in the commit
		dialog will launch the external diff tool to show your changes.
	</para>
	<para>
		After pressing <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, a dialog appears displaying
		the progress of the commit.
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-commit-dia-3">
			<title>The Progress dialog showing a commit in progress</title>
			<graphic fileref="images/CommitProgress.png"/>
		</figure>
	</para>
	<para>
		The progress dialog uses colour coding to highlight different
		commit actions
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Blue</term>
				<listitem>
					Committing a modification or a new item.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Dark red</term>
				<listitem>
					Committing a deletion or a replacement.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Black</term>
				<listitem>
					All other items.
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</para>
	<tip>
		<title>Special Folder Properties</title>
		<para>
			There are several special folder properties which can be used to
			help give more control over the formatting of commit log messages and
			the language used by the spellchecker module.
			Read <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-propertypage"/> for further information.
		</para>
	</tip>
	<tip>
		<title>Integration with Bugtracking Tools</title>
		<para>
			If you have activated the bugtracking system, you could set one or more 
			Issues in the <guilabel>Bug-ID / Issue-Nr:</guilabel> Textfield. Several Issues 
			should be comma separated. Learn more <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-bugtracker"/>.
		</para>
	</tip>
</sect1>
