<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-settings">
	<title>TortoiseSVN's Settings</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>settings</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		To find out what the different settings are for, just leave your
		mouse pointer a second on the editbox/checkbox... and a helpful
		tooltip will popup.
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-settings-main">
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSMAIN"?>
		<title>The Settings Dialog, Main Tab</title>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-settings-dia-1">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Main Tab</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/SettingsMain.png"/>
			</figure>
			Apart from setting your preferred language, this dialog allows you to
			specify (almost) every setting TortoiseSVN has. 
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Language</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Selects your user interface language.
							What else did you expect?
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Exclude pattern</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<indexterm>
								<primary>exclude pattern</primary>
							</indexterm>
							Exclude patterns are used to prevent unversioned files from
							showing up e.g. in the commit dialog. Files matching the
							patterns are also ignored by an import.
							Exclude files or directories by typing in the names or extensions.
							Patterns are separated by spaces e.g.
							<literal>bin obj *.bak *.~?? *.jar *.[Tt]mp</literal>.
							The first two entries refer to directories, the 
							other four to files.
						</para>
						<para>
							This exclude pattern will affect all your projects. It is not versioned, so it 
							will not affect other users. In contrast you can also use the versioned <literal>svn:ignore</literal> 
							property to exclude files or directories from version control. You can set the <literal>svn:ignore</literal> 
							property using the 
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenuitem>Add to Ignore List</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>
							command. After commiting every other user will have the same 
							<literal>svn:ignore</literal> property set for this project / directory as you.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Default number of log messages</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Limits the number of log messages that TortoiseSVN fetches when you first select
							<menuchoice>
								<guimenuitem>Show Log</guimenuitem>
							</menuchoice>
							Useful for slow connections / servers. You can always
							<guibutton>Fetch All</guibutton> messages.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Edit...</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							... the subversion configuration file directly.
							Some settings cannot be modified by TortoiseSVN.
							For more information about the subversion
							<filename>config</filename> file see the  
							<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/svnbook-1.1/ch07.html#svn-ch-7-sect-1.3.2">
							<citetitle>Subversion Manual</citetitle></ulink>. The section on
							<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/svnbook-1.1/ch07s02.html#svn-ch-7-sect-2.4">
							<citetitle>Automatic Property Setting</citetitle></ulink>
							is of particular interest, and that is configured here.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Short date / time format in log messages</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							If the standard long messages use up too much 
							space on your screen use the short format.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Set filedates to "last commit time"</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This option tells TortoiseSVN to set the filedates to the last commit time 
							when doing a checkout or an update. Otherwise TortoiseSVN will use 
							the current date.
							If you are developing software it is generally best to use the current date
							because build systems normally look at the datestamps to decide which
							files need compiling. If you use "last commit time" and revert to an
							older file revision, your project may not compile as you expect it to.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Close windows automatically</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							TortoiseSVN will automatically close all progress dialogs 
							when the action is finished without error.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Don't close on conflicts</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Automatic window closing is suppressed if there were
							conflicts during an update. This option is highly
							recommended to avoid missing conflict reports.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Check for newer versions</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							If checked, TortoiseSVN will check once a week if an update is available
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Show BugID/Issue-Nr. Box</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Shows a textbox in the commit dialog where you can enter
							a BugID or Issue-Nr. from a bugtracker to associate the
							commit with that ID/number.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Paste Log template in english</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							This only applies if you have selected a language other
							than english for TortoiseSVN. In that case, when pasting
							the log template in the commit dialog, the status of each
							file is pasted in the selected language. With this option
							checked, the status is pasted in english.
							This is useful if your project requires all log messages
							to be in english.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-settings-overlay">
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSOVERLAY"?>
		<title>The Settings Dialog, Look and Feel Tab</title>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-settings-dia-2">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Look and Feel Tab</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/SettingsOverlay.png"/>
			</figure>
			This tab allows you to choose the items for which TortoiseSVN will
			display icon overlays. If you feel that your icon overlays are very 
			slow (explorer is not responsive), uncheck the
			"Recurse into folders to fetch the status" box.
			You can even disable all icon overlays, but where's the fun in that?
		</para>
		<para>
			The <guilabel>Exclude Paths</guilabel> are used to tell TortoiseSVN for which
			paths <emphasis>not</emphasis> to show icon overlays and status columns.
			This is useful if you have some very big working copies containing
			only libraries which you won't change at all and therefore don't
			need the overlays. For example:
		</para>
		<para>
			<filename>f:\development\SVN\Subversion</filename> will disable
			the overlays on <emphasis>only</emphasis> that specific folder. You
			still can see the overlays on all files and folder inside that folder.
		</para>
		<para>
			<filename>f:\development\SVN\Subversion*</filename> will disable the
			overlays on <emphasis>all</emphasis> files and folders whose path
			starts with <filename>f:\development\SVN\Subversion</filename>. That
			means you won't see overlays for any files and folders below that
			path.
		</para>
		<para>
			The same applies to the <guilabel>Include Paths</guilabel>. Only that for those
			paths the overlays are shown even if the overlays are disabled for
			that specific drive type.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can also specify here which of the TortoiseSVN context menu
			entries will show up in the main context menu.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-settings-network">
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSPROXY"?>
		<title>The Settings Dialog, Network Tab</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>proxy server</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-settings-dia-4">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Network Tab</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/SettingsProxy.png"/>
			</figure>
			Here you can configure your proxy server, if you need one to get through your company's firewall.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can also specify which program TortoiseSVN should use to establish a secure connection to a svn+ssh repository.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-settings-progs">
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSPROGS"?>
		<title>The Settings Dialog, Diff/Merge Tab</title>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-settings-dia-5">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Diff/Merge Tab</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/SettingsProgs.png"/>
			</figure>
			Here you can define your own diff/merge programs that TortoiseSVN should use.
			The basic setting is to use the builtin TortoiseMerge which is installed alongside TortoiseSVN.
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Diff Program</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							An external diff program used for comparing different revisions of files.
							You can specify the following parameters to the path:
							<variablelist>
								<varlistentry>
									<term>%base</term>
									<listitem>
										<para>
											The original file without your changes
										</para>
									</listitem>
								</varlistentry>
								<varlistentry>
									<term>%mine</term>
									<listitem>
										<para>
											Your own file, with your changes
										</para>
									</listitem>
								</varlistentry>
							</variablelist>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Merge Program</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							An external merge program used to resolve conflicted files. You can specify the 
							following parameters to the path. The order of the parameters depends on the 
							merge program you use.
							<variablelist>
								<varlistentry>
									<term>%base</term>
									<listitem>
										<para>
											the original file without your or the others changes
										</para>
									</listitem>
								</varlistentry>
								<varlistentry>
									<term>%mine</term>
									<listitem>
										<para>
											your own file, with your changes
										</para>
									</listitem>
								</varlistentry>
								<varlistentry>
									<term>%theirs</term>
									<listitem>
										<para>
											the file as it is in the repository
										</para>
									</listitem>
								</varlistentry>
								<varlistentry>
									<term>%merged</term>
									<listitem>
										<para>
											the conflicted file, the result of the merge operation
										</para>
									</listitem>
								</varlistentry>
							</variablelist>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Diff Viewer</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							A viewer program for GNU diff files (patch files).
							If you don't have one the builtin option is to use NotePad.
							No Parameters.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-settings-dia-6">
				<title>The Settings Dialog, Diff/Merge Advanced Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="images/SettingsProgsAdv.png"/>
			</figure>
			In the advanced settings, you can define a different diff and merge program for every file extension. 
			For instance you could associate Photoshop as the "Diff" Program for .jpg files :-)
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
