<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-commit">
	<title>Sending Your Changes To The Repository</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>commit</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_LOGPROMPT"?>
	<para>
		Sending the changes you made to your working copy is known as
		<firstterm>committing</firstterm> the changes. But before you
		commit you have to make sure that your working copy is up to
		date. You can either use
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Update</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		directly. Or you can use
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Check for Modifications</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		first, to see which files have changed locally or on the server.
	</para>
	<para>
		If your working copy is up to date and there are no conflicts,
		you are ready to commit your changes. Select any file
		and/or folders you want to commit, then
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Commit...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-commit-dia-1">
			<title>The Commit dialog</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/Commit.png"/>
		</figure>
	</para>
	<para>
		The commit dialog will show you every changed file,
		including added, deleted and unversioned files. If you don't
		want a changed file to be committed, just uncheck that
		file. If you want to include an unversioned file,
		just check that file to add it to the commit.
	</para>
	<para>
		Items which have been switched to a different repository path are
		also indicated using an <literal>(s)</literal> marker. You may have
		switched something while working on a branch and forgotten to switch
		back to trunk. This is your warning sign!
	</para>
	<tip>
		<title>Commit files or folders?</title>
		<para>
			When you commit files, the commit dialog shows only
			the files you have selected. When you commit a folder
			the commit dialog will select the changed files automatically.
			If you forget about a new file you created, committing the
			folder will find it anyway. Committing a folder does <emphasis>not</emphasis>
			mean that every file gets marked as changed; It just makes
			your life easier by doing more work for you.
		</para>
	</tip>
	<para>
		If you have modified files which have been included from a different
		repository using <literal>svn:externals</literal>, those changes cannot
		be included in the same atomic commit. A warning symbol below the file
		list tells you if this has happened, and the tooltip explains that
		those external files have to be committed separately.
	</para>
	<tip>
		<title>Many unversioned files in the commit dialog</title>
		<para>
			If you think that the TSVN commit dialog shows you too
			many unversioned (e.g. compiler generated or editor backup)
			files, there are several ways to handle this. You can:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						add the file (or a wildcard extension)
						to the list of files to exclude on the settings page.
						This will affect every working copy you have.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						add the file to the <literal>svn:ignore</literal> list
						using
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Add to ignore list</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice>
						This will only affect the directory on
						which you set the <literal>svn:ignore</literal> property.
						Using the SVN Property Dialog, you can alter the
						<literal>svn:ignore</literal> property for a directory.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-ignore"/> for more information. 
		</para>
	</tip>
	<para>
		<action>Doubleclicking</action> on any modified file in the commit
		dialog will launch the external diff tool to show your changes.
		The context menu will give you more options, as shown in the screenshot.
		You can also drag files from here into another application such as a
		text editor or an IDE.
	</para>
	<para>
		The columns displayed in the bottom pane are customizable. If you
		<action>right click</action> on any column header you will see a
		context menu allowing you to select which columns are displayed.
		You can also change column width by using the drag handle which
		appears when you move the mouse over a column boundary. These
		customizations are preserved, so you will see the same headings
		next time.
		Note that due to an implementation detail, you may see two different
		drag icons, depending on exactly where you position the mouse over the
		boundary. One has a solid vertical dividing line and the other has two
		thin vertical lines. Only the solid drag pointer works.
	</para>
	<para>
		Be sure to enter a log message which describes the changes you are
		committing. This will help you to see what happened and when, as you
		browse through the project log messages at a later date. The message
		can be as long or as brief as you like; many projects have guidelines
		for what should be included, the language to use, and sometimes even
		a strict format.
	</para>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-commit-dia-2">
			<title>The Commit Dialog Spellchecker</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/CommitSpellcheck.png"/>
		</figure>
		TortoiseSVN includes a spellchecker to help you get your log messages
		right. This will highlight any mis-spelled words. Use the context menu
		to access the suggested corrections. Of course, it doesn't know
		<emphasis>every</emphasis> technical term that you do, so correctly
		spelt words will sometimes show up as errors. But don't worry. You can
		just add them to your personal dictionary using the context menu.
	</para>
	<para>
		The log message window also includes a filename and function auto-completion
		facility. This uses regular expressions to extract class and function names
		from the (text) files you are committing, as well as the filenames themselves.
		If a word you are typing matches anything in the list (after you have typed at
		least 3 characters), a drop-down appears allowing you to select the full name.
		The regular expressions supplied with TortoiseSVN are held in the TortoiseSVN
		installation <filename>bin</filename> folder. You can also define your own
		regexes and store them in <filename>%APPDATA%\TortoiseSVN\autolist.txt</filename>.
		Of course your private autolist will not be overwritten when you update your
		installation of TortoiseSVN. If you are unfamiliar with regular expressions,
		take a look at the online documentation and tutorial at
		<ulink url="http://www.regular-expressions.info/">
			<citetitle>http://www.regular-expressions.info/</citetitle>
		</ulink>.
	</para>
	<para>
		After pressing <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, a dialog appears displaying
		the progress of the commit.
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-commit-dia-3">
			<title>The Progress dialog showing a commit in progress</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/CommitProgress.png"/>
		</figure>
	</para>
	<para>
		The progress dialog uses colour coding to highlight different
		commit actions
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Blue</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Committing a modification.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Purple</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Committing a new addition.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Dark red</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Committing a deletion or a replacement.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Black</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					All other items.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</para>
	<para>
		This is the default colour scheme, but you can customise those colours
		using the settings dialog.
		Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-settings-colours"/> for more information.
	</para>
	<tip>
		<title>Special Folder Properties</title>
		<para>
			There are several special folder properties which can be used to
			help give more control over the formatting of commit log messages and
			the language used by the spellchecker module.
			Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-propertypage"/> for further information.
		</para>
	</tip>
	<tip>
		<title>Integration with Bugtracking Tools</title>
		<para>
			If you have activated the bugtracking system, you could set one or more 
			Issues in the <guilabel>Bug-ID / Issue-Nr:</guilabel> Textfield. Several Issues 
			should be comma separated. Learn more <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-bugtracker"/>.
		</para>
	</tip>
</sect1>
