<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-general">
	<title>Getting Started</title>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-general-menu">
		<title>Context Menus</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>context menu</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-context-dir-control">
				<title>Context menu for a directory under version control</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/ContextMenuDirControl.png"/>
			</figure>
			All TortoiseSVN commands are invoked from the context menu of the windows
			explorer. Most are directly visible, when you <action>right click</action>
			on a file or folder. The commands that are available depend on whether the
			file or folder or its parent folder is under version control or not.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-general-drag">
		<title>Drag and Drop</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>drag handler</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>drag-n-drop</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-right-drag">
				<title>Right drag menu for a directory under version control</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/RightDragMenu.png"/>
			</figure>
			Other commands are available as drag handlers, when you <action>right drag</action>
			files or folders to a new location inside working copies or when you 
			<action>right drag</action> a non-versioned file or folder into a directory 
			which is under version control.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-general-auth">
		<title>Authentication</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>authentication</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			If the repository that you are trying to access is password protected, an 
			authentication Dialog will show up.
			<figure id="tsvn-fig-authentication">
				<title>Authentication Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/Authenticate.png"/>
			</figure>
			Enter your username and password. The checkbox will make TortoiseSVN
			store the credentials in Subversion's default directory: 
			<filename>$APPDATA\Subversion\auth</filename> in three subdirectories:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>svn.simple</filename> contains credentials
						for basic authentication (username/password).
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>svn.ssl.server</filename> contains
						SSL server certificates.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<filename>svn.username</filename> contains credentials
						for username-only authentication (no password needed).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			There is one file for each server that you access, formatted as
			plain text, so you can use a text editor to check which server
			it applies to. If you want to make Subversion and TortoiseSVN
			(and any other Subversion client) forget your credentials for
			a particular server, you have to delete the corresponding file.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to clear the authentication cache for <emphasis>all</emphasis>
			servers, you can do so from the <guilabel>General</guilabel> page
			of TortoiseSVN's settings dialog. That button will clear all cached
			auth data from the Subversion auth directories, as well as any auth
			data stored in the registry by earlier versions of TortoiseSVN.
			Refer to <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-settings-main"/>.
		</para>
		<para>
			For more information on how to set up your server for
			authentication and access control, refer to
			<xref linkend="tsvn_serversetup"/>
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
				If you have to authenticate against a Windows NT domain,
				enter your username including the domain name, like:
				<filename>MYDOMAIN/johnd</filename>.
			</para>
		</tip>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
