<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-bugtracker">
	<title>Integration with Bugtracking Systems / Issue trackers</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>bugtracking</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>bugtracker</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>issuetracker</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		It is very common in Software Development for changes to be related to a specific
		bug or issue ID. Users of bug tracking systems (issue trackers) would like to associate
		the changes they make in Subversion with a specific ID in their issue tracker.
		Most issue trackers therefore provide a pre-commit hook script which parses the log
		message to find the bug ID with which the commit is associated.
		This is somewhat error prone since it relies on the user to write the log message
		properly so that the pre-commit hook script can parse it correctly.
	</para>
	<para>
		TortoiseSVN can help the user in two ways:
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					When the user enters a log message, a well defined line including
					the issue number associated with the commit can be added automatically.
					This reduces the risk that the user enters the issue number in a way
					the bug tracking tools can't parse correctly.
				</para>
				<para>
					Or TortoiseSVN can highlight the part of
					the entered log message which is recognized by the issue tracker.
					That way the user knows that the log message can be parsed correctly.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					When the user browses the log messages, TortoiseSVN
					creates a link out of each bug ID in the log message which fires
					up the browser to the issue mentioned.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
		You can integrate a Bugtracking Tool of your choice in
		TortoiseSVN. To do this, you have to define
		some properties, which start with <literal>bugtraq:</literal>.
		They must be set on Folders: (<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-propertypage"/>)
	</para>
	<para>
		There are two ways to integrate TortoiseSVN with issue trackers. One is
		based on simple strings, the other is based on <literal>regular expressions</literal>.
		The properties used by both approaches are:
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:url</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Set this property to the url of your bugtracking tool.
						It must be properly URI encoded and it has to contain
						<literal>%BUGID%</literal>.
						<literal>%BUGID%</literal> is replaced with the Issuenumber
						you entered. This allows TortoiseSVN
						to display a link in the log dialog, so when you are looking
						at the revision log you can jump directly to your
						bugtracking tool.
						You do not have to provide this property, but then
						TortoiseSVN shows only the
						issuenumber and not the link to it.
						e.g the TortoiseSVN project is using
						<literal>http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/issues/show_bug.cgi?id=%BUGID%</literal>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:warnifnoissue</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Set this to <literal>true</literal>, if you want
						TortoiseSVN to warn you
						because of an empty issuenumber textfield. Valid values 
						are <literal>true/false</literal>.
						<emphasis>
							If not defined, <literal>false</literal> is assumed.
						</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</para>
	<para>
		In the simple approach, TortoiseSVN shows the user
		a separate input field where a bug ID can be entered. Then a separate line
		is appended/prepended to the log message the user entered.
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:message</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis>
							This property activates the Bugtracking System.
						</emphasis>
						If this property is set, then TortoiseSVN
						will prompt you to enter an issue number when you commit
						your changes. It's used to add a line at the end of the
						logmessage. It must contain
						<literal>%BUGID%</literal>, which is replaced with the
						issuenumber on commit. This ensures that your commit log
						contains a reference to the issuenumber which is always
						in a consistent format and can be parsed by your
						Bugtracking tool to associate the issuenumber with a
						particular commit. e.g the TortoiseSVN project is using
						<literal>Issue : %BUGID%</literal>, 
						but this depends on your Tool.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:append</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This property defines if the bug-ID is appended (true)
						to the end of the log message or inserted (false) at the
						start of the log message. Valid values are
						<literal>true/false</literal>.
						<emphasis>
							If not defined, <literal>true</literal> is assumed,
							so that existing projects don't break.
						</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:label</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This text is shown by TortoiseSVN
						on the commit dialog to label the edit box where you enter
						the issuenumber. If it's not set,
						<literal>Bug-ID / Issue-Nr:</literal> will be displayed.
						Keep in mind though that the window will not be resized
						to fit this label, so keep the size of the label below
						20-25 characters. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:number</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If set to <literal>true</literal> only numbers are allowed
						in the issuenumber textfield.
						An exception is the comma, so you can comma separate several
						numbers. Valid values are <literal>true/false</literal>. 
						<emphasis>
							If not defined, <literal>true</literal> is assumed.
						</emphasis>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</para>
	<para>
		In the approach with <literal>regular expressions</literal>, TortoiseSVN
		doesn't show a separate input field but marks the part of the log message the user
		enters which is recognized by the issue tracker. This is done while the user
		writes the log message. This also means that the bug ID can be anywhere inside a log
		message!
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>bugtraq:logregex</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This property contains one or two regular expressions, separated
						by a newline.
					</para>
					<para>
						If only one expression is set, then the bare bug ID's must be matched
						in the groups of the regex string. Example:
						<literal>[Ii]ssue(?:s)? #?(\d+)</literal>
					</para>
					<para>
						If two expressions are set, then the first expression is used to find
						a string which relates to the bug ID but may contain more than just
						the bug ID (e.g. "Issue #123" or "resolves issue 123").
						The second expression is then used to extract the bare bug ID from the string
						extracted with the first expression.
						An example:
					</para>
					<para>
						If you want to catch every pattern "issue #XXX" and "issue #890, #789"
						inside a log message you could use the following regex strings:
						<literal>[Ii]ssue #?(\d+)(,? ?#'(\d+))+</literal> and the second expression as
						<literal>(\d+)</literal>
					</para>
					<para>
						If you are unfamiliar with regular expressions, take a look at
						the online documentation and tutorial at
						<ulink url="http://www.regular-expressions.info/">
							<citetitle>http://www.regular-expressions.info/</citetitle>
						</ulink>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</para>
	<tip>
		<para>
			Even if you don't have an issue tracker with a pre-commit hook parsing your
			log messages, you still can use this to turn the issues mentioned in your
			log messages into links!
		</para>
	</tip>
	<para>
		Some <literal>tsvn:</literal> properties require a
		<literal>true/false</literal> value. TSVN also understands
		<literal>yes</literal> as a synonym for <literal>true</literal> and
		<literal>no</literal> as a synonym for <literal>false</literal>.
	</para>
	<important>
		<title>Set the Properties on Folders</title>
		<para>
			These properties must be set on folders for the system to work. 
			When you commit a file or folder the properties are read from that folder.
			If the properties are not found there, TortoiseSVN will search upwards
			through the folder tree to find them until it comes to an unversioned
			folder, or the tree root (eg. <literal>C:\</literal>) is found.
			If you can be sure that each user checks out only from e.g
			<filename>trunk/</filename> and not some subfolder, then it's enough if
			you set the properties on <filename>trunk/</filename>.
			If you can't be sure, you should set the properties recursively
			on each subfolder.
			A property setting deeper in the project hierarchy overrides settings on
			higher levels (closer to <filename>trunk/</filename>).
		</para>
		<para>
			For <literal>tsvn:</literal> properties <emphasis>only</emphasis>
			you can use the <guilabel>Recursive</guilabel> checkbox to set
			the property to all subfolders in the hierarchy, without also
			setting it on all files.
		</para>
	</important>
	<para>
		This issue tracker integration is not restricted to TortoiseSVN; it can be used
		with any Subversion client. For more information, read the full
		<ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/svn/tortoisesvn/trunk/doc/issuetrackers.txt">
			<citetitle>Issuetracker Integration Specification</citetitle>
		</ulink>.
	</para>
</sect1>
