<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-showlog">
	<title>Revision Log Dialog</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>log</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>history</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_LOGMESSAGE"?>
	<para>
		For every change you make and commit, you should provide
		a log message for that change. That way you can later find out
		what changes you made and why, and you have a detailed log for
		your development process.
	</para>
	<para>
		The Revision Log Dialog retrieves all those log messages and shows them
		to you.
		The display is divided into 3 panes.
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The top pane shows a list of revisions where changes to the
					file/folder have been committed. This summary includes the
					date and time, the person who committed the revision and the
					start of the log message.
				</para>
				<para>
					Lines shown in blue indicate that something has been copied
					to this development line (perhaps from a branch).
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The middle pane shows the full log message for the selected
					revision.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The bottom pane shows a list of all files and folders that
					were changed as part of the selected revision.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		But it does much more than that - it provides context menu
		commands which you can use to get even more information about the
		project history.
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-1">
		<title>Invoking the Revision Log Dialog</title>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-1-dia-1">
				<title>The Revision Log Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/LogMessages.png"/>
			</figure>
			There are several places from where you can show the Log dialog:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						From the TortoiseSVN context submenu
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						From the property page
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						From the Progress dialog after an update
						has finished. Then the Log dialog only shows those revisions
						which were changed since your last update
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-2">
		<title>Getting Additional Information</title>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-2-dia-1">
				<title>The Revision Log Dialog Top Pane with Context Menu</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/LogContextMenu.png"/>
			</figure>
			The top pane of the Log dialog has a context menu that allows you to
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Compare the selected revision with your working copy.
						The default Diff-Tool is TortoiseMerge which
						is supplied with TortoiseSVN.
						If the log dialog is for a folder, this will show you a list
						of changed files, and allow you to review the changes made
						to each file individually.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						View the changes made in the selected revision as a
						Unified-Diff file.
						The Unified-Diff operation is faster than invoking the 
						<quote>normal</quote> external
						diff viewer because TortoiseSVN doesn't have to fetch
						whole files but only the differences.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Save the selected revision to a file so you have an older
						version of that file. This option is only available when
						you access the log for a file, and it saves a version of
						that one file only.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Open the repository browser to examine the selected folder.
						This option is only available when you access the log for
						a directory.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Create a branch/tag from a selected revision.
						This is useful e.g. if you forgot to create a tag and already
						committed some changes which weren't supposed to get into
						that release.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Update your working copy to the selected
						revision. Useful if you want to have your working copy reflect
						a time in the past. It is best to update a whole directory
						in your working copy, not just one file, otherwise your
						working copy will be inconsistent and you will be unable to
						commit any changes.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Revert changes from which were made in the selected
						revision. The changes are reverted in your working copy so
						this operation does <emphasis>not</emphasis> affect the
						repository at all! Note that this will undo the changes
						made in that revision only. It does not replace your
						working copy with the entire file at the earlier revision.
						This is very useful for undoing an earlier change when
						other unrelated changes have been made since.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Edit the log message or author attached to a previous commit.
						Read <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-showlog-4"/> to find out
						how this works.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Search log messages for the text you enter. This searches
						the log messages that you entered and also the action summaries
						created by Subversion (shown in the bottom pane). The search
						is not case sensitive.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-2-dia-1a">
				<title>Top Pane Context Menu for 2 Selected Files</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/LogContextMenu1.png"/>
			</figure>
			If you select two revisions at once (using the usual
			<keycap>Ctrl</keycap>-modifier), the context menu changes and
			gives you fewer options:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Compare the two selected revisions using a visual
						difference tool. The default Diff-Tool is TortoiseMerge
						which is supplied with TortoiseSVN. If you select this
						option for a folder, a further dialog pops up listing
						the changed files and you can diff them one at a time.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						View the differences between the two selected revisions
						as a Unified-Diff file. This works for files and folders.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Edit the log message or author as described above.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Search log messages as described above.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			If you select multiple consecutive revisions (using the usual
			<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> or <keycap>Shift</keycap> modifiers),
			the context menu will include an entry to Revert all changes
			which were made in that range of revisions. This is the easiest
			way to rollback a group of revisions in one go.
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-2-dia-2">
				<title>The Log Dialog Bottom Pane with Context Menu</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/LogContextMenu2.png"/>
			</figure>
			The bottom pane of the Log dialog also has a context menu that allows you to
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Show differences made in the selected revision for the
						selected file. This context menu is only available for
						files shown as <literal>Modified</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Open the selected file, either with the default viewer for
						that file type, or with a program you choose.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Revert the changes made to the selected file in that revision.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						View the Subversion properties for the selected item.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Show the revision log for the selected single file.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Save the selected revision to a file so you
						have an older version of that file.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-3">
		<title>Getting more log messages</title>
		<para>
			The Log dialog does not always show all changes ever made for a
			number of reasons:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						For a large repository there may be hundreds or even
						thousands of changes and fetching them all could take
						a long time. Normally you are only interested in the
						more recent changes. By default, the number of log
						messages fetched is limited to 100, but you can change
						this value in 
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Settings</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice>
						(<xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-settings"/>),
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When the <guilabel>Stop on copy/rename</guilabel>
						box is checked, Show Log will stop at the point that
						the selected file or folder was copied from somewhere
						else within the repository. This can be useful when
						looking at branches (or tags) as it stops at the root
						of that branch, and gives a quick indication of changes
						made in that branch only.
					</para>
					<para>
						Normally you will want to leave this option unchecked.
						TortoiseSVN remembers the state of the checkbox, so
						it will respect your preference.
					</para>
					<para>
						When the Show Log dialog is invoked from within the
						Merge dialog, the box is always checked by default.
						This is because merging is most often looking at
						changes on branches, and going back beyond the root
						of the branch does not make sense in that instance.
					</para>
					<para>
						Note that Subversion currently implements renaming
						as a copy/delete pair, so renaming a file or folder
						will also cause the log display to stop if this
						option is checked.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to see more log messages, click the
			<guibutton>Next 100</guibutton> to retrieve the next 100 log messages.
			You can repeat this as many times as needed.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want to see <emphasis>all</emphasis> log messages right back
			to revision 1, press <guibutton>Show All</guibutton>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-4">
		<title>Changing the Log Message and Author</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>edit log/author</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Sometimes you might want to change a log message you once entered,
			maybe because there's a spelling error in it or you want to
			improve the message or change it for other reasons. Or you want to
			change the author of the commit because you forgot to set up
			authentication or...
		</para>
		<para>
			Subversion lets you change both the log message and the author
			of revisions any time you want. But since such changes can't be
			undone (those changes are not versioned) this feature is disabled
			by default. To make this work, you must set up a pre-revprop-change
			hook. Please refer to the chapter on
			<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.1/ch05s02.html#svn-ch-5-sect-2.1">
				<citetitle>Hook Scripts</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			in the Subversion Book for details about how to do that.
			Read <xref linkend="tsvn-repository-hooks"/> to find some further
			notes on implementing hooks on a Windows machine.
		</para>
		<para>
			Once you've set up your server with the required hooks, you can
			change both author and log message of any revision, using the context
			menu from the top pane of the Log dialog.
		</para>
		<warning>
			<para>
				Because Subversion's revision properties are not versioned, making 
				modifications to such a property (for example, the
				<literal>svn:log</literal> commit 
				message property) will overwrite the previous value of that 
				property <emphasis>forever</emphasis>.
			</para>
		</warning>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-filter">
		<title>Filtering Log Messages</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>filter</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			If you want to restrict the log messages to show only those
			you are interested in rather than scrolling through a list
			of hundreds, you can use the filter controls at the top of
			the Log Dialog. The start and end date controls allow you
			to restrict the output to a known date range. The search
			box allows you to show only messages which contain a
			particular phrase.
		</para>
		<para>
			Note that these filters act on the messages already retrieved.
			They do not control downloading of messages from the repository.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-showlog-5">
		<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_STATGRAPH"?>
		<title>Statistical Information</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>statistics</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			The <guibutton>Statistics</guibutton> button brings up a box
			showing some interesting information about the revisions
			shown in the Log dialog. This shows how many authors have
			been at work, how many commits they have made, progress
			by week, and much more. Now you can see at a glance who
			has been working hardest and who is slacking ;-)
		</para>
		<para>
			Note that the statistics cover the same period as the
			Log dialog. If that is only displaying one revision
			then the statistics will not tell you very much.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
