<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-settings-registry">
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGS_CONFIG"?>
	<title>Advanced Settings</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>registry</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		A few infrequently used settings are available only in the advanced
		page of the settings dialog. These settings modify the registry directly
		and you have to know what each of these settings is used for and what
		it does. Do not modify these settings unless you are sure you need to
		change them.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">ConfigDir</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					You can specify a different location for the Subversion
					configuration file here.
					This will affect all TortoiseSVN operations.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">Debug</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Set this to <literal>true</literal> if you want a dialog to
					pop up for every command showing the command line used to
					start TortoiseProc.exe
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">CacheTrayIcon</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					To add a cache tray icon for the TSVNCache program, set
					this value to <literal>true</literal>.
					This is really only useful for developers as it allows
					you to terminate the program gracefully.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">ShowContextMenuIcons</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This can be useful if you use something other than the windows explorer
					or if you get problems with the context menu displaying incorrectly.
					Set this value to <literal>false</literal>
					if you don't want TortoiseSVN to show icons for the 
					shell context menu items.
					Set this value to <literal>true</literal> to show the icons again.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">ShowAppContextMenuIcons</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If you don't want TortoiseSVN to show icons for the context menus
					in its own dialogs, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">LogStatusCheck</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The log dialog shows the revision the working copy path
					is at in bold. But this requires that the log dialog fetches
					the status of that path. Since for very big working copies
					this can take a while, you can set this value to <literal>false</literal>
					to deactivate this feature.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">FullRowSelect</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The status list control which is used in various dialogs
					(e.g., commit, check-for-modifications, add, revert, ...)
					uses full row selection (i.e., if you select an entry, the
					full row is selected, not just the first column).
					This is fine, but the selected row then also covers the
					background image on the bottom right, which can look ugly.
					To disable full row select, set this value to 
					<literal>false</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">StyleCommitMessages</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The commit and log dialog use styling (e.g. bold, italic)
					in commit messages
					(see <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-commit-log"/> for details).
					If you don't want to do this, set the value to 
					<literal>false</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">ShellMenuAccelerators</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseSVN uses accelerators for its explorer context menu
					entries. Since this can lead to doubled accelerators (e.g.
					the <literal>SVN Commit</literal> has the <keycap>Alt-C</keycap>
					accelerator, but so does the <literal>Copy</literal> entry
					of explorer).
					If you don't want or need the accelerators of the TortoiseSVN
					entries, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">AlwaysExtendedMenu</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					As with the explorer, TortoiseSVN shows additional commands
					if the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key is pressed while the
					context menu is opened.
					To force TortoiseSVN to always show those extended commands,
					set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">BlockStatus</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If you don't want the explorer to update the status overlays 
					while another TortoiseSVN command is running 
					(e.g. Update, Commit, ...) then set this value to
					<literal>true</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">UpdateCheckURL</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This value contains the URL from which TortoiseSVN tries 
					to download a text file to find out if there are updates 
					available. 
					This might be useful for company admins who don't want 
					their users to update TortoiseSVN until they approve it.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">ColumnsEveryWhere</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The extra columns the TortoiseSVN adds to the details view
					in Windows Explorer are normally only active in a working
					copy. If you want those to be accessible everywhere, not
					just in working copies, set this value to 
					<literal>true</literal>.
					Note that the extra columns are only available in XP.
					Vista and later doesn't support that feature any more.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">AllowUnversionedObstruction</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If an update adds a new file from the repository which
					already exists in the local working copy as an unversioned
					file, the default action is to keep the local file, showing
					it as a (possibly) modified version of the new file from the
					repository.
					If you would prefer TortoiseSVN to create a conflict in
					such situations, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">OldVersionCheck</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseSVN checks whether there's a new version available
					about once a week. If an updated version is found, the
					commit dialog shows a link control with that info.
					If you prefer the old behavior back where a dialog
					pops up notifying you about the update, set this value to
					<literal>true</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">VersionCheck</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseSVN checks whether there's a new version available
					about once a week. If you don't want TortoiseSVN to do this
					check, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">AutocompleteRemovesExtensions</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The auto-completion list shown in the commit message editor
					displays the names of files listed for commit.
					To also include these names with extensions removed,
					set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">Merge log separator</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					When you merge revisions from another branch, and merge tracking
					information is available, the log messages from the revisions
					you merge will be collected to make up a commit log message.
					A pre-defined string is used to separate the individual log
					messages of the merged revisions. If you prefer, you can set
					this to a value containing a separator string of your choice.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">DiffBlamesWithTortoiseMerge</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseSVN allows you to assign an external diff viewer.
					Most such viewers, however, are not suited for change blaming
					(<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-blame-diffs"/>),
					so you might wish to fall back to TortoiseMerge in this case.
					To do so, set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">IncludeExternals</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					By default, TortoiseSVN always runs an update with externals
					included. This avoids problems with inconsistent working copies.
					If you have however a lot of externals set, an update can
					take quite a while. Set this value to <literal>false</literal>
					to run the default update with externals excluded. To
					update with externals included, either run the
					<literal>Update to revision...</literal> dialog or set this
					value to <literal>true</literal> again.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term condition="pot">CtrlReturn</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					In most dialogs in TortoiseSVN, you can use <keycap>Ctrl+Enter</keycap>
					to dismiss the dialog as if you clicked on the OK button.
					If you don't want this, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</sect2>