<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage">
  <title>Project Settings</title>
  <sect2 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props">
    <title>Subversion Properties</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>Subversion properties</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPERTIES"?>
    <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPERTYVALUE"?>
    <para>
      <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-dia-2">
        <title>Subversion property page</title>
        <graphic fileref="../images/PropertyList.png"/>
      </figure>
      You can read and set the Subversion properties
      from the Windows properties dialog, but also from
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>
      and within TortoiseSVN's status lists, from
      <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
        <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
      </menuchoice>.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can add your own properties, or some properties with a
      special meaning in Subversion. These begin with <literal>svn:</literal>.
      <literal>svn:externals</literal> is such a property; see how to handle
      externals in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-externals"/>.
    </para>
    <sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props-keywords">
      <title>svn:keywords</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>keywords</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>expand keywords</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        Subversion supports CVS-like keyword expansion which can be
        used to embed filename and revision information within the
        file itself. Keywords currently supported are:
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">$Date$</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Date of last known commit. This is based on
                information obtained when you update your working
                copy. It does <emphasis>not</emphasis> check the
                repository to find more recent changes.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">$Revision$</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Revision of last known commit.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">$Author$</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Author who made the last known commit.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">$HeadURL$</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The full URL of this file in the repository.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">$Id$</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                A compressed combination of the previous
                four keywords.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      <para>
        To find out how to use these keywords, look at the
        <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.8/svn.advanced.props.special.keywords.html">
          <citetitle>svn:keywords section</citetitle>
        </ulink>
        in the Subversion book, which gives a full description of these
        keywords and how to enable and use them.
      </para>
    </sect3>

    <para>
      For more information about properties in Subversion see the
      <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.8/svn.advanced.props.html">
        <citetitle>Special Properties</citetitle>
      </ulink>.
    </para>
    <sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props-add">
      <title>Adding and Editing Properties</title>
      <para>
        <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-dia-add">
          <title>Adding properties</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropertyAdd.png"/>
        </figure>
        To add a new property, first click on <guilabel>New...</guilabel>.
        Select the required property name from the menu, and then
        fill in the required information in the specific property
        dialog. These specific property dialogs are described in more
        detail in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-propertypage-editors"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        To add a property that doesn't have its own dialog, choose
        <guimenuitem>Advanced</guimenuitem> from the <guilabel>New...</guilabel>
        menu. Then either select an existing property in the combo box
        or enter a custom property name.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you want to apply a property to many items at once, select the
        files/folders in explorer, then select
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you want to apply the property to <emphasis>every</emphasis> file
        and folder in the hierarchy below the current folder, check the
        <guilabel>Recursive</guilabel> checkbox.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you wish to edit an existing property, select that property from
        the list of existing properties, then click on <guibutton>Edit...</guibutton>.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you wish to remove an existing property, select that property from
        the list of existing properties, then click on <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>svn:externals</literal> property can be used to
        pull in other projects from the same repository or a completely
        different repository. For more information, read
        <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-externals"/>.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <title>Edit properties at HEAD revision</title>
        <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_PROPERTIES"?>
        <para>
          Because properties are versioned, you cannot edit the properties
          of previous revisions. If you look at properties from the log
          dialog, or from a non-HEAD revision in the repository browser,
          you will see a list of properties and values, but no edit controls.
        </para>
      </tip>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props-import">
      <title>Exporting and Importing Properties</title>
      <para>
        Often you will find yourself applying the same set of properties many
        times, for example <literal>bugtraq:logregex</literal>. To simplify
        the process of copying properties from one project to another, you
        can use the Export/Import feature.
      </para>
      <para>
        From the file or folder where the properties are already set, use
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>,
        select the properties you wish to export and click on
        <guibutton>Export...</guibutton>. You will be prompted for a filename
        where the property names and values will be saved.
      </para>
      <para>
        From the folder(s) where you wish to apply these properties, use
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        and click on <guibutton>Import...</guibutton>. You will be prompted
        for a filename to import from, so navigate to the place you saved
        the export file previously and select it. The properties will be added
        to the folders non-recursively.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you want to add properties to a tree recursively, follow the steps
        above, then in the property dialog select each property in turn,
        click on <guibutton>Edit...</guibutton>, check the
        <guilabel>Apply property recursively</guilabel> box and click on
        <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Import file format is binary and proprietary to TortoiseSVN.
        Its only purpose is to transfer properties using Import and Export,
        so there is no need to edit these files.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props-binary">
      <title>Binary Properties</title>
      <para>
        TortoiseSVN can handle binary property values using files.
        To read a binary property value, <guibutton>Save...</guibutton>
        to a file. To set a binary value, use a hex editor or other appropriate
        tool to create a file with the content you require, then
        <guibutton>Load...</guibutton> from that file.
      </para>
      <para>
        Although binary properties are not often used, they can be useful in
        some applications. For example if you are storing huge graphics files,
        or if the application used to load the file is huge, you might want
        to store a thumbnail as a property so you can obtain a preview quickly.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-auto-props">
      <title>Automatic property setting</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>auto-props</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        You can configure Subversion and TortoiseSVN to set properties
        automatically on files and folders when they are added to the
        repository. There are two ways of doing this.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can edit the Subversion configuration file to enable
        this feature on your client. The <guilabel>General</guilabel>
        page of TortoiseSVN's settings dialog has an edit button to
        take you there directly.
        The config file is a simple text file which controls some of
        Subversion's workings. You need to change two things:
        firstly in the section headed
        <literal>miscellany</literal> uncomment the line
        <literal>enable-auto-props = yes</literal>.
        Secondly you need to edit the section below to define which
        properties you want added to which file types.
        This method is a standard Subversion feature and works with
        any Subversion client. However it has to be defined on each
        client individually - there is no way to propagate these settings
        from the repository.
      </para>
      <para>
        An alternative method is to set the <literal>tsvn:autoprops</literal>
        property on folders, as described in the next section. This method
        only works for TortoiseSVN clients, but it does get propagated
        to all working copies on update.
      </para>
      <para>
        As of Subversion 1.8, you can also set the property
        <literal>svn:auto-props</literal> on the root folder. The property value
        is automatically inherited by all child items.
      </para>
      <para>
        Whichever method you choose, you should note that auto-props
        are only applied to files at the time they are added to the
        working copy. Auto-props will never change the properties of files
        which are already versioned.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you want to be absolutely sure that new files have the correct
        properties applied, you should set up a repository pre-commit
        hook to reject commits where the required properties are not set.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <important>
      <title>Commit properties</title>
      <para>
        Subversion properties are versioned. After you change or add a
        property you have to commit your changes.
      </para>
    </important>
    <tip>
      <title>Conflicts on properties</title>
      <para>
        If there's a conflict on committing the changes, because another
        user has changed the same property, Subversion generates a
        <filename>.prej</filename> file. Delete this file after you
        have resolved the conflict.
      </para>
    </tip>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props">
    <title>TortoiseSVN Project Properties</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>project properties</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>TortoiseSVN properties</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>
      TortoiseSVN has a few special properties of its own, and these begin
      with <literal>tsvn:</literal>.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>tsvn:logminsize</literal>
            sets the minimum length of a log message for a commit.
            If you enter a shorter message than specified here, the commit
            is disabled. This feature is very useful for reminding you to
            supply a proper descriptive message for every commit.
            If this property is not set,
            or the value is zero, empty log messages are allowed.
          </para>
          <para>
            <literal>tsvn:lockmsgminsize</literal>
            sets the minimum length of a lock message.
            If you enter a shorter message than specified here, the lock
            is disabled. This feature is very useful for reminding you to
            supply a proper descriptive message for every lock you get.
            If this property is not set,
            or the value is zero, empty lock messages are allowed.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>tsvn:logwidthmarker</literal> is used with projects which
            require log messages to be formatted with some maximum width
            (typically 80 characters) before a line break. Setting this
            property to a non-zero will do 2 things in the log message
            entry dialog: it places a marker to indicate the maximum width,
            and it disables word wrap in the display, so that you can see
            whether the text you entered is too long. Note: this feature
            will only work correctly if you have a fixed-width font
            selected for log messages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>tsvn:logtemplate</literal> is used with projects which
            have rules about log message formatting. The property holds
            a multi-line text string which will be inserted in the commit
            message box when you start a commit. You can then edit it to
            include the required information. Note: if you are also using
            <literal>tsvn:logminsize</literal>, be sure to set the length
            longer than the template or you will lose the protection mechanism.
          </para>
          <para>
            There are also action specific templates which you can use instead
            of <literal>tsvn:logtemplate</literal>. The action specific templates
            are used if set, but <literal>tsvn:logtemplate</literal> will be
            used if no action specific template is set.
          </para>
          <para>
            The action specific templates are:
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <literal>tsvn:logtemplatecommit</literal> is used
                  for all commits from a working copy.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <literal>tsvn:logtemplatebranch</literal> is used
                  when you create a branch/tag, or when you copy
                  files or folders directly in the repository browser.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <literal>tsvn:logtemplateimport</literal> is used
                  for imports.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <literal>tsvn:logtemplatedelete</literal> is used
                  when deleting items directly in the repository browser.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <literal>tsvn:logtemplatemove</literal> is used
                  when renaming or moving items in the repository browser.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <literal>tsvn:logtemplatemkdir</literal> is used
                  when creating directories in the repository browser.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <literal>tsvn:logtemplatepropset</literal> is used
                  when modifying properties in the repository browser.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <literal>tsvn:logtemplatelock</literal> is used
                  when getting a lock.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Subversion allows you to set <quote>autoprops</quote> which
            will be applied to newly added or imported files, based on
            the file extension. This depends on every client having set
            appropriate autoprops in their Subversion configuration file.
            <literal>tsvn:autoprops</literal> can be set on folders
            and these will be merged with the user's local autoprops
            when importing or adding files.
            The format is the same as for Subversion autoprops, e.g.
            <literal>*.sh = svn:eol-style=native;svn:executable</literal>
            sets two properties on files with the <literal>.sh</literal>
            extension.
          </para>
          <para>
            If there is a conflict between the local autoprops and
            <literal>tsvn:autoprops</literal>, the project settings take
            precedence because they are specific to that project.
          </para>
          <para>
            As of Subversion 1.8, you should use the property
            <literal>svn:auto-props</literal> instead of
            <literal>tsvn:autoprops</literal> since this has the
            very same functionality but works with all svn clients
            and is not specific to TortoiseSVN.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the Commit dialog you have the option to paste in the
            list of changed files, including the status of each file
            (added, modified, etc).
            <literal>tsvn:logfilelistenglish</literal> defines whether
            the file status is inserted in English or in the localized
            language. If the property is not set, the default is
            <literal>true</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            TortoiseSVN can use spell checker modules which are also
            used by OpenOffice and Mozilla. If you have those installed
            this property will determine which spell checker to use, i.e.
            in which language the log messages for your project should
            be written.
            <literal>tsvn:projectlanguage</literal> sets the language
            module the spell checking engine should use when you enter
            a log message. You can find the values for your language
            on this page:
            <ulink url="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ms776260.aspx">
              <citetitle>MSDN: Language Identifiers</citetitle>
            </ulink>.
          </para>
          <para>
            You can enter this value in decimal, or in hexadecimal if
            prefixed with <literal>0x</literal>.
            For example English (US) can be entered as
            <literal>0x0409</literal> or <literal>1033</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The property <literal>tsvn:logsummary</literal> is used to
            extract a portion of the log message which is then shown
            in the log dialog as the log message summary.
          </para>
          <para>
            The value of the <literal>tsvn:logsummary</literal> property
            must be set to a one line regex string which contains one
            regex group. Whatever matches that group is used as the
            summary.
          </para>
          <para>
            An example:
            <literal>\[SUMMARY\]:\s+(.*)</literal>
            Will catch everything after <quote>[SUMMARY]</quote> in the log message
            and use that as the summary.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The property <literal>tsvn:logrevregex</literal> defines
            a regular expression which matches references to revisions
            in a log message. This is used in the log dialog to turn
            such references into links which when clicked will either
            scroll to that revision (if the revision is already shown
            in the log dialog, or if it's available from the log cache)
            or open a new log dialog showing that revision.
          </para>
          <para>
            The regular expression must match the whole reference, not
            just the revision number. The revision number is extracted
            from the matched reference string automatically.
          </para>
          <para>
            If this property is not set, a default regular expression
            is used to link revision references.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            There are several properties available to configure
            client-side hook scripts. Each property is for
            one specific hook script type.
          </para>
          <para>
            The available properties/hook-scripts are
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>tsvn:startcommithook</listitem>
              <listitem>tsvn:precommithook</listitem>
              <listitem>tsvn:postcommithook</listitem>
              <listitem>tsvn:startupdatehook</listitem>
              <listitem>tsvn:preupdatehook</listitem>
              <listitem>tsvn:postupdatehook</listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          <para>
            The parameters are the same as if you would
            configure the hook scripts in the settings dialog.
            See <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-settings-hooks"/> for
            the details.
          </para>
          <para>
            Since not every user has his or her working copy
            checked out at the same location with the same
            name, you can configure a script/tool to execute
            that resides in your working copy by specifying
            the URL in the repository instead, using <filename>%REPOROOT%</filename>
            as the part of the URL to the repository root.
            For example, if your hook script is in your working copy
            under <filename>contrib/hook-scripts/client-side/checkyear.js</filename>,
            you would specify the path to the script as
            <filename>%REPOROOT%/trunk/contrib/hook-scripts/client-side/checkyear.js</filename>.
            This way even if you move your repository to
            another server you do not have to adjust the
            hook script properties.
          </para>
          <para>
            Instead of <filename>%REPOROOT%</filename> you
            can also specify <filename>%REPOROOT+%</filename>.
            The <literal>+</literal> is used to insert any
            number of folder paths necessary to find the script.
            This is useful if you want to specify your script
            so that if you create a branch the script is still
            found even though the url of the working copy is now
            different. Using the example above, you would
            specify the path to the script as
            <filename>%REPOROOT+%/contrib/hook-scripts/client-side/checkyear.js</filename>.
          </para>
          <para>
            The following screenshot shows how the script
            to check for current copyright years in source
            file headers is configured for TortoiseSVN.
            <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props-copyright">
              <title>Property dialog for hook scripts</title>
              <graphic fileref="../images/hookpropertydlg.png"/>
            </figure>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When you want to add a new property, you can either pick one from
            the list in the combo box, or you can enter any property name
            you like. If your project uses some custom properties,
            and you want those properties to appear in the list in the combo
            box (to avoid typos when you enter a property name), you can
            create a list of your custom properties using
            <literal>tsvn:userfileproperties</literal> and
            <literal>tsvn:userdirproperties</literal>.
            Apply these properties to a folder. When you go to edit
            the properties of any child item, your custom properties will
            appear in the list of pre-defined property names.
          </para>
          <para>
            You can also specify whether a custom dialog is used
            to add/edit your property. TortoiseSVN offers four
            different dialog, depending on the type of your property.
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term condition="pot">bool</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If your property can only have two states,
                    e.g., true and false, then you can configure
                    your property as a <literal>bool</literal> type.
                    <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props-userbool">
                      <title>Property dialog boolean user types</title>
                      <graphic fileref="../images/userpropbool.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    Specify your property like this:
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <literal>propertyname=bool;labeltext(YESVALUE;NOVALUE;Checkboxtext)</literal>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    the <literal>labeltext</literal> is the text shown
                    in the dialog above the checkbox where you can explain the purpose
                    and use of the property. The other parameters should be self explanatory.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term condition="pot">state</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    If your property represents one of many possible
                    states, e.g., <literal>yes, no, maybe</literal>,
                    then you can configure your property as a <literal>state</literal>
                    <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props-userstate">
                      <title>Property dialog state user types</title>
                      <graphic fileref="../images/userpropstate1.png"/>
                      <graphic fileref="../images/userpropstate2.png"/>
                      <graphic fileref="../images/userpropstate3.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    property like this:
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <literal>propertyname=state;labeltext(DEFVAL;VAL1;TEXT1;VAL2;TEXT2;VAL3;TEXT3;...)</literal>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    The parameters are the same as for the <literal>bool</literal>
                    property, with <literal>DEFVAL</literal> being the default
                    value to be used if the property isn't set yet or has a value that's
                    not configured.
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    For up to three different values, the dialog shows
                    up to three radio buttons. If there are more values
                    configured, it uses a combo box from where the user
                    can select the required state.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term condition="pot">singleline</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    For properties that consist of one line of text,
                    use the <literal>singleline</literal> property type:
                    <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props-usersingleline">
                      <title>Property dialog single-line user types</title>
                      <graphic fileref="../images/userpropsingleline.png"/>
                    </figure>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <literal>propertyname=singleline;labeltext(regex)</literal>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    the <literal>regex</literal> specifies a regular
                    expression which is used to validate (match)
                    the text the user entered. If the text does
                    not match the regex, then the user is shown an error
                    and the property isn't set.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry>
                <term condition="pot">multiline</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    For properties that consist of multiple lines of text,
                    use the <literal>multiline</literal> property type:
                    <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props-usermultiline">
                      <title>Property dialog multi-line user types</title>
                      <graphic fileref="../images/userpropmultiline.png"/>
                    </figure>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    <literal>propertyname=multiline;labeltext(regex)</literal>
                  </para>
                  <para>
                    the <literal>regex</literal> specifies a regular
                    expression which is used to validate (match)
                    the text the user entered. Don't forget to
                    include the newline (\n) character in the regex!
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
            The screenshots above were made with the following
            <literal>tsvn:userdirproperties</literal>:
            <screen>
my:boolprop=bool;This is a bool type property. Either check or uncheck it.(true;false;my bool prop)
my:stateprop1=state;This is a state property. Select one of the two states.(true;true;true value;false;false value)
my:stateprop2=state;This is a state property. Select one of the three states.(maybe;true;answer is correct;false;answer is wrong;maybe;not answered)
my:stateprop3=state;Specify the day to set this property.(1;1;Monday;2;Tuesday;3;Wednesday;4;Thursday;5;Friday;6;Saturday;7;Sunday)
my:singlelineprop=singleline;enter a small comment(.*)
my:multilineprop=multiline;copy and paste a full chapter here(.*)
            </screen>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      TortoiseSVN can integrate with some bug tracking tools. This uses
      project properties that start with <literal>bugtraq:</literal>.
      Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-bugtracker"/> for further information.
    </para>
    <para>
      It can also integrate with some web-based repository browsers,
      using project properties that start with <literal>webviewer:</literal>.
      Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-repoviewer"/> for further information.
    </para>
    <important>
      <title>Set the project properties on folders</title>
      <para>
        These special project properties must be set on
        <emphasis>folders</emphasis> for the system to work.
        When you use a TortoiseSVN command which uses these properties, the
        properties are read from the folder you clicked on.
        If the properties are not found there, TortoiseSVN will search upwards
        through the folder tree to find them until it comes to an unversioned
        folder, or the tree root (e.g. <literal>C:\</literal>) is found.
        If you can be sure that each user checks out only from e.g
        <filename>trunk/</filename> and not some sub-folder, then it is
        sufficient to set the properties on <filename>trunk/</filename>.
        If you can't be sure, you should set the properties recursively on
        each sub-folder.
        If you set the same property but you use different values at different
        depths in your project hierarchy then you will get different results
        depending on where you click in the folder structure.
      </para>
      <para>
        For project properties <emphasis>only</emphasis>,
        i.e. <literal>tsvn:</literal>, <literal>bugtraq:</literal>
        and <literal>webviewer:</literal>
        you can use the <guilabel>Recursive</guilabel> checkbox to set
        the property to all sub-folders in the hierarchy, without also
        setting it on all files.
      </para>
    </important>
    <para>
      When you add new sub-folders to a working copy using TortoiseSVN, any
      project properties present in the parent folder
      will automatically be added to the new child folder too.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <title>Limitations Using the Repository Browser</title>
      <para>
        Fetching properties remotely is a slow operation, so some
        of the features described above will not work in the
        repository browser as they do in a working copy.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When you add a property using the repo browser, only
            the standard <literal>svn:</literal> properties are offered
            in the pre-defined list. Any other property name must be
            entered manually.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Properties cannot be set or deleted recursively
            using the repo browser.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Project properties will <emphasis>not</emphasis> be
            propagated automatically when a child folder is added
            using the repo browser.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>tsvn:autoprops</literal> will <emphasis>not</emphasis>
            set properties on files which are added using the repo browser.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </tip>
    <caution>
      <para>
        Although TortoiseSVN's project properties are extremely useful,
        they only work with TortoiseSVN, and some will only work in newer versions
        of TortoiseSVN. If people working on your project use a variety of
        Subversion clients, or possibly have old versions of TortoiseSVN,
        you may want to use repository hooks to enforce project policies.
        project properties can only help to implement a
        policy, they cannot enforce it.
      </para>
    </caution>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-editors">
    <title>Property Editors</title>
    <para>
      Some properties have to use specific values, or be formatted in a specific
      way in order to be used for automation. To help get the formatting correct,
      TortoiseSVN presents edit dialogs for some particular properties which
      show the possible values or break the property into its individual components.
    </para>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-external">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPEXTERNALSVALUE"?>
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPEXTERNALS"?>
      <title>External Content</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>svn:externals property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditExternal.png"/>
        </figure>
        The <literal>svn:externals</literal> property can be used to
        pull in other projects from the same repository or a completely
        different repository as described in
        <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-externals"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        You need to define the name of the sub-folder that the external
        folder is checked out as, and the Subversion URL of the external item.
        You can check out an external at its HEAD revision, so when the external
        item changes in the repository, your working copy will receive those
        changes on update. However, if you want the external to reference a
        particular stable point then you can specify the specific revision to
        use. IN this case you may also want to specify the same revision as a
        peg revision. If the external item is renamed at some point in the future
        then Subversion will not be able to update this item in your working copy.
        By specifying a peg revision you tell Subversion to look for an item that
        had that name at the peg revision rather than at HEAD.
      </para>
      <para>
        The button <guibutton>Find HEAD-Revision</guibutton>
        fetches the HEAD revision of every external URL and
        shows that HEAD revision in the rightmost column.
        After the HEAD revision is known, a simple right click
        on an external gives you the command to peg the
        selected externals to their explicit HEAD revision.
        In case the HEAD revision is not known yet, the right
        click command will fetch the HEAD revision first.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-keywords">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPKEYWORDS"?>
      <title>SVN Keywords</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>svn:keywords property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditKeywords.png"/>
        </figure>
        Select the keywords that you would like to be expanded in your file.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-eol">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPEOL"?>
      <title>EOL Style</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>svn:eol-style property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditEol.png"/>
        </figure>
        Select the end-of-line style that you wish to use and TortoiseSVN will
        use the correct property value.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-bugtraq">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPKEYWORDS"?>
      <title>Issue Tracker Integration</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>tsvn:bugtraq property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditBugtraq.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-log-size">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPTSVNSIZES"?>
      <title>Log Message Sizes</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Size of log messages property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditLogSize.png"/>
        </figure>
        These 3 properties control the formatting of log messages.
        The first 2 disable the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> in the
        commit or lock dialogs until the message meets the minimum length.
        The border position shows a marker at the given column width as
        a guide for projects which have width limits on their log messages.
        Setting a value to zero will delete the property.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-language">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPTSVNLANG"?>
      <title>Project Language</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>Language property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditLanguage.png"/>
        </figure>
        Choose the language to use for spell-checking log messages in the
        commit dialog. The file lists checkbox comes into effect when you
        right click in the log message pane and select
        <guilabel>Paste file list</guilabel>. By default the Subversion
        status will be shown in your local language. When this box is checked
        the status is always given in English, for projects which require
        English-only log messages.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-mime-type">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPMIMETYPE"?>
      <title>MIME-type</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>svn:mime-type property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditMimeType.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-needs-lock">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPNEEDSLOCK"?>
      <title>svn:needs-lock</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>svn:needs-lock property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditNeedsLock.png"/>
        </figure>
        This property simply controls whether a file will be checked out as
        read-only if there is no lock held for it in the working copy.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-exe">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPEXECUTABLE"?>
      <title>svn:executable</title>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <title>svn:executable property page</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/PropEditExe.png"/>
        </figure>
        This property controls whether a file will be given executable status
        when checked out on a Unix/Linux system. It has no effect on a Windows
        checkout.
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="tsvn_dug_propertypage-edit-mergelogmsgtemplate">
      <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPMERGELOGTEMPLATE"?>
      <title>Merge log message templates</title>
      <para>
        Whenever revisions are merged into a working copy,
        TortoiseSVN generates a log message from all the
        merged revisions. Those are then available from the
        <guibutton>Recent Messages</guibutton> button in the
        commit dialog.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can customize that generated message with the following
        properties:
        <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props-mergelogtemplate">
          <title>Property dialog merge log message templates</title>
          <graphic fileref="../images/mergelogmsgtemplate.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">tsvn:mergelogtemplatetitle, tsvn:mergelogtemplatereversetitle</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This property specifies the first part of the generated
                log message. The following keywords can be used:
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{revisions}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        A comma separated list of the merged revisions,
                        e.g., <literal>3, 5, 6, 7</literal>
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{revisionsr}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        Like <literal>{revisions}</literal>, but with each
                        revision preceded with an <literal>r</literal>,
                        e.g., <literal>r3, r5, r6, r7</literal>
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{revrange}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        A comma separated list of the merged revisions,
                        grouped into ranges if possible,
                        e.g., <literal>3, 5-7</literal>
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{mergeurl}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        The source URL of the merge, i.e., where the
                        revisions are merged from.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </para>
              <para>
                The default value for this string is
                <literal>Merged revision(s) {revrange} from {mergeurl}:</literal>
                with a newline at the end.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">tsvn:mergelogtemplatemsg</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This property specifies how the text for each
                merged revision should look like. The following
                keywords can be used:
                <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{msg}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        The log message of the merged revision, as it was entered.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{msgoneline}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        Like <literal>{msg}</literal>, but all
                        newlines are replaced with a space, so that
                        the whole log message appears on one single line.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{author}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        The author of the merged revision.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{rev}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        The merged revision itself.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term condition="pot">{bugids}</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        The bug IDs of the merged revision, if
                        there are any.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term condition="pot">tsvn:mergelogtemplatemsgtitlebottom</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                This property specifies the position of the title string specified
                with the <literal>tsvn:mergelogtemplatetitle</literal> or
                <literal>tsvn:mergelogtemplatereversetitle</literal>. If the
                property is set to <literal>yes</literal> or <literal>true</literal>,
                then the title string is appended at the bottom instead of
                the top.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </para>
      <para>
        <important>
          <para>
            This only works if the merged revisions
            are already in the log cache. If you have disabled
            the log cache or not shown the log first
            before the merge, the generated message
            won't contain any information about the merged
            revisions.
          </para>
        </important>
      </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
