<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-blame">
	<title>Who Changed Which Line?</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>blame</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>annotate</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>praise</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_BLAME"?>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-blame-dia-1">
			<title>The Annotate / Blame Dialog</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/BlameDialog.png"/>
		</figure>
		Sometimes you need to know not only what lines have changed, but also
		who exactly changed specific lines in a file. That's when the
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Blame...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		command, sometimes also referred to as <firstterm>annotate</firstterm>
		command comes in handy.
	</para>
	<para>
		This command lists, for every line in a file, the author and the revision
		the line was changed.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you're not interested in changes from earlier revisions you can
		set the revision from which the blame should start. Set this to <literal>1</literal>,
		if you want the blame for <emphasis>every</emphasis> revision.
	</para>
	<para>
		By default the blame file is viewed using <firstterm>TortoiseBlame</firstterm>,
		which highlights the different revisions to make it easier to read.
		If you wish to print or edit the blame file, select
		<guilabel>Use Text viewer to view blames</guilabel>
	</para>
	<para>
		Once you press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> TortoiseSVN starts retrieving
		the data to create the blame file. Please note: This can take several
		minutes to finish, depending on how much the file has changed and
		of course your network connection to the repository. Once the blame
		process has finished the result is written into a temporary file and
		you can view the results.
	</para>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-blame-dia-2">
			<title>TortoiseBlame</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/TortoiseBlame.png"/>
		</figure>
		TortoiseBlame, which is included with TortoiseSVN, makes the blame file
		easier to read. When you hover the mouse over a line in the blame info
		column, all lines with the same revision are shown with a darker
		background. Lines from other revisions which were changed by the same author
		are shown with a light background.
		The colouring may not work as clearly if you have your display set to
		256 colour mode.
	</para>
	<para>
		If you <action>left click</action>
		on a line, all lines with the same revision are highlighted, and lines from
		other revisions by the same author are highlighted in a lighter colour.
		This highlighting is sticky, allowing you to move the mouse without losing
		the highlights. Click on that revision again to turn off highlighting.
	</para>
	<para>
		The revision comments are shown in a hint box whenever the mouse hovers over
		the blame info column.
	</para>
	<para>
		You can search within the Blame report using
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Find...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>.
		This allows you to search for revision numbers, authors and the content of
		the file itself. Log messages are not included in the search - you should
		use the Log Dialog to search those.
	</para>
</sect1>
