<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-merge">
	<title>Merging</title>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_MERGE"?>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>merge</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		Where branches are used to maintain separate lines of development,
		at some stage you will want to merge the changes made on one branch
		back into the trunk, or vice versa.
	</para>
	<para>
		It is important to understand how branching and merging works in
		Subversion before you start using it, as it can become quite complex.
		It is highly recommended that you read the chapter
		<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.1/ch04.html">
			<citetitle>Branching and Merging</citetitle>
		</ulink>
		in the
		<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">
			<citetitle>Subversion Book</citetitle>
		</ulink>
		which gives a full description, and many examples of how it is used.
	</para>
	<para>
		An important point to remember is that Merge is closely related to
		Diff. The merge process works by generating a list of differences
		between two points in the repository, and applying those differences
		to your working copy. For example if you want to merge the changes
		made in revision N then you have to compare revision N with revision
		(N-1). Novices often ask
		<quote>Why do I have to subtract 1 from the start revision.</quote>
		Think of the underlying Diff process and it will become clearer.
		TO make this easier, when you use <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton> to
		select a range of revisions to merge, TortoiseSVN makes this adjustment
		for you automatically.
	</para>
	<para>
		In general it is a good idea to perform a merge into an unmodified
		working copy. If you have made other changes in your WC, commit those
		first. If the merge does not go as you expect, you may want to revert
		the changes, and the <guilabel>Revert</guilabel> command will discard
		<emphasis>all</emphasis> changes including any you made before the merge.
	</para>
	<para>
		There are two common use cases for merging which are handled in
		slightly different ways, as described below.
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-1">
		<title>Merging a Range of Revisions</title>
		<para>
			This method covers the case when you have made one or more
			revisions to a branch (or to the trunk) and you want to port
			those changes across to a different branch.
		</para>
		<para>
			<figure id="tsvn-dug-merge-dia-1">
				<title>The Merge Dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/Merge.png"/>
			</figure>
			To merge revisions you need to go to a working copy of the
			branch in which you want to receive the changes, often the trunk.
			Select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Merge...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			from the context menu.
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>From:</guilabel> field enter the full
						folder url of the branch or tag containing the changes
						you want to port into your working copy.
						You may also click
						<guibutton>...</guibutton>
						to browse the repository and find the desired branch.
						If you have merged from this branch before, then just
						use the drop down list which shows a history of
						previously used URLs.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Because you are porting a range of revisions from
						the same branch into your working copy, make sure the
						<guilabel>Use "From:" URL</guilabel> checkbox is
						checked.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>From Revision</guilabel> field enter the
						start revision number. This is the revision
						<emphasis>before</emphasis> the changes you want to merge.
						Remember that Subversion will create a diff file in order
						to perform the merge, so the start point has to be just
						before the first change you are interested in.
						For example,
						your log messages may look something like this:
<screen>
Rev Comments
39. Working on MyBranch
38. Working on trunk
37. Working on MyBranch
36. Create branch MyBranch
35. Working on trunk
34. Working on trunk
         ...
</screen>
						If you now want to merge all the changes from MyBranch into
						the trunk you have to choose 36 as the
						<guilabel>From Revision</guilabel>, not 37 as you might think.
						If you select revision 37 as the start point, then the
						difference engine compares the end point with revision 37,
						and will miss the changes made in revision 37 itself.
						If that sounds complicated, don't worry, there is an
						easier way in TortoiseSVN ...
					</para>
					<para>
						The easiest way to select the range of revisions you need
						is to click on <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton>, as this
						will list recent changes with their log comments.
						If you want to merge the changes from a single revision, just
						select that revision. If you want to merge changes from several
						revisions, then select that range
						(using the usual <keycap>Shift</keycap>-modifier).
						Click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and the revision numbers
						of the <guilabel>From revision</guilabel> and
						<guilabel>To revision</guilabel> in the Merge dialog will
						<emphasis>both</emphasis> be filled in for you.
					</para>
					<para>
						When the <guilabel>Use "From:" URL</guilabel> checkbox is
						checked, only one <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton> button
						is enabled. This is because the Show Log dialog sets both
						<guilabel>From:</guilabel> and <guilabel>To:</guilabel>
						revisions, so you need to use the multiple selection method
						outlined above.
					</para>
					<para>
						If you have already merged some changes from this branch,
						hopefully you will have made a note of the last revision
						merged in the log message when you committed the change.
						In that case, you can use <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton>
						for the Working Copy to trace that log message. Use the
						end point of the last merge as the start point for this
						merge. For example, if you have merged revisions 37 to 39
						last time, then the start point for this merge should be
						revision 39.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If you have not used <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton> to
						select the revision range, then you will need to set the
						<guilabel>To Revision</guilabel> manually. Enter the
						last revision number in the range you want to merge.
						Often this will be the HEAD revision, although it doesn't
						need to be - you may just want to merge a single revision.
					</para>
					<para>
						If other people may be committing changes then be careful
						about using the HEAD revision. It may not refer to the
						revision you think it does if someone else made a commit
						after your last update.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to complete the merge.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			The merge is now complete. It's a good idea to have a look at the
			merge and see if it's as expected. Merging is usually quite complicated.
			Conflicts often arise if the branch has drifted far from the trunk.
		</para>
		<para>
			When you have tested the changes and come to commit this revision,
			your commit log message should <emphasis>always</emphasis>
			include the revision numbers which have been ported in the merge.
			If you want to apply another merge at a later time you will need to
			know what you have already merged, as you do not want to port a
			change more than once. Unfortunately merge information is not
			stored by Subversion. For more information about this, refer to
			<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.1/ch04s03.html#svn-ch-4-sect-3.2.1">
				<citetitle>Tracking Merges Manually</citetitle>
			</ulink>
			in the
			<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">
				<citetitle>Subversion Book</citetitle>
			</ulink>
		</para>
		<para>
			Branch management is important. If you want to keep this branch up to
			date with the trunk, you should be sure to merge often so that the
			branch and trunk do not drift too far apart. Of course, you
			should still avoid repeated merging of changes, as explained above.
		</para>
		<important>
			<para>
				Subversion can't merge a file with a folder and vice versa - only
				folders to folders and files to files. If you click on a file and
				open up the merge dialog, then you have to give a path to a file
				in that dialog. If you select a folder and bring up the dialog,
				then you must specify a folder url for the merge.
			</para>
		</important>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-2">
		<title>Merging Two Different Trees</title>
		<para>
			This method covers the case when you have made a feature branch
			as discussed in the Subversion book. All trunk changes have been
			ported to the feature branch, week by week, and now the feature
			is complete you want to merge it back into the trunk. Because
			you have kept the feature branch synchronized with the trunk,
			the latest versions of branch and trunk will be absolutely
			identical except for your branch changes. So in this special case,
			you would merge by comparing the branch with the trunk.
		</para>
		<para>
			To merge the feature branch back into the trunk you need to go to
			a working copy of the trunk.
			Select
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Merge...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			from the context menu.
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>From:</guilabel> field enter the full
						folder url of the <emphasis>trunk</emphasis>. This
						may sound wrong, but remember that the trunk is the
						start point to which you want to add the branch changes.
						You may also click
						<guibutton>...</guibutton>
						to browse the repository.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Because you are comparing two different trees, make sure
						the <guilabel>Use "From:" URL</guilabel> checkbox is
						<emphasis>not</emphasis> checked.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In the <guilabel>To:</guilabel> field enter the full
						folder url of the feature branch.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In both the <guilabel>From Revision</guilabel> field and
						the <guilabel>To Revision</guilabel> field, enter the
						last revision number at which the two trees were
						synchronized. If you are sure no-one else is making
						commits you can use the HEAD revision in both cases.
						If there is a chance that someone else may have made
						a commit since that synchronization, use the specific
						revision number to avoid losing more recent commits.
					</para>
					<para>
						You can also use <guibutton>Show Log</guibutton> to
						select the revision. Note that in this case you are
						not selecting a range of revisions, so the revision
						you select there is what will actually appear in the
						<guilabel>Revision</guilabel> field.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to complete the merge.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			In this case you will not need the feature branch again
			because the new feature is now integrated into the trunk.
			The feature branch is redundant and can be deleted
			from the repository if required.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-merge-3">
		<title>Previewing Merge Results</title>
		<para>
			If you are uncertain about the merge operation, you may want to
			preview what will happen do before you allow it to change your
			working copy. There are two additional buttons to help you.
		</para>
		<para>
			<guibutton>Unified Diff</guibutton> creates the diff file (remember
			that merge is based on diff) and shows you which lines will be changed
			in your working copy files. As this is a unified diff (patch) file it is
			not always easy to read out of context, but for small scale changes it
			is often helpful.
		</para>
		<para>
			<guibutton>Dry Run</guibutton> performs the merge operation, but does
			<emphasis>not</emphasis> modify the working copy at all.
			It shows you a list of the files that will be changed
			by a real merge, and notes those areas where conflicts will occur.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
