<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-shelving">
  <title>Shelving</title>
  <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SHELVE"?>
  <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_UNSHELVE"?>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>shelve</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>unshelve</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    More often than wanted, it's necessary to stop what you were working on
    and work on something else. For example a serious problem needs immediate
    dealing with and you have to stop working on the new feature.
    If possible, you should commit the changes you have done so far and then
    start working on the urgent issue, but often those changes would break
    the build or are just not ready for committing yet.
  </para>
  <para>
    So if you can't commit your local changes yet, you have to put them
    aside while you're working on the urgent issue. The <firstterm>shelving</firstterm>
    feature helps you do exactly that: you can store your local changes on
    a shelve, get your working copy in a clean state again and work on the
    issue. After you're finished with the urgent issue and you've committed
    those changes, you can <firstterm>unshelve</firstterm> your shelved
    work and continue working on your previous task again.
  </para>
  <para>
    Two new commands are implemented for this. One for shelving and one for
    unshelving.
  </para>
  <para>
    To shelve your local changes, select your working copy and use
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Shelve</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    The following dialog allows you to select the files you want to shelve and
    give a name under which you want to store them.
    <figure id="tsvn-dug-shelve-dlg">
      <title>Shelve dialog</title>
      <graphic fileref="../images/Shelve.png"/>
    </figure>
    If you select an existing shelf, then a new version is created for that shelf.
    If you provide a new name, a new shelf is created for the selected files.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you click the <guibutton>Shelve</guibutton> button, the shelf is created
    and your working copy files are reset to a clean state.
    If you click the <guibutton>Checkpoint</guibutton> button, the shelf
    is created but your local modifications are kept.
  </para>
  <para>
    To unshelve your changes, use
    <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
      <guimenuitem>Unshelve</guimenuitem>
    </menuchoice>
    to get the unshelve dialog. This dialog shows you a list of all shelved
    items. Select the shelved item you want and the version to apply back to your working copy
    and click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>.
    <figure id="tsvn-dug-unshelve-dlg">
      <title>Unshelve dialog</title>
      <graphic fileref="../images/Unshelve.png"/>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <tip>
    <para>
      Shelves are purely a local client feature. Creating and removing
      Shelves will not affect the repository, nor anyone else's working
      copy.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <warning>
    <para>
      The shelving feature is considered <literal>experimental</literal>
      in the Subversion library. Which means it might change significantly
      in future versions.
    </para>
    <para>
      So make sure that when you store changes on the shelf that you apply
      those changes before you update TortoiseSVN to another minor version
      (e.g. from 1.x to 1.y).
    </para>
  </warning>
</sect1>
