<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-settings-registry">
  <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGS_CONFIG"?>
  <title>Advanced Settings</title>
  <indexterm>
    <primary>registry</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>
    A few infrequently used settings are available only in the advanced
    page of the settings dialog. These settings modify the registry directly
    and you have to know what each of these settings is used for and what
    it does. Do not modify these settings unless you are sure you need to
    change them.
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">AllowAuthSave</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Sometimes multiple users use the same account on the same computer.
          In such situations it's not really wanted to save the authentication
          data. Setting this value to <literal>false</literal> disables the
          <literal>save authentication</literal> button in the authentication
          dialog.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">AllowUnversionedObstruction</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If an update adds a new file from the repository which
          already exists in the local working copy as an unversioned
          file, the default action is to keep the local file, showing
          it as a (possibly) modified version of the new file from the
          repository.
          If you would prefer TortoiseSVN to create a conflict in
          such situations, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">AlwaysExtendedMenu</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          As with the explorer, TortoiseSVN shows additional commands
          if the <keycap>Shift</keycap> key is pressed while the
          context menu is opened.
          To force TortoiseSVN to always show those extended commands,
          set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">AutoCompleteMinChars</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The minimum amount of chars from which the editor
          shows an auto-completion popup. The default value
          is <literal>3</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">AutocompleteRemovesExtensions</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The auto-completion list shown in the commit message editor
          displays the names of files listed for commit.
          To also include these names with extensions removed,
          set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">BlockPeggedExternals</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          File externals that are pegged to a specific revision are
          blocked by default from being selected for a commit. This
          is because a subsequent update would revert those changes again
          unless the pegged revision of the external is adjusted.
        </para>
        <para>
          Set this value to <literal>false</literal> in case you still
          want to commit changes to such external files.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">BlockStatus</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you don't want the explorer to update the status overlays
          while another TortoiseSVN command is running
          (e.g. Update, Commit, ...) then set this value to
          <literal>true</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">CacheTrayIcon</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          To add a cache tray icon for the TSVNCache program, set
          this value to <literal>true</literal>.
          This is really only useful for developers as it allows
          you to terminate the program gracefully.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">ColumnsEveryWhere</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The extra columns the TortoiseSVN adds to the details view
          in Windows Explorer are normally only active in a working
          copy. If you want those to be accessible everywhere, not
          just in working copies, set this value to
          <literal>true</literal>.
          Note that the extra columns are only available in XP.
          Vista and later doesn't support that feature any more.
          However some third-party explorer replacements do support
          those even on Windows versions later than XP.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">ConfigDir</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          You can specify a different location for the Subversion
          configuration file here.
          This will affect all TortoiseSVN operations.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">CtrlEnter</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In most dialogs in TortoiseSVN, you can use <keycap>Ctrl+Enter</keycap>
          to dismiss the dialog as if you clicked on the OK button.
          If you don't want this, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">Debug</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Set this to <literal>true</literal> if you want a dialog to
          pop up for every command showing the command line used to
          start TortoiseProc.exe.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">DebugOutputString</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Set this to <literal>true</literal> if you want TortoiseSVN
          to print out debug messages during execution. The messages
          can be captured with special debugging tools only.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">DialogTitles</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The default format (value of 0) of dialog titles is
          <literal>url/path - name of dialog - TortoiseSVN</literal>.
          If you set this value to 1, the format changes to
          <literal>name of dialog - url/path - TortoiseSVN</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">DiffBlamesWithTortoiseMerge</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          TortoiseSVN allows you to assign an external diff viewer.
          Most such viewers, however, are not suited for change blaming
          (<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-blame-diffs"/>),
          so you might wish to fall back to TortoiseMerge in this case.
          To do so, set this value to <literal>true</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">FixCaseRenames</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Some apps change the case of filenames without notice
          but those changes aren't really necessary nor wanted.
          For example a change from <filename>file.txt</filename>
          to <filename>FILE.TXT</filename> wouldn't bother
          normal Windows applications, but Subversion is case
          sensitive in these situations. So TortoiseSVN automatically
          fixes such case changes.
        </para>
        <para>
          If you don't want TortoiseSVN to automatically fix
          such case changes for you, you can set this value
          to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">FullRowSelect</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The status list control which is used in various dialogs
          (e.g., commit, check-for-modifications, add, revert, ...)
          uses full row selection (i.e., if you select an entry, the
          full row is selected, not just the first column).
          This is fine, but the selected row then also covers the
          background image on the bottom right, which can look ugly.
          To disable full row select, set this value to
          <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">GroupTaskbarIconsPerRepo</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This option determines how the Win7 taskbar icons of the various
          TortoiseSVN dialogs and windows are grouped together. This
          option has no effect on Vista!
        </para>
        <para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The default value is 0. With this setting, the
                icons are grouped together by application type.
                All dialogs from TortoiseSVN are grouped together,
                all windows from TortoiseMerge are grouped together, ...
                <figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-registry-task0-1">
                  <title>Taskbar with default grouping</title>
                  <graphic fileref="../images/TaskbarGroup0.png"/>
                </figure>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If set to 1, then instead of all dialogs in one
                single group per application, they're grouped
                together by repository. For example, if you have
                a log dialog and a commit dialog open for repository
                <literal>A</literal>, and a check-for-modifications
                dialog and a log dialog for repository <literal>B</literal>,
                then there are two application icon groups shown
                in the Win7 taskbar, one group for each repository.
                But TortoiseMerge windows are not grouped together
                with TortoiseSVN dialogs.
                <figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-registry-task1-1">
                  <title>Taskbar with repository grouping</title>
                  <graphic fileref="../images/TaskbarGroup1.png"/>
                </figure>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If set to 2, then the grouping works as with
                the setting set to 1, except that TortoiseSVN, TortoiseMerge,
                TortoiseBlame, TortoiseIDiff and TortoiseUDiff windows
                are all grouped together. For example, if you have
                the commit dialog open and then double click on
                a modified file, the opened TortoiseMerge diff window
                will be put in the same icon group on the taskbar
                as the commit dialog icon.
                <figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-registry-task2-1">
                  <title>Taskbar with repository grouping</title>
                  <graphic fileref="../images/TaskbarGroup2.png"/>
                </figure>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If set to 3, then the grouping works as with
                the setting set to 1, but the grouping isn't done
                according to the repository but according to the
                working copy. This is useful if you have all your
                projects in the same repository but different
                working copies for each project.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If set to 4, then the grouping works as with
                the setting set to 2, but the grouping isn't done
                according to the repository but according to the
                working copy.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">HideExternalInfo</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If this is set to <literal>false</literal>, then
          every <literal>svn:externals</literal> is shown
          during an update separately.
        </para>
        <para>
          If it is set to <literal>true</literal> (the default),
          then update information for externals is only shown
          if the externals are affected by the update, i.e.
          changed in some way. Otherwise nothing is shown
          as with normal files and folders.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">GroupTaskbarIconsPerRepoOverlay</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This has no effect if the option <literal>GroupTaskbarIconsPerRepo</literal>
          is set to 0 (see above).
        </para>
        <para>
          If this option is set to <literal>true</literal>, then every
          icon on the Win7 taskbar shows a small colored rectangle overlay,
          indicating the repository the dialogs/windows are used for.
          <figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-registry-overlay-1">
            <title>Taskbar grouping with repository color overlays</title>
            <graphic fileref="../images/TaskbarGroupOverlay.png"/>
          </figure>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">IncludeExternals</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          By default, TortoiseSVN always runs an update with externals
          included. This avoids problems with inconsistent working copies.
          If you have however a lot of externals set, an update can
          take quite a while. Set this value to <literal>false</literal>
          to run the default update with externals excluded. To
          update with externals included, either run the
          <literal>Update to revision...</literal> dialog or set this
          value to <literal>true</literal> again.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">LogFindCopyFrom</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When the log dialog is started from the merge wizard,
          already merged revisions are shown in gray, but revisions
          beyond the point where the branch was created are also shown.
          These revisions are shown in black because those can't be
          merged.
        </para>
        <para>
          If this option is set to <literal>true</literal> then TortoiseSVN
          tries to find the revision where the branch was created from
          and hide all the revisions that are beyond that revision.
          Since this can take quite a while, this option is disabled
          by default. Also this option doesn't work with some SVN servers
          (e.g., Google Code Hosting, see
          <ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/support/issues/detail?id=5471">
            <citetitle>issue #5471</citetitle>
          </ulink>).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">LogMultiRevFormat</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A format string for the log messages when multiple revisions
          are selected in the log dialog.
        </para>
        <para>
          You can use the following placeholders in your format string:
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term condition="pot">%1!ld!</term>
              <listitem>
                gets replaced with the revision number text
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term condition="pot">%2!s!</term>
              <listitem>
                gets replaced with the short log message of the revision
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">LogStatusCheck</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The log dialog shows the revision the working copy path
          is at in bold. But this requires that the log dialog fetches
          the status of that path. Since for very big working copies
          this can take a while, you can set this value to <literal>false</literal>
          to deactivate this feature.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">MergeLogSeparator</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          When you merge revisions from another branch, and merge tracking
          information is available, the log messages from the revisions
          you merge will be collected to make up a commit log message.
          A pre-defined string is used to separate the individual log
          messages of the merged revisions. If you prefer, you can set
          this to a value containing a separator string of your choice.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">NumDiffWarning</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you want to show the diff at once for more items
          than specified with this settings, a warning dialog
          is shown first. The default is 10.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">OldVersionCheck</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          TortoiseSVN checks whether there's a new version available
          about once a week. If an updated version is found, the
          commit dialog shows a link control with that info.
          If you prefer the old behavior back where a dialog
          pops up notifying you about the update, set this value to
          <literal>true</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">RepoBrowserTrySVNParentPath</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The repository browser tries to fetch the web page that's
          generated by an SVN server configured with the SVNParentPath
          directive to get a list of all repositories. To disable that
          behavior, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">ScintillaDirect2D</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This option enables the use of Direct2D accelerated
          drawing in the Scintilla control which is used
          as the edit box in e.g. the commit dialog, and also
          for the unified diff viewer.
          With some graphic cards however this sometimes
          doesn't work properly so that the cursor to enter
          text isn't always visible. If that happens, you
          can turn this feature off by setting this value
          to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">OutOfDateRetry</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you don't want TortoiseSVN to ask you to update
          the working copy automatically after an <literal>Out of date</literal>
          error, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">ShellMenuAccelerators</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          TortoiseSVN uses accelerators for its explorer context menu
          entries. Since this can lead to doubled accelerators (e.g.
          the <literal>SVN Commit</literal> has the <keycap>Alt-C</keycap>
          accelerator, but so does the <literal>Copy</literal> entry
          of explorer).
          If you don't want or need the accelerators of the TortoiseSVN
          entries, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">ShowContextMenuIcons</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This can be useful if you use something other than the windows explorer
          or if you get problems with the context menu displaying incorrectly.
          Set this value to <literal>false</literal>
          if you don't want TortoiseSVN to show icons for the
          shell context menu items.
          Set this value to <literal>true</literal> to show the icons again.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">ShowAppContextMenuIcons</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you don't want TortoiseSVN to show icons for the context menus
          in its own dialogs, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">StyleCommitMessages</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The commit and log dialog use styling (e.g. bold, italic)
          in commit messages
          (see <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-commit-log"/> for details).
          If you don't want to do this, set the value to
          <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">UpdateCheckURL</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This value contains the URL from which TortoiseSVN tries
          to download a text file to find out if there are updates
          available.
          This might be useful for company admins who don't want
          their users to update TortoiseSVN until they approve it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term condition="pot">VersionCheck</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          TortoiseSVN checks whether there's a new version available
          about once a week. If you don't want TortoiseSVN to do this
          check, set this value to <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</sect2>