<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-settings-main">
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSMAIN"?>
	<title>General Settings</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>sounds</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-main">
			<title>The Settings Dialog, General Page</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/SettingsMain.png"/>
		</figure>
		This dialog allows you to specify your preferred language,
		and the Subversion-specific settings.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Language</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Selects your user interface language.
					What else did you expect?
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Automatically check for newer versions every week</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If checked, TortoiseSVN will contact its download site once a week 
					to see if there is a newer version of the program available.
					Use <guibutton>Check now</guibutton> if you want an answer
					right away. The new version will not be downloaded; you
					simply receive an information dialog telling you that the
					new version is available.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>System sounds</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					TortoiseSVN has three custom sounds which are installed by default.
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							Error
							</para>
							</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							Notice
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							Warning
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					You can select different sounds (or turn these sounds
					off completely) using the Windows Control Panel.
					<guibutton>Configure</guibutton> is a shortcut to the Control Panel.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Global ignore pattern</term>
			<listitem>
				<indexterm>
					<primary>exclude pattern</primary>
				</indexterm>
				<indexterm>
					<primary>global ignore</primary>
				</indexterm>
				<para>
					Global ignore patterns are used to prevent unversioned files from
					showing up e.g. in the commit dialog. Files matching the
					patterns are also ignored by an import.
					Ignore files or directories by typing in the names or extensions.
					Patterns are separated by spaces e.g.
					<literal>*/bin */obj *.bak *.~?? *.jar *.[Tt]mp</literal>.
					Remember that these patterns may be used against paths which
					include N levels of parent directory. Setting ignore patterns
					for anything other than simple file extensions is not as trivial
					as it first appears, so be sure to read
					<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-ignore-glob"/> for more information
					on the pattern-matching syntax, and how paths are checked.
				</para>
				<para>
					Note that the ignore patterns you specify here will also
					affect other Subversion clients running on your PC, including
					the command line client.
				</para>
				<caution>
					<para>
					If you use the Subversion configuration file to set
					a <literal>global-ignores</literal> pattern, it will
					override the settings you make here. The Subversion
					configuration file is accessed using the
					<guibutton>Edit</guibutton> as described below.
					</para>
				</caution>
				<para>
					This ignore pattern will affect all your projects.
					It is not versioned, so it will not affect other users.
					By contrast you can also use the versioned
					<literal>svn:ignore</literal> property to exclude
					files or directories from version control. Read
					<xref linkend="tsvn-dug-ignore"/>
					for more information.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Set file dates to the "last commit time"</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This option tells TortoiseSVN to set the file dates to
					the last commit time when doing a checkout or an update.
					Otherwise TortoiseSVN will use the current date.
					If you are developing software it is generally best
					to use the current date because build systems normally
					look at the date stamps to decide which files need
					compiling. If you use "last commit time" and revert
					to an older file revision, your project may not compile
					as you expect it to.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Subversion configuration file</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Use <guibutton>Edit</guibutton> to edit the 
					Subversion configuration file directly.
					Some settings cannot be modified directly by 
					TortoiseSVN, and need to be set here instead.
					For more information about the Subversion 
					<filename>config</filename> file see the 
					<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.2/svn.advanced.html">
						<citetitle>Runtime Configuration Area</citetitle>
					</ulink>.
					The section on 
					<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.2/svn.advanced.props.html">
						<citetitle>Automatic Property Setting</citetitle>
					</ulink>
					is of particular interest, and that is configured here.
					Note that Subversion can read configuration information
					from several places, and you need to know which one
					takes priority. Refer to 
					<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.2/svn.advanced.html">
						<citetitle>Configuration and the Windows Registry</citetitle>
					</ulink> to find out more.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Use "_svn" instead of ".svn" directories</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					VS.NET when used with web projects can't handle the <literal>.svn</literal>
					folders that Subversion uses to store its internal information.
					This is not a bug in Subversion. The bug is in VS.NET and the frontpage
					extensions it uses. Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-settings-asp-dot-net"/>
					to find out more about this issue.
				</para>
				<para>
					If you want to change the behaviour of Subversion and TortoiseSVN,
					you can use this checkbox to set the environment variable which
					controls this.
				</para>
				<para>
					You should note that changing this option will not automatically
					convert existing working copies to use the new admin directory.
					You will have to do that yourself using a script (See our FAQ)
					or simply check out a fresh working copy.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</sect2>
