<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-cleanup">
    <title>Cleanup</title>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>cleanup</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_CLEANUP"?>
    <para>
        If a Subversion command cannot complete successfully, perhaps
        due to server problems, your working copy can be left in an
        inconsistent state. In that case you need to use
        <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Cleanup</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>
        on the folder. It is a good idea to do this at the top level
        of the working copy.
    </para>
    <para>
        In the cleanup dialog, there are also other useful options
        to get the working copy into a <literal>clean</literal> state.
        <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Clean up working copy status</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        As stated above, this option tries to get an inconsistent
                        working copy into a workable and usable state. This doesn't
                        affect any data you have but only the internal states of
                        the working copy database. This is the actual
                        <literal>Cleanup</literal> command you know from older
                        TortoiseSVN clients or other SVN clients.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Refresh shell overlays</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Sometimes the shell overlays, especially on the tree view
                        on the left side of the explorer don't show the current
                        status, or the status cache failed to recognize changes.
                        In this situation, you can use this command to force
                        a refresh.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Include externals</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        If this is checked, then all actions are done for all
                        files and folders included with the <literal>svn:externals</literal>
                        property as well.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Delete unversioned files and folders, Delete ignored files and folders</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This is a fast and easy way to remove all generated files
                        in your working copy. All files and folders that are not
                        versioned are moved to the trash bin.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Note: you can also do the same from the
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Revert</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice> dialog. There you also get a list of all
                        the unversioned files and folders to select for removal.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
                <term>Revert all changes recursively</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        This command reverts all your local modifications which
                        are not committed yet.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Note: it's better to use the
                        <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                            <guimenuitem>Revert</guimenuitem>
                        </menuchoice> command instead, because there you can
                        first see and select the files which you want to revert.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
    </para>
</sect1>
