<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage">
	<title>Project Settings</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>properties</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		<figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-dia-1">
			<title>Explorer property page, Subversion tab</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/Properties.png"/>
		</figure>
		Sometimes you want to have more detailed information
		about a file/directory than just the icon overlay.
		You can get all the information Subversion provides in the
		explorer properties dialog. Just select the file or
		directory and select
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Windows Menu</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>
		in the context menu (note: this is the normal properties menu entry
		the explorer provides, not the one in the TortoiseSVN submenu!).
		In the properties dialog box TortoiseSVN has added a new
		property page for files/folders under Subversion control,
		where you can see all relevant information about the
		selected file/directory.
	</para>
    <sect2 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-props">
        <title>Subversion Properties</title>
        <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPERTIES"?>
        <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_EDITPROPERTYVALUE"?>
        <para>
            <figure id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-dia-2">
                <title>Subversion property page</title>
                <graphic fileref="../images/PropertyList.png"/>
            </figure>
            You can read and set the Subversion properties
            from the Windows properties dialog, but also from
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
            and within TSVN's status lists, from
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>.
        </para>
        <para>
            You can add your own properties, or some properties with a 
            special meaning in Subversion. These begin with <literal>svn:</literal>. 
            <literal>svn:externals</literal> is such a property; see how to handle
            externals in <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-import-4"/>.
            For more information about properties in Subversion see the  
            <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.1/ch07s02.html#svn-ch-7-sect-2.3">
                <citetitle>Subversion Manual</citetitle>
            </ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
            To add a new property, first click on <guilabel>Add...</guilabel>.
            Select the required property name from the combo box,
            or type in a name of your own choice, then enter a value
            in the box below. Properties which take multiple values, such as an
            ignore list, can be entered on multiple lines.
            Click on <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to add that property to the list.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you want to apply a property to many items at once, select the
            files/folders in explorer, then select
            <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Context menu</guimenu>
                <guimenuitem>properties</guimenuitem>
            </menuchoice>
        </para>
        <para>
            If you want to apply the property to <emphasis>every</emphasis> file
            and folder in the hierarchy below the current folder, check the
            <guilabel>Recursive</guilabel> checkbox.
        </para>
        <para>
            Some properties, for example <literal>svn:needs-lock</literal>,
            can only be applied to files, so the property name doesn't appear
            in the drop down list for folders. You can still apply such a
            property recursively to all files in a hierarchy, but you have
            to type in the property name yourself.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you wish to edit an existing property, select that property from
            the list of existing properties, then click on <guibutton>Edit...</guibutton>.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you wish to remove an existing property, select that property from
            the list of existing properties, then click on <guibutton>Remove</guibutton>.
        </para>
        <para>
            The <literal>svn:externals</literal> property can be used to
            pull in other projects from the same repository or a completely
            different repository. For more information, read
            <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-import-4"/>.
        </para>
        <para>
            TortoiseSVN can handle binary property values using files.
            To read a binary property value, <guibutton>Save...</guibutton>
            to a file. To set a binary value, use a hex editor or other appropriate
            tool to create a file with the content you require, then
            <guibutton>Load...</guibutton> from that file.
        </para>
        <important>
            <title>Commit properties</title>
            <para>
                Subversion properties are versioned. After you change or add a 
                property you have to commit your changes.
            </para>
        </important>
        <tip>
            <title>Conflicts on properties</title>
            <para>
                If there's a conflict on committing the changes, because another 
                user has changed the same property, Subversion generates a 
                <filename>.prej</filename> file. Delete this file after you 
                have resolved the conflict. 
            </para>
        </tip>
        <tip>
            <title>Automatic property setting</title>
            <para>
                You can configure Subversion to set properties automatically 
                on files and folders when they are added to the repository.
                Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-settings"/> for further information. 
            </para>
        </tip>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="tsvn-dug-propertypage-tsvn-props">
        <title>TortoiseSVN Properties</title>
        <para>
            TortoiseSVN has a few special properties of its own, and these begin
            with <literal>tsvn:</literal>.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>tsvn:logminsize</literal>
                        sets the minimum length of a log message for a commit.
                        If you enter a shorter message than specified here, the commit
                        is disabled. This feature is very useful for reminding you to
                        supply a proper descriptive message for every commit.
                        If this property is not set,
                        or the value is zero, empty log messages are allowed.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        <literal>tsvn:lockmsgminsize</literal>
                        sets the minimum length of a lock message.
                        If you enter a shorter message than specified here, the lock
                        is disabled. This feature is very useful for reminding you to
                        supply a proper descriptive message for every lock you get.
                        If this property is not set,
                        or the value is zero, empty lock messages are allowed.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>tsvn:logwidthmarker</literal> is used with projects which
                        require log messages to be formatted with some maximum width
                        (typically 80 characters) before a line break. Setting this
                        property to a non-zero will do 2 things in the log message
                        entry dialog: it places a marker to indicate the maximum width,
                        and it disables word wrap in the display, so that you can see
                        whether the text you entered is too long. Note: this feature
                        will only work correctly if you have a fixed-width font
                        selected for log messages.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <literal>tsvn:logtemplate</literal> is used with projects which
                        have rules about log message formatting. The property holds
                        a multi-line text string which will be inserted in the commit
                        message box when you start a commit. You can then edit it to
                        include the required information. Note: if you are also using
                        <literal>tsvn:logminsize</literal>, be sure to set the length
                        longer than the template or you will lose the protection mechanism.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        In the Commit dialog you have the option to paste in the
                        list of changed files, including the status of each file
                        (added, modified, etc).
                        <literal>tsvn:logfilelistenglish</literal> defines whether
                        the file status is inserted in english or in the localized
                        language. If the property is not set, the default is
                        <literal>true</literal>. 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        TortoiseSVN can use spell checker modules which are also
                        used by OpenOffice and Mozilla. If you have those installed
                        this property will determine which spell checker to use, i.e.
                        in which language the log messages for your project should
                        be written.
                        <literal>tsvn:projectlanguage</literal> sets the language
                        module the spell checking engine should use when you enter
                        a log message. You can find the values for your language
                        on this page:
                        <ulink url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/intl/nls_238z.asp">
                            <citetitle>MSDN: Language Identifiers</citetitle>
                        </ulink>.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        You can enter this value in decimal, or in hexadecimal if
                        prefixed with <literal>0x</literal>.
                        For example English (US) can be entered as
                        <literal>0x0409</literal> or <literal>1033</literal>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
            Some <literal>tsvn:</literal> properties require a
            <literal>true/false</literal> value. TSVN also understands
            <literal>yes</literal> as a synonym for <literal>true</literal> and
            <literal>no</literal> as a synonym for <literal>false</literal>.
        </para>
        <important>
            <title>Set the tsvn: properties on folders</title>
            <para>
                These <literal>tsvn:</literal> properties must be set on
                <emphasis>folders</emphasis> for the system to work. 
                When you commit a file or folder the properties are read from that folder.
                If the properties are not found there, TortoiseSVN will search upwards
                through the folder tree to find them until it comes to an unversioned
                folder, or the tree root (eg. <literal>C:\</literal>) is found.
                If you can be sure that each user checks out only from e.g
                <filename>trunk/</filename> and not some subfolder, then it is
                sufficient to set the properties on <filename>trunk/</filename>.
                If you can't be sure, you should set the properties recursively on each subfolder.
                A property setting deeper in the project hierarchy overrides settings on
                higher levels (closer to <filename>trunk/</filename>).
            </para>
            <para>
                For <literal>tsvn:</literal> properties <emphasis>only</emphasis>
                you can use the <guilabel>Recursive</guilabel> checkbox to set
                the property to all subfolders in the hierarchy, without also
                setting it on all files.
            </para>
        </important>
        <para>
            TortoiseSVN can integrate with some bugtracking 
            tools. This uses properties, which start with <literal>bugtraq:</literal>.
            Read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-bugtracker"/> for further information. 
        </para>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
