<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-dug-externals">
	<title>External Items</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>external repositories</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>externals</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<para>
		Sometimes it is useful to construct a working copy that is made out
		of a number of different checkouts. For example, you may want different
		files or subdirectories to come from different locations in a repository,
		or perhaps from different repositories altogether. 
		If you want every user to have the same layout, you can define the
		<literal>svn:externals</literal> properties to pull in the specified
		resource at the locations where they are needed.
	</para>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-externals-folders">
		<title>External Folders</title>
		<para>
			Let's say you check out a working copy of
			<filename>/project1</filename> to
			<filename>D:\dev\project1</filename>.
			Select the folder <filename>D:\dev\project1</filename>,
			<action>right click</action> and choose 
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Windows Menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			from the context menu. 
			The Properties Dialog comes up. Then go to the Subversion tab.
			There, you can set properties. Click <guibutton>Add...</guibutton>.
			Select the <literal>svn:externals</literal> property from the
			combobox and write in the edit box the repository URL in the format
			<literal>url folder</literal>
			or if you want to specify a particular revision,
			<literal>-rREV url folder</literal>
			You can add multiple external projects, 1 per line.
			Suppose that you have set these properties on
			<filename>D:\dev\project1</filename>:
<screen>
http://sounds.red-bean.com/repos  sounds
http://graphics.red-bean.com/repos/fast%20graphics  "quick graphs"
-r21 http://svn.red-bean.com/repos/skin-maker  skins/toolkit
</screen>
			Now click <guibutton>Set</guibutton> and commit your changes.
			When you (or any other user) update your working copy, Subversion
			will create a sub-folder 
			<filename>D:\dev\project1\sounds</filename> and checkout the sounds
			project, another sub-folder <filename>D:\dev\project1\quick_graphs</filename>
			containing the graphics project, and finally a nested sub-folder
			<filename>D:\dev\project1\skins\toolkit</filename> containing
			revision 21 of the skin-maker project.
		</para>
		<para>
			URLs must be properly escaped or they will not work, e.g. you must 
			replace each space with <literal>%20</literal> as shown in the 
			second example above.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you want the local path to include spaces or other special characters,
			you can enclose it in double quotes, or you can use the <literal>\</literal>
			(backslash) character as a Unix shell style escape character preceding any
			special character. Of course this also means that you must use 
			<literal>/</literal> (forward slash) as a path delimiter.
			Note that this behaviour is new in Subversion 1.6 and will not work with
			older clients.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<title>Use explicit revision numbers</title>
			<para>
				You should strongly consider using explicit revision numbers
				in all of your externals definitions, as described above.
				Doing so means
				that you get to decide when to pull down a different snapshot
				of external information, and exactly which snapshot to pull.
				Besides the common sense aspect of not being surprised by
				changes to third-party repositories that you might not have
				any control over, using explicit revision numbers also means
				that as you backdate your working copy to a previous
				revision, your externals definitions will also revert to the
				way they looked in that previous revision, which in turn means
				that the external working copies will be updated to match they
				way <emphasis>they</emphasis> looked back when your repository was
				at that previous revision.  For software projects, this could
				be the difference between a successful and a failed build of
				an older snapshot of your complex code base.
			</para>
		</tip>
		<tip>
			<title>Older svn:externals definitions</title>
			<para>
				The format shown here was introduced in Subversion 1.5. You may
				also see the older format which has the same information in a
				different order. The new format is preferred as it supports
				several useful features described below, but it will not work on
				older clients. The differences are shown in the
				<ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.5/svn.advanced.externals.html">
					<citetitle>Subversion Book</citetitle>
				</ulink>.
			</para>
		</tip>
		<para>
			If the external project is in the same repository, any changes
			you make there there will be included in the commit list when
			you commit your main project.
		</para>
		<para>
			If the external project is in a different repository, any
			changes you make to the external project will be notified
			when you commit the main project, but you have to commit
			those external changes separately.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you use absolute URLs in <literal>svn:externals</literal>
			definitions and you have to relocate your working copy (i.e.,
			if the URL of your repository changes), then your externals
			won't change and might not work anymore.
		</para>
		<para>
			To avoid such problems, Subversion clients version 1.5 and
			higher support relative external URLs. Four different methods
			of specifying a relative URL are supported.
			In the following examples, assume we have two repositories: one at
			<systemitem class="url">http://example.com/svn/repos-1</systemitem>
			and another at
			<systemitem class="url">http://example.com/svn/repos-2</systemitem>.
			We have a checkout of
			<systemitem class="url">http://example.com/svn/repos-1/project/trunk</systemitem>
			into <filename>C:\Working</filename> and the <literal>svn:externals</literal>
			property is set on trunk.
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Relative to parent directory</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						These URLs always begin with the string <literal>../</literal>
						for example:
<screen>
../../widgets/foo  common/foo-widget
</screen>
						This will extract
						<systemitem class="url">http://example.com/svn/repos-1/widgets/foo</systemitem>
						into
						<filename>C:\Working\common\foo-widget</filename>.
					</para>
					<para>
						Note that the URL is relative to the URL of the directory with the
						<literal>svn:externals</literal> property, not to the directory where
						the external is written to disk.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Relative to repository root</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						These URLs always begin with the string <literal>^/</literal>
						for example:
<screen>
^/widgets/foo  common/foo-widget
</screen>
						This will extract
						<systemitem class="url">http://example.com/svn/repos-1/widgets/foo</systemitem>
						into
						<filename>C:\Working\common\foo-widget</filename>.
					</para>
					<para>
						You can easily refer to other repositories with the same
						<literal>SVNParentPath</literal> (a common directory holding
						several repositories). For example:
<screen>
^/../repos-2/hammers/claw  common/claw-hammer
</screen>
						This will extract
						<systemitem class="url">http://example.com/svn/repos-2/hammers/claw</systemitem>
						into
						<filename>C:\Working\common\claw-hammer</filename>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Relative to scheme</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						URLs beginning with the string <literal>//</literal> copy
						only the scheme part of the URL. This is useful when the same hostname
						must the accessed with different schemes depending upon network location;
						e.g. clients in the intranet use <systemitem class="url">http://</systemitem>
						while external clients use <systemitem class="url">svn+ssh://</systemitem>.
						For example:
<screen>
//example.com/svn/repos-1/widgets/foo  common/foo-widget
</screen>
						This will extract
						<systemitem class="url">http://example.com/svn/repos-1/widgets/foo</systemitem>
						or
						<systemitem class="url">svn+ssh://example.com/svn/repos-1/widgets/foo</systemitem>
						depending on which method was used to checkout
						<filename>C:\Working</filename>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Relative to the server's hostname</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						URLs beginning with the string <literal>/</literal> copy
						the scheme and the hostname part of the URL, for example:
<screen>
/svn/repos-1/widgets/foo  common/foo-widget
</screen>
						This will extract
						<systemitem class="url">http://example.com/svn/repos-1/widgets/foo</systemitem>
						into
						<filename>C:\Working\common\foo-widget</filename>.
						But if you checkout your working copy from another server at
						<systemitem class="url">svn+ssh://another.mirror.net/svn/repos-1/project1/trunk</systemitem>
						then the external reference will extract
						<systemitem class="url">svn+ssh://another.mirror.net/svn/repos-1/widgets/foo</systemitem>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
			You can also specify a peg revision after the URL if required, e.g.
			<systemitem class="url">http://sounds.red-bean.com/repos@19</systemitem>.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you need more information how TortoiseSVN
			handles Properties read <xref linkend="tsvn-dug-propertypage"/>.
		</para>
		<para>
			To find out about different methods of accessing common sub-projects
			read <xref linkend="tsvn-howto-common-projects"/>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-externals-files">
		<title>External Files</title>
		<para>
			As of Subversion 1.6 you can add single file externals to
			your working copy using the same syntax as for folders.
			However, there are some restrictions.
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The path to the file external must place the file in an existing 
					versioned folder. In general it makes most sense to place the file
					directly in the folder that has <literal>svn:externals</literal> 
					set, but it can be in a versioned sub-folder if necessary. 
					By contrast, directory externals will automatically create any 
					intermediate unversioned folders as required.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The URL for a file external must be in the same repository as the URL
					that the file external will be inserted into; inter-repository file
					externals are not supported.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			A file external behaves just like any other versioned file in many respects,
			but they cannot be moved or deleted using the normal commands; the
			<literal>svn:externals</literal> property must be modified instead.
		</para>
		<warning>
			<title>File externals support incomplete in Subversion 1.6</title>
			<para>
				In subversion 1.6 it is not possible to remove a file external
				from your working copy once you have added it, even if you delete
				the <literal>svn:externals</literal> property altogether. You
				have to checkout a fresh working copy to remove the file.
			</para>
		</warning>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
