<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-import">
	<title>Importing Data Into A Repository</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>import</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>Repository</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_IMPORT"?>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-import-1">
		<title>Repository Layout</title>
		<para>
			Before you import your data into the repository you should
			first think about how you want to organize your data. If you
			use one of the recommended layouts you will later have it much
			easier.
		</para>
		<para>
			There are some standard, recommended ways to organize a
			repository. Most people create a <filename>trunk</filename>
			directory to hold the "main line" of development, a
			<filename>branches</filename> directory to contain branch
			copies, and a <filename>tags</filename> directory to contain
			tag copies. If a repository holds only one project, then
			often people create these top-level directories:
		</para>
		<screen>
/trunk
/branches
/tags
</screen>
		<para>
			If a repository contains multiple projects, people often
			index their layout by branch:
		</para>
		<screen>
/trunk/paint
/trunk/calc
/branches/paint
/branches/calc
/tags/paint
/tags/calc
</screen>
		<para>
			...or by project:
		</para>
		<screen>
/paint/trunk
/paint/branches
/paint/tags
/calc/trunk
/calc/branches
/calc/tags
</screen>
		<para>
			Indexing by project makes sense if the projects are not closely related
			and each one is checked out individually. For related projects where
			you may want to check out all projects in one go, or where the projects
			are all tied together in a single distribution package, it is often better
			to index by branch. This way you have only one trunk to checkout, and
			the relationships between the sub-projects is more easily visible.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you adopt a top level <filename>/trunk /tags /branches</filename>
			approach, there is nothing to say that you have to copy the entire trunk
			for every branch and tag, and in some ways this structure offers the
			most flexibility.
		</para>
		<para>
			For unrelated projects you may prefer to use separate repositories.
			When you commit changes, it is the revision number of the whole
			repository which changes, not the revision number of the project.
			Having 2 unrelated projects share a repository can mean large gaps
			in the revision numbers. The Subversion and TortoiseSVN projects
			appear at the same host address, but are completely separate
			repositories allowing independent development, and no confusion
			over build numbers.
		</para>
		<para>
			Of course, you're free to ignore these common layouts.  You
			can create any sort of variation, whatever works best for you or
			your team.  Remember that whatever you choose, it's not a
			permanent commitment.  You can reorganize your repository at any
			time.  Because branches and tags are ordinary directories,
			TortoiseSVN can move or rename them however you wish. 
		</para>
		<para>
			Switching from one layout to another is just a matter of 
			issuing a series of server-side moves; If you don't like the 
			way things are organized in the repository, just juggle the 
			directories around.
		</para>
		<para>
			So if you haven't already created a basic folder structure inside
			your repository you should do that now:
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						create a new empty folder on your hard drive
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						create your desired top-level folder structure inside
						that folder - don't put any files in it yet!
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						import this structure into the repository via a 
						<action>right click</action> on the folder and
						selecting
						<menuchoice>
							<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
							<guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem>
						</menuchoice>
						This will import your temp
						folder into the repository root to create the basic
						repository layout.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			Note that the name of the folder you are importing does not appear in
			the repository, only its contents. For example, create the following folder
			structure:
<screen>
C:\Temp\New\trunk
C:\Temp\New\branches
C:\Temp\New\tags
</screen>
			Import <filename>C:\Temp\New</filename> into the repository root,
			which will then look like this:
<screen>
/trunk
/branches
/tags
</screen>
		</para>
		<para>
			You can also use the repository browser to create new folders directly
			in the repository.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-import-2">
		<title>Import</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>temporary files</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Before you import your project into a repository you should:
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Remove all files which are not needed to
						build the project (temporary files, files which are
						generated by a compiler e.g. *.obj, compiled
						binaries, ...)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Organize the files in folders and
						subfolders. Although it is possible to rename/move
						files later it is highly recommended to get your project's
						structure straight before importing!
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			Now select the top-level folder of your project
			directory structure in the windows explorer and
			<action>right click</action>
			to open the context menu. Select the command
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			which brings up a dialog box:
			<figure id="tsvn-DUG-import-dia-1">
				<title>The Import dialog</title>
				<graphic fileref="../images/Import.png"/>
			</figure>
		</para>
		<para>
			In this dialog you have to enter the URL of the repository into
			which you want to import your project.
		</para>
		<para>
			The import message is used as a log message. Since you
			usually just started your project a default <literal>initial import</literal>
			is filled in by TortoiseSVN.
		</para>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>exclude pattern</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<important>
			<para>
				Files or directories which match the 
				<guilabel>exclude pattern</guilabel>
				are <emphasis>not</emphasis> imported.
			</para>
		</important>
		<para>
			As soon as you press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> TortoiseSVN imports the
			complete directory tree including all files into the repository.
			As before, the name of the folder you import does not appear in
			the repository, only the folder contents.
			The project is now stored in the repository under version control.
			Please note that the folder you imported is <emphasis>NOT</emphasis>
			under version control! To get a version-controlled
			<firstterm>working copy</firstterm>
			you need to do a Checkout of the version you just imported.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-import-3">
		<title>Special Files</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>special files</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Sometimes you need to have a file under version control which contains
			user specific data. That means you have a file which every developer/user
			needs to modify to suit his/her local setup. But versioning such a file
			is difficult because every user would commit his/her changes every
			time to the repository.
		</para>
		<para>
			In such cases we suggest to use <literal>template</literal> files.
			You create a file which contains all the data your developers
			will need, add that file to version control and let the developers
			check this file out. Then, each developer has to <emphasis>make a copy</emphasis>
			of that file and rename that copy. After that, modifying the copy
			is not a problem anymore.
		</para>
		<para>
			As an example, you can have a look at TortoiseSVN's build script. It
			calls a file named <filename>TortoiseVars.bat</filename> which
			doesn't exist in the repository. Only the file
			<filename>TortoiseVars.tmpl</filename>.
			<filename>TortoiseVars.tmpl</filename> is the template file which
			every developer has to create a copy from and rename that file
			to <filename>TortoiseVars.bat</filename>. Inside that file, we added
			comments so that the users will see which lines they have to edit
			and change according to their local setup to get it working.
		</para>
		<para>
			So as not to disturb the users, we also added the file
			<filename>TortoiseVars.bat</filename> to the ignore list of its
			parent folder, i.e. we've set the Subversion property
			<literal>svn:ignored</literal> to include that filename.
			That way it won't show up as unversioned on every commit.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	<sect2 id="tsvn-DUG-import-4">
		<title>Referenced Projects</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>external repositories</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>externals</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Sometimes it is useful to construct a working copy that is made out
			of a number of different checkouts. For example, you may want different
			subdirectories to come from different locations in a repository, or
			perhaps from different repositories altogether. 
			If you want every user to have the same layout, you can define the
			<literal>svn:externals</literal> properties.
		</para>
		<para>
			Let's say you check out a working copy of
			<filename>/project1</filename> to
			<filename>D:\dev\project1</filename>.
			Select the folder <filename>D:\dev\project1</filename>,
			<action>right click</action> and choose 
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Windows Menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			from the context menu. 
			The Properties Dialog comes up. Then go to the Subversion tab.
			There, you can set properties. Select the
			<literal>svn:externals</literal> property from the combobox and
			write in the edit box the repository url in the format
			<literal>name url</literal>
			or if you want to specify a particular revision,
			<literal>name -rREV url</literal>
			You can add multiple external projects, 1 per line.
			Note that URLs and filenames must be properly escaped or they will
			not work properly. For example you must replace each space with
			<literal>%20</literal>.
			Suppose that you have set these properties on
			<filename>D:\dev\project1</filename>:
<screen>
sounds   http://sounds.red-bean.com/repos
quick%20graphs  http://graphics.red-bean.com/repos/fast%20graphics
skins/toolkit -r21 http://svn.red-bean.com/repos/skin-maker
</screen>
			Now click <guibutton>Set</guibutton> and commit your changes.
			When you (or any other user) update your working copy, Subversion
			will create a subfolder 
			<filename>D:\dev\project1\sounds</filename> and checkout the sounds
			project, another subfolder <filename>D:\dev\project1\quick graphs</filename>
			containing the graphics project, and finally a nested subfolder
			<filename>D:\dev\project1\skins\toolkit</filename> containing
			revision 21 of the skin-maker project.
		</para>
		<para>
			If the external project is in the same repository, any changes
			you make there there will be included in the commit list when
			you commit your main project.
		</para>
		<para>
			If the external project is in a different repository, any
			changes you make to the external project will be notified
			when you commit the main project, but you have to commit
			those external changes separately.
		</para>
		<para>
			Note that if you change the URL in an <literal>svn:externals</literal>
			property, then next time you update your working copy Subversion will
			delete the old external folder and make a fresh checkout, so you
			will see files being <literal>Added</literal>, rather than being
			<literal>Updated</literal> as you might have expected. This
			situation might occur if you reference a tag from another
			project. When a new version of that project is released, you
			change your external reference to point to the new tag.
		</para>
		<tip>
			<para>
			You should strongly consider using explicit revision numbers
			in all of your externals definitions.  Doing so means
			that you get to decide when to pull down a different snapshot
			of external information, and exactly which snapshot to pull.
			Besides the common sense aspect of not being surprised by
			changes to third-party repositories that you might not have
			any control over, using explicit revision numbers also means
			that as you backdate your working copy to a previous
			revision, your externals definitions will also revert to the
			way they looked in that previous revision, which in turn means
			that the external working copies will be updated to match they
			way <emphasis>they</emphasis> looked back when your repository was
			at that previous revision.  For software projects, this could
			be the difference between a successful and a failed build of
			an older snapshot of your complex codebase.
		</para>
		</tip>
		<para>
			URLs in <literal>svn:externals</literal> definitions are absolute.
			You cannot use relative URLs. If you relocate your working copy,
			or if the external repository is relocated, these URLs will not be
			updated automatically. Also, if you branch a project which has
			external references within the same repository, the URLs in the
			branched copy will be unchanged; you may then want to change trunk
			references to branch references instead.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you need more information how TortoiseSVN
			handles Properties read <xref linkend="tsvn-DUG-propertypage"/>.
		</para>
		<para>
			To find out about different methods of accessing common sub-projects
			read <xref linkend="tsvn-howto-common-projects"/>.
		</para>
	</sect2>
</sect1>
