<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sect1 id="tsvn-DUG-checkout">
	<title>Checking Out A Working Copy</title>
	<indexterm>
		<primary>checkout</primary>
	</indexterm>
	<?dbhh topicname="HIDD_CHECKOUT"?>
	<para>
		To obtain a working copy you need to do a <firstterm>checkout</firstterm>
		from a repository.
	</para>
	<para>
		Select a directory in windows explorer where you want to place
		your working copy. <action>Right click</action> to pop up the
		context menu and select the command
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
			<guimenuitem>Checkout...</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice>,
		which brings up the following dialog box:
		<figure id="tsvn-DUG-checkout-dia-1">
			<title>The Checkout dialog</title>
			<graphic fileref="../images/Checkout.png"/>
		</figure>
		If you enter a folder name that does not yet exist, then a
		directory with that name is created.
	</para>
	<important>
		<para>
			You should only check out into an empty directory. If you want to check out
			your source tree into the same directory that you imported from, Subversion
			will throw an error message because it will not overwrite the existing
			unversioned files with versioned ones.
			You will have to check out into a different directory or delete the 
			existing sourcetree first.
		</para>
	</important>
	<para>
		If you want to check out the top level folder only and omit all sub-folders,
		use the <guilabel>Only check out the top folder</guilabel> checkbox.
	</para>
	<para>
		If the project contains references to external projects which you do
		<emphasis>not</emphasis> want checked out at the same time, use the
		<guilabel>Omit externals</guilabel> checkbox.
	</para>
	<important>
		<para>
			If either of these options are checked, you will have to perform
			updates to your working copy using
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Update to Revision...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			instead of
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Update</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			The standard update will include all sub-folders and all externals.
		</para>
	</important>
	<para>
		It is recommended that you check out only the <literal>trunk</literal> part of the
		directory tree. If you specify the parent path of the
		directory tree in the URL then you might end up with a full
		hard disk since you will get a copy of the entire repository tree
		including every branch and tag of your project!
	</para>
	<tip>
		<title>Exporting</title>
		<indexterm>
			<primary>export</primary>
		</indexterm>
		<para>
			Sometimes you may want a copy without any of those
			<filename>.svn</filename> directories, e.g. to create a zipped
			tarball of your source. Instead of making a copy and then delete
			all those <filename>.svn</filename> directories manually,
			TortoiseSVN offers the command
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>TortoiseSVN</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Export...</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>.
			If you execute this command
			on your working copy you'll be asked for a place to save the
			<literal>clean</literal> working copy without the
			<filename>.svn</filename>
			folders. Also, you can specify if you want to export 
			<emphasis>all</emphasis> files or just the versioned files.
		</para>
		<para>
			Another way to do an export is by right-dragging a working copy
			folder to another location and choose
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Subversion export here</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
			or 
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Context Menu</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Subversion export all here</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice>
		</para>
	</tip>
</sect1>
