<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect2 SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<sect2 id="tsvn-dug-settings-revgraph">
  <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSREVGRAPH"?>
  <title>Revision Graph Settings</title>
  <para>
    <figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-revgraph">
      <title>The Settings Dialog, Revision Graph Page</title>
      <graphic fileref="../images/SettingsRevGraph.png"/>
    </figure>
  </para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Classification Patterns</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The revision graph attempts to show a clearer picture
          of your repository structure by distinguishing between
          trunk, branches and tags. As there is no such classification
          built into Subversion, this information is extracted from
          the path names. The default settings assume that you use
          the conventional English names as suggested in the Subversion
          documentation, but of course your usage may vary.
        </para>
        <para>
          Specify the patterns used to recognise these paths in the
          three boxes provided. The patterns will be matched case-insensitively,
          but you must specify them in lower case. Wild cards
          <literal>*</literal> and <literal>?</literal> will work
          as usual, and you can use <literal>;</literal> to separate
          multiple patterns. Do not include any extra white space
          as it will be included in the matching specification.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Modify Colors</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Colors are used in the revision graph to indicate the node
          type, i.e. whether a node is added, deleted, renamed.
          In order to help pick out node classifications,
          you can allow the revision graph to blend colors to
          give an indication of both node type and classification.
          If the box is checked, blending is used. If the box is
          unchecked, color is used to indicate node type only.
          Use the color selection dialog to allocate the
          specific colors used.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <sect3 id="tsvn-dug-settings-revgraph-colors">
    <?dbhh topicname="HIDD_SETTINGSREVGRAPHCOLORS"?>
    <title>Revision Graph Colors</title>
    <para>
      <figure id="tsvn-dug-settings-dia-revgraph-colors">
        <title>The Settings Dialog, Revision Graph Colors Page</title>
        <graphic fileref="../images/SettingsRevGraphColors.png"/>
      </figure>
      This page allows you to configure the colors used. Note that the
      color specified here is the solid color. Most nodes are colored
      using a blend of the node type color, the background color and
      optionally the classification color.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Deleted Node</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Items which have been deleted and not copied
            anywhere else in the same revision.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Added Node</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Items newly added, or copied (add with history).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Renamed Node</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Items deleted from one location and added in another
            in the same revision.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Modified Node</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Simple modifications without any add or delete.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unchanged Node</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            May be used to show the revision used as the source
            of a copy, even when no change (to the item being graphed)
            took place in that revision.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>HEAD node</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Current HEAD revision in the repository.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>WC Node</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you opt to show an extra node for your modified working copy,
            attached to its last-commit revision on the graph,
            use this color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>WC Node Border</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you opt to show whether the working copy is modified,
            use this color border on the WC node when modifications
            are found.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Tag Nodes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Nodes classified as tags may be blended with this color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Trunk Nodes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Nodes classified as trunk may be blended with this color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Folded Tag Markers</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you use tag folding to save space, tags are marked
            on the copy source using a block in this color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Selected Node Markers</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When you left click on a node to select it, the marker
            used to indicate selection is a block in this color.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stripes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These colors are used when the graph is split into sub-trees
            and the background is colored in alternating stripes to help
            pick out the separate trees.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
