<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix SYSTEM "../../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<appendix id="tsvn-ssh-publickeyauth">
	<title>SVN+SSH+public key authentication on Windows Box as server</title>
	<simplesect>
		<para>
			This walkthrough on getting SVN+SSH up and running on a 
			Windows Box was provided by Thorsten Müller. Thanks!
		</para>
	</simplesect>
	<sect1 id="tsvn-ssh-publickeyauthwalkthrough">
		<title>Walkthrough</title>
		<para>
			I just want to provide my solution to the community since 
			I have found out that there might be many people struggling 
			with the same issue.		
		</para>
		<para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Server: Install Cygwin SSH daemon as described here: 
						<ulink url="http://pigtail.net/LRP/printsrv/cygwin-sshd.html">
							<citetitle>http://pigtail.net/LRP/printsrv/cygwin-sshd.html</citetitle>
						</ulink>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Install SVN on the server (as described in the Subversion doku)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Server: Create an account (for instance "SVNuser") 
						which you will later use for logging in. Check 
						that the user permissions are sufficient to read 
						and write your SVN repository directory on the server.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Server (if not already done): Open Cygwin console and run 
						<screen>
mkpasswd -l > /etc/passwd
						</screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Client: Download PuTTY and PuTTYgen 
						<ulink url="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/download.html">
							<citetitle>http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/download.html</citetitle>
						</ulink>
						and place it in a directory which is part of 
						the PATH, for instance <filename>C:\Windows</filename>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Client: Create a key pair with PuTTYgen an save the keys.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Transfer the public key to the server file: <filename>/home/&lt;svnuser&gt;/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Create a PuTTY session for loggin in to the server as described here:
						<xref linkend="tsvn-ssh-howto" />
						Do not forget to activate auto login, i.e. set the user name.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Test whether you can log in to the server with the key.
						Server: If that works you might want to disable 
						password authentication for SSH by editing 
						<filename>/etc/sshd_config</filename>. Change/edit 
						lines as follows (and restart SSH service afterwards):
						<screen>
PubkeyAuthentication yes
PasswordAuthentication no
PermitEmptyPasswords no
ChallengeResponseAuthentication no
						</screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Server: Modify <filename>/home/&lt;svnuser&gt;/.ssh/authorized_keys</filename>
						as follows. Note that every user which is supposed 
						to use SVN uses the same login but a different 
						key, thus you have to add one line for every user/key.
					</para>
					<para>
						Note: This is all on one very long line.
						<screen>
command="svnserve -t -r c:/mySVNroot/ --tunnel-user=&lt;SVNuser&gt;",no-port-forwarding,no-agent-forwarding,no-X11-forwarding,no-pty ssh-rsa &lt;thePublicKey&gt; &lt;publicKeyComment&gt;
						</screen>
						The trick here is to use the slash instead of backslash to specifiy the SVN repository root:
						<screen>
-r c:/mySVNroot
						</screen>
						Another important thing is --tunnel-user=&lt;SVNuser&gt;.
						Since all users later will do a SSH login with 
						the same login name (but different keys) you 
						have to map each key to a SVN user - remember 
						that SVN maintains its own users/userrights.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Client: Access the repository with a URL like:
						<screen>
svn+ssh://&lt;PuTTYSessionName&gt; /&lt;MyRepository&gt;/trunk
						</screen>
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			In various documentations and news group postings you will 
			read that the URL has to contain the real path on the 
			server. But this is not neccessary if the -r parameter was 
			set correctly, see 10. I swear, for me it works fine.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</appendix>
