<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../dtd/dblite.dtd">
<chapter id="qs-introduction">
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<sect1 id="qs-intro-about">
		<title>What is this Guide For?</title>
		<para>
			This guide is aimed at people who would like to find out what
			TortoiseSVN is all about and give it a test drive. It explains
			how to install TortoiseSVN and set up a local repository, and
			it walks you through the most commonly used operations.
		</para>
		<para>
			Naturally it doesn't explain everything - this is just the Quick
			Start Guide after all. Once you are up and running you should take
			the time to read the main TortoiseSVN user guide, which takes you
			through things in much more detail. It also explains more about
			setting up a proper Subversion server.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="qs-intro-install">
		<title>Installing TortoiseSVN</title>
		<sect2>
			<title>System requirements</title>
			<para>
				TortoiseSVN runs on Windows XP or higher and is available in both
				32 bit and 64 bit flavours.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
			<title>Installation</title>
			<indexterm>
				<primary>install</primary>
			</indexterm>
			<para>
				TortoiseSVN comes with an easy to use installer. Double click on
				the installer file and follow the instructions. The installer
				will take care of the rest. 
			</para>
			<important>
				<para>
					You need Administrator privileges to install TortoiseSVN.
				</para>
			</important>
			<para>
				Language packs are available which translate the TOrtoiseSVN
				user interface into many different languages. Please check the
				main user guide for more information on how to install these.
			</para>
			<para>
				If you encounter any problems during or after installing
				TortoiseSVN please refer to our online FAQ at
				<ulink url="http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/faq.html">
					<citetitle>http://tortoisesvn.tigris.org/faq.html</citetitle>
				</ulink>
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
<!--
local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
